<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Data Science PD newsletter</title>
<link>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/</link>
<atom:link href="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>A newsletter to share professional development tips for data scientists in the NHS
</description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.553</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2024 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Professional Development Newsletter April 2024</title>
  <dc:creator>Jennifer Struthers, Giulia Mantovani, Harriet Sands</dc:creator>
  <link>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_04/newsletter.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/images/banner_april.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Welcome to the latest Professional Development newsletter, brought to you by the Data Science Professional Development Functional Team.</p>
<p>The newsletter team are always happy to receive constructive feedback, and we invite you to send us any contributions you may have.</p>
<p>There are some legacy NHS Digital items which we have identified with❗</p>
<p>If you cannot access something of interest to you, please <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new" target="_blank">reach out</a>.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading! – PD newsletter team</p>
<section id="highlights" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Highlights</h1>
</section>
<section id="now-accessible-to-all" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="now-accessible-to-all">Now Accessible to All!</h3>
<p>After trialing the use of the <a href="https://github.com/NHSDigital" target="_blank">NHS Digital GitHub</a> to aid in the creation of the newsletter, it has now been officially moved to the publically accessible <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland" target="_blank">NHS England GitHub</a>.</p>
<p>We strongly encourage contributions to the newsletter from all our colleagues, which can be submitted through <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" target="_blank">clicking here</a> or any of the “Contribute” buttons around the site.</p>
</section>
<section id="mentoring-scheme-expression-of-interest" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="mentoring-scheme-expression-of-interest">Mentoring Scheme Expression of Interest</h3>
<p>The Professional Development Function Team are investigating the interest in starting up a Mentorship Scheme between senior and junior NHS Data Science colleagues.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.southampton.ac.uk/professional-development/mentoring/benefits-of-a-mentoring-relationship.page" target="_blank">Mentorship benefits both parties</a>: mentees are provided with guidance from someone who has once been in their shoes and mentors gain insights from a new perspective, and gain experience in staff management and development. If you are interested in becoming a mentor <strong>and/or</strong> mentee, please fill out the <a href="https://forms.office.com/pages/responsepage.aspx?id=slTDN7CF9UeyIge0jXdO45Vp0C6IOYJOjBrGZlr3xANUMkRSNTg1UElOVUJXRzJaS1VGQklPMUY1Ti4u" target="_blank">expression of interest form</a>.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="events" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Events</h1>
</section>
<p>Lots of exciting things coming up! See the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/calendars" target="_blank">full calendar here</a>❗, and a small selection below.</p>
<section id="hdr-uk-advanced-computer-science-summit-ai-and-healthcare" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="hdr-uk-advanced-computer-science-summit-ai-and-healthcare"><a href="https://www.hdruk.ac.uk/events/hdr-uk-advanced-computer-science-summit-ai-and-healthcare/" target="_blank">HDR UK Advanced Computer Science Summit: AI and Healthcare</a></h3>
<p><strong>24 April 2024, 10:00AM - 3:30PM, Online</strong></p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.hdruk.ac.uk/events/hdr-uk-advanced-computer-science-summit-ai-and-healthcare/" target="_blank">HDR UK Advanced Computer Science Summit: AI and Healthcare</a> aims to anticipate advances in technologies that are on the horizon and discuss the impact these may have on health data research.</p>
<p>Cool speakers include but are not limited to:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/elham-kashefi-76b9286/">Elham Kashefi</a> (Chief Scientist for the <a href="https://www.nqcc.ac.uk/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Press-release-Announcement-of-the-appointment-of-the-Chief-Scientist-for-the-NQCC.pdf">UK’s National Quantum Computing Centre</a> will discuss quantum computation)</li>
<li><a href="https://profiles.ucl.ac.uk/78197-honghan-wu">Honghan Wu</a> (Associate Professor at the Institute of Health Informatics at UCL will lead on NLP and using text technologies and Knowledge Graph techniques to analyze health data)</li>
<li><a href="https://www.ed.ac.uk/profile/dr-william-whiteley">William Whiteley</a> (Professor of Neurology and Epidemiology at the University of Edinburgh will discuss replicating RCTs by use of data at large scale)</li>
<li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/mobuolafoluwa-onayade/">Mobuolafoluwa Onayade</a> (Health Data Scientist and Analyst at Swansea University will be presenting on The use of Causal Machine Learning (CausalML) as an upgrade to Traditional Machine Learning)</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="the-turing-roche-knowledge-share-series-fairness-in-ai-for-health" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-turing-roche-knowledge-share-series-fairness-in-ai-for-health"><a href="https://www.turing.ac.uk/events/turing-roche-knowledge-share-series-fairness-ai-health">The Turing-Roche Knowledge Share Series: Fairness in AI for Health</a></h3>
<p><strong>Tuesday 30th April, 3-4pm, Online</strong></p>
<p>Join the Turing-Roche Partnership’s virtual event series for partnership updates, knowledge sharing and new perspectives. This event will explore the theme of fairness in AI, with relation to health, and hear from Leandra Bräuninger, a PhD student at University College London and Adarsh Srivastava, Head of Data and Analytics Quality Assurance at Roche.</p>
</section>
<section id="digital-footprints-2024" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="digital-footprints-2024"><a href="https://digifootprints.co.uk/digital-footprints-2024/" target="_blank">Digital Footprints 2024</a></h3>
<p><strong>Wednesday 8th May 1pm – Thursday 9th May 4pm, University of Bristol</strong></p>
<p>Focusing on digital footprints data for social impact, inviting innovative research that harnesses the potential of these novel datasets to address pressing societal challenges and drive positive change. The conference is organised by Turing Novel Data Linkage for Health and Wellbeing Interest Group.</p>
<p><em>Please note attendance of the conference is subject to a £50 fee.</em></p>
</section>
<section id="data-science-festival-mayday-2024" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-science-festival-mayday-2024"><a href="https://datasciencefestival.com/event/mayday-2024/" target="_blank">Data Science Festival MayDay 2024</a></h3>
<p><strong>Saturday 18th May, 9-6pm, CodeNode, London</strong></p>
<p>Enter the ballot for a chance to grab a <em>free</em> ticket to this years’ Data Science Festival, hosted in London. Many speakers and sessions to be announced, but already lined up are talks on Gender Bias in Machine Learning and Leveraging GANs for Building Synthetic Data.</p>
</section>
<section id="dark-data---data-ethics-and-society-reading-group" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="dark-data---data-ethics-and-society-reading-group"><a href="https://www.tickettailor.com/events/dataethics/1193123/r/nhs" target="_blank">Dark Data - Data Ethics and Society Reading Group</a></h3>
<p><strong>Tuesday 4th June, 1-2pm, Online (Teams)</strong></p>
<p>Join the Public Sector Data Ethics &amp; Society Reading Group to discuss David Hand’s book ‘Dark Data’. <a href="https://www.tickettailor.com/events/dataethics/1193123/r/nhs" target="_blank">Sign up now to reserve your spot</a> (and receive details of the 40% discount off the paperback we’ve scooped😎).</p>
<hr>
<p>See more future events on our <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Data+Science+Events" target="_blank">confluence calendar</a>❗</p>
<p>Know of any events we should feature next month? Let us know by clicking the “Contribute” button, or <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="knowledge-sharing" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Knowledge Sharing</h1>
</section>
<section id="data-science-discussions" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-science-discussions">Data Science Discussions</h3>
<center>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_04/DS_Discussion.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Data Scientists discussing a fun topic over coffee, building relationships and expanding their knowledge base</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</center>
<p>On Thursday 11th April we had our first Data Science discussion, hosted by Will Poulett. Data Science Discussions are a new event, focussed on peer to peer discussions on a broad range of Data Science topics. For this discussion Will asked everyone attending to research a future application of AI that interested them, and also consider how it could be later applied to healthcare. The discussion began with Will presenting his case: <a href="https://www.projectceti.org/" target="_blank">Project CETI</a>, who are applying advanced machine learning and state-of-the-art robotics to listen to and translate the communication of sperm whales. Check out his slide deck <a href="https://nhs.sharepoint.com/:f:/r/sites/msteams_2768a1/Shared%20Documents/FT%20-%20Professional%20Development/PD%20Events/Data%20Science%20Discussions?csf=1&amp;web=1&amp;e=Tbm3Gq" target="_blank">here</a>. We then broke up into smaller groups to further discuss his case and our own.</p>
<p>The Professional Development Functional Team hope to hold Data Science Discussions monthly. If you have an area of Data Science you’re interested in sharing, and encouraging others to look into too, please <a href="mailto:datascience@nhs.net">contact us</a> to host a session! Most of the session is held in break out rooms, and so all you need to do is spark discussion.</p>
</section>
<section id="rap-drop-in-sessions-now-on-tuesdays" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="rap-drop-in-sessions-now-on-tuesdays">RAP Drop In Sessions (Now on Tuesdays)</h3>
<p>The RAP Squad hold a <a href="https://teams.microsoft.com/l/meetup-join/19:meeting_NGE5Mjc5ZGQtYjJkZi00OGQ4LWJmYmMtOGIxYzI3NWQ3NWZi@thread.v2/0?context=%7B%22Tid%22:%2237c354b2-85b0-47f5-b222-07b48d774ee3%22,%22Oid%22:%226a6e419b-5da0-48cb-854e-e7cca39c57e2%22%7D" target="_blank">weekly drop in session on Teams</a>,<strong>Tuesdays 10-11am</strong>, for anything and all things RAP (Reproducibile Analytical Pipelines). Come along to ask questions, get tips, or share instances of best practice in your team!</p>
<p>Check out the <a href="https://nhsdigital.github.io/rap-community-of-practice/?utm_source=p_d_newsletter&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=homepage">RAP Community of Practice website</a> to learn more, including <a href="https://nhsdigital.github.io/rap-community-of-practice/introduction_to_RAP/gov-policy-on-rap/?utm_source=p_d_newsletter&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=gov_policy">information on what the government has been saying about RAP</a> (spoiler: it’s fast becoming the required way of working with data).</p>
<hr>
<p>Stay tuned for an update on what seminars &amp; show and tells will look like in the new team. Please bear with us as it is likely to be a learning process! Contact <a href="mailto:amelia.noonan1@nhs.net">Mia Noonan</a> for more information.</p>
</section>
<section id="training-opportunities" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Training Opportunities</h1>
</section>
<section id="the-turing-way-book-dash" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-turing-way-book-dash">The Turing Way Book Dash</h3>
<p><a href="https://the-turing-way.netlify.app/community-handbook/bookdash/bookdash-events.html"><strong>The Turing Way Book Dash</strong></a> is a collaborative event where you’ll work with others to add to and improve <strong>The Turing Way book</strong> and become a part of its community.</p>
<p>The online contribution sessions (collaborative co-working format) and the social networking session will take place from <strong>3 to 6 June 2024</strong>, and two community share-out events on <strong>7 June 2024</strong>. <a href="https://the-turing-way.netlify.app/community-handbook/bookdash/bookdash-events">See details</a>. There may also be an opportunity to join an in-person hub in your area - please indicate your interest in the application.</p>
<p><strong>Application</strong> <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1FdrlFh_4yw7XsqoG-yQt8zbEH9J8wHVhKl3ZfNz_NBk/edit">Please see the application form here</a>. Submission deadline is <strong>Friday 26th April 2024</strong> and the application form may take around 30 minutes to complete.</p>
<p><strong>Who should apply?</strong> Everyone that has expertise that The Turing Way project can benefit from. The skills and contributions that they’re looking for include, but are not limited to:</p>
<ul>
<li>Tools, methods, and case studies from reproducibility in Data Science 🛠️</li>
<li>Science communication skills: skills in writing, editing, and/or exciting interactive communications 📝</li>
<li>Project design and management skills 📊</li>
<li>Approaches and principles for collaboration in data science 🤝</li>
<li>Collaboratively writing new chapters 📝</li>
<li>Reviewing others’ contributions or editing the current chapters 📋</li>
<li>Updating how the book looks online (e.g., website design, CSS, logos, layout) 🖥️</li>
<li>Documenting other contributions as illustrations or stories 📸</li>
</ul>
<p>Participants will be expected to attend at least one co-working session (2.5 hours each) per day virtually.</p>
<hr>
<p>Check out all the resources in the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Training+Brochure" target="_blank">Training Brochure</a> ❗ Can you spot something missing? <a href="mailto:datascience@nhs.net">Contact us</a>!</p>
</section>
<section id="need-a-quick-break" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Need a Quick Break?</h1>
</section>
<p><a href="https://mywordle.strivemath.com/?word=mivuj">How many tries will it take you?</a></p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<p><a href="https://forms.office.com/e/JJsmgPmVVJ" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-success btn-lg">Subscribe (nhs.net login)</a><a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">Contribute</a><a href="./newsletter.pdf" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">PDF Version</a></p>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>newsletter</category>
  <category>compentency</category>
  <guid>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_04/newsletter.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Professional Development Newsletter March 2024</title>
  <dc:creator>Jennifer Struthers, Giulia Mantovani</dc:creator>
  <link>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_03/newsletter.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/images/banner_march.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Welcome to the latest Professional Development newsletter, brought to you by the Data Science skilled team Professional Development Functional Group.</p>
<p>The newsletter team are always happy to receive constructive feedback, and we invite you to send us any contributions you may have.</p>
<p>There are some legacy NHS Digital items which we have identified with❗</p>
<p>If you cannot access something of interest to you, please <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new" target="_blank">reach out</a>.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading! – PD newsletter team</p>
<section id="highlights" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Highlights</h1>
</section>
<section id="leadership-competency-framework" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="leadership-competency-framework">Leadership Competency Framework</h3>
<p>NHS England has <a href="https://www.england.nhs.uk/leaders/" target="_blank">published the leadership competency framework</a> which comprises a set of leadership competencies incorporating the skills, values and behaviours required in NHS board roles and establishes what good looks like in leadership terms, providing a new and consistent national standard of leadership. Many of us are very far from those positions, but it does not hurt to aim high. But also, it is good to know what is expected of our leaders. These are the six leadership competency domains that you can learn about reading the framework:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Driving high-quality and sustainable outcomes</li>
<li>Setting strategy and delivering long-term transformation</li>
<li>Promoting equality and inclusion, and reducing health and workforce inequalities</li>
<li>Providing robust governance and assurance</li>
<li>Creating a compassionate, just and positive culture</li>
<li>Building a trusted relationship with partners and communities</li>
</ol>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="events" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Events</h1>
</section>
<p>Lots of exciting things coming up! See the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/calendars" target="_blank">full calendar here</a>❗, and a small selection below.</p>
<section id="ai-uk-fringe-events" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ai-uk-fringe-events"><a href="https://ai-uk.turing.ac.uk/fringe-events/" target="_blank">AI UK Fringe Events</a></h3>
<p><strong>4th-29th March, various times, In person across the UK and online</strong></p>
<p>At a series of events AI UK Fringe brings together leaders in academia from across the UK’s AI ecosystem to demonstrate, exhibit and update on their ground-breaking work. Attendees at our AI UK Fringe events will be able to network with local colleagues and peers and take part in specialist debates and roundtables relevant to their regions. Browse this year’s events below and make sure to register your place.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-person-centred-healthcare-record---pipe-dream-or-inevitability" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-person-centred-healthcare-record---pipe-dream-or-inevitability"><a href="https://www.tickettailor.com/events/publicdigital/1167958?mc_cid=c757cfd211&amp;mc_eid=f15dd17114" target="_blank">The person-centred healthcare record - pipe dream or inevitability?</a></h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 18th April, 6-7:30pm, in person in London or on Zoom</strong></p>
<p>Successive administrations have tried and failed to implement a person-centred healthcare record, but can it be done? Join us to hear four digital healthcare experts debate the question of how interoperable access to patient data could or should be delivered, looking at political, commercial, and technical considerations.</p>
</section>
<section id="lunch-and-learn" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="lunch-and-learn">Lunch and Learn</h3>
<p><strong>Monday 22nd April, 12-1pm, Wellington Place: Town Hall Collaboration Space</strong></p>
<p>Andy Jackson has recently released news of new lunch and learn seminars held in person in Leeds. The next one will feature a guest speaker from ONS - Population Demographics. Watch your email for more information.</p>
</section>
<section id="digital-footprints-2024" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="digital-footprints-2024"><a href="https://digifootprints.co.uk/digital-footprints-2024/" target="_blank">Digital Footprints 2024</a></h3>
<p><strong>Wednesday 8th May 1pm – Thursday 9th May 4pm, University of Bristol</strong></p>
<p>Focusing on digital footprints data for social impact, inviting innovative research that harnesses the potential of these novel datasets to address pressing societal challenges and drive positive change. The conference is organised by Turing Novel Data Linkage for Health and Wellbeing Interest Group.</p>
<p><em>Please note attendance of the conference is subject to a £50 fee.</em></p>
</section>
<section id="data-science-festival-mayday-2024" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-science-festival-mayday-2024"><a href="https://datasciencefestival.com/event/mayday-2024/" target="_blank">Data Science Festival MayDay 2024</a></h3>
<p><strong>Saturday 18th May, 9-6pm, CodeNode, London</strong></p>
<p>Enter the ballot for achance to grab a <em>free</em> ticket to this years’ Data Science Festival, hosted in London. Many speakers and sessions to be announced, but already lined up are talks on Gender Bias in Machine Learning and Leveraging GANs for Building Synthetic Data.</p>
</section>
<section id="dark-data---data-ethics-and-society-reading-group" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="dark-data---data-ethics-and-society-reading-group"><a href="https://www.tickettailor.com/events/dataethics/1193123/r/nhs" target="_blank">Dark Data - Data Ethics and Society Reading Group</a></h3>
<p><strong>Tuesday 4th June, 1-2pm, Online (Teams)</strong></p>
<p>Join the Public Sector Data Ethics &amp; Society Reading Group to discuss David Hand’s book ‘Dark Data’. <a href="https://www.tickettailor.com/events/dataethics/1193123/r/nhs" target="_blank">Sign up now to reserve your spot</a> (and receive details of the 40% discount off the paperback we’ve scooped😎).</p>
<hr>
<p>See more future events on our <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Data+Science+Events" target="_blank">confluence calendar</a>❗</p>
<p>Know of any events we should feature next month? Let us know by clicking the “Contribute” button, or <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="knowledge-sharing" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Knowledge Sharing</h1>
</section>
<section id="generative-ai-in-a-research-context" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="generative-ai-in-a-research-context">Generative AI in a research context</h3>
<p>Generative AI is increasingly used to draft, edit, annotate and debug code. It’s not just industry software developers who are taking advantage of the tools it has to offer. Those who develop and use software for academic research are benefitting from them too. So how do you make the best use of generative AI for coding in a research context? As software engineers with The Alan Turing Institute’s <a href="https://www.turing.ac.uk/work-turing/research/research-engineering-group" target="_blank">Research Engineering Group</a> (REG) and <a href="https://www.turing.ac.uk/work-turing/studentships/enrichment" target="_blank">PhD Enrichment scheme</a>, we’ve been asking ourselves just this question. <a href="https://www.turing.ac.uk/blog/using-generative-ai-write-code-guide-researchers" target="_blank">Here</a>, we share our thoughts, along with some tips for researchers.</p>
</section>
<section id="github-vs-gitlab-terminology-differences" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="github-vs-gitlab-terminology-differences"><a href="https://nhsdigital.github.io/rap-community-of-practice/training_resources/git/github_gitlab_terminology/?utm_source=p_d_newsletter&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=github_gitlab" target="_blank">GitHub vs Gitlab Terminology Differences</a></h3>
<p>GitHub and GitLab are two very similar yet different platforms and that can lead to some confusion between teams who are familiar with one but not the other when some key pieces of terminology have been changed slightly between them. The RAP Community of Pracice have recently released a quick summary of some of these terminology differences. Read over this and you’ll never get your MRs and PRs mixed up again!</p>
<hr>
<p>Stay tuned for an update on what seminars &amp; show and tells will look like in the new team. Please bear with us as it is likely to be a learning process! Contact <a href="mailto:amelia.noonan1@nhs.net">Mia Noonan</a> for more information..</p>
</section>
<section id="training-opportunities" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Training Opportunities</h1>
</section>
<section id="pluralsight-access" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pluralsight-access"><a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Pluralsight+Access" target="_blank">Pluralsight Access</a></h3>
<p>After the reinstation of the Pluralsight license, a confluence page on how to access it (whether or not you had access before) has been set up. Check it out to gain access to all of the Pluralsight training resources again.</p>
<hr>
<p>Check out all the resources in the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Training+Brochure" target="_blank">Training Brochure</a>! Can you spot something missing? <a href="mailto:datascience@nhs.net">Contact us</a>!</p>
</section>
<section id="need-a-quick-break" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Need a Quick Break?</h1>
</section>
<p><a href="https://mywordle.strivemath.com/?word=icuhw" target="_blank">How many tries will it take you?</a></p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<p><a href="https://forms.office.com/e/JJsmgPmVVJ" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-success btn-lg">Subscribe (nhs.net login)</a><a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">Contribute</a><a href="./newsletter.pdf" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">PDF Version</a></p>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>newsletter</category>
  <category>leadership</category>
  <guid>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_03/newsletter.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Professional Development Newsletter February 2024</title>
  <dc:creator>Harriet Sands and Jennifer Struthers</dc:creator>
  <link>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_02/newsletter.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/images/banner_feb.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Welcome to the latest Professional Development newsletter, brought to you by the Data Science skilled team Professional Development Capability team <strong>- now in a new format!</strong></p>
<p>The newsletter team are always happy to receive constructive feedback, and we invite you to send us any contributions you may have.</p>
<p>There are some legacy NHS Digital items which we have identified with❗</p>
<p>If you cannot access something of interest to you, please <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new" target="_blank">reach out</a>.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading! – PD newsletter team</p>
<section id="highlights" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Highlights</h1>
</section>
<section id="your-professional-development---job-descriptions" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="your-professional-development---job-descriptions"><u><strong>Your Professional Development</strong> - Job Descriptions </u></h4>
<p>When preparing for future career opportunities here at NHSE, it’s a good idea to understand the job descriptions for each role you hope to apply for.</p>
<p>Take a look at the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Data+Science+Job+Descriptions" target="_blank">current data science job descriptions saved on Confluence</a> which detail the requirements and expectations for the various roles we may look to recruit for in the team. These will be used for recruitment in the immediate future.</p>
<p>Familiarising yourself with these specifications can help you shape your professional development plans and tailor the training opportunities you seek out.</p>
<p>Please note that in the longer term these job descriptions may change to be aligned to the <a href="https://future.nhs.uk/DataAnalytics/view?objectID=31311216">National Competency Framework</a> and this will be communicated to the team.</p>
</section>
<section id="health-and-care-analytics-conference-2024---call-for-abstracts" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="health-and-care-analytics-conference-2024---call-for-abstracts"><u><strong>Health and Care Analytics Conference 2024</strong> - Call for Abstracts</u></h4>
<p>Have some interesting work to share? The <a href="https://haca-conference.nhs.uk/" target="_blank">HACA Conference 2024</a> is officially accepting applications to present (in the form of a talk or poster) at the 2024 conference, hosted 23rd-24th July at Telford International Centre. The deadline to submit is <strong>Thursday February 29th 2024</strong>. Check out the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/HACA+2024" target="_blank">HACA 2024 Confluence page</a>❗ to see the steps and track submissions.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="events" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Events</h1>
</section>
<p>Lots of exciting things coming up! See the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/calendars" target="_blank">full calendar here</a>❗</p>
<section id="severe-mental-illness-physical-disease" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="severe-mental-illness-physical-disease"><a href="https://www.hdruk.ac.uk/events/severe-mental-illness-and-physical-disease/" target="_blank">Severe Mental Illness &amp; Physical Disease</a></h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 29th February 10:00 - 13:00, Online</strong></p>
<p>Hosted by researchers at the Usher Institute, The University of Edinburgh, with contributions from DataMind, the Health Data Research Hub for Mental Health we will hear from researchers working on projects relating to severe mental illness and receipt of cardiovascular care as well as people with lived experience, clinicians and public health and government representatives.</p>
</section>
<section id="making-a-difference-using-data-to-improve-care" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="making-a-difference-using-data-to-improve-care"><a href="event link" target="_blank">Making a difference: Using Data to Improve Care</a></h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 29th February 2024 13:00 - 16:00, Online</strong></p>
<p>Join us for the HDR UK Midlands &amp; Health Innovation East Midlands Insight Sharing Webinar. Highlights include: Dementia and the correlation with cardiovascular diseases, Leveraging administrative healthcare data to enhance drug approval in rare disease, EU data infrastructure for Rare Disease.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-career-live" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-career-live"><a href="https://nhsengland.sharepoint.com/sites/thehub/SitePages/Help-us-inspire-students-to-join-the-NHS.aspx" target="_blank">What Career? Live</a></h3>
<p><strong>Friday 1st and Saturday 2nd March, NEC Birmingham</strong></p>
<p>NHS Health Careers is looking for people to help inspire students to join the NHS by attending this national careers event. If you’re interested, <a href="mailto:laura.monks2@nhs.net">email Laura Monks</a> by <strong>Monday 26th February</strong> .</p>
</section>
<section id="policy-making-for-the-age-of-ai" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="policy-making-for-the-age-of-ai"><a href="https://thestrandgroup.kcl.ac.uk/event/policy-making-for-the-age-of-ai/" target="_blank">Policy Making for the Age of AI</a></h3>
<p><strong>Wednesday 6th March, 18:30, King’s College London</strong></p>
<p>The sixty-eigth Strand Group will take place at 18.30 on Wednesday 6th March 2024 when Sarah Munby, Permanent Secretary of the Department for Science, Innovation and Technology, will give her second lecture as Visiting Professor on ‘Policy Making in the Age of AI.’</p>
</section>
<section id="the-politics-and-philosophy-of-ai" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-politics-and-philosophy-of-ai"><a href="https://www.lse.ac.uk/Events/2024/03/202403191830/ai" target="_blank">The politics and philosophy of AI</a></h3>
<p><strong>Tuesday 19th March 2024 18:30 to 20:00, London School of Economics &amp; Online</strong></p>
<p>As artificial intelligence (AI) moves beyond the realm of science fiction, it is already having a profound impact on our economies, societies and politics. To make sense of the transformative power and disruptive potential of AI, we are joined by thinkers at the cutting edge of the technological frontier for an in-depth discussion of its multifaceted impact. Speakers include the ‘godfather of AI’, Geoffrey Hinton; Kate Vredenburgh, Assistant Professor in the Department of Philosophy, Logic and Scientific Method at LSE and Robin Archer, the Director of the postgraduate programme in political sociology and the Director of the Ralph Miliband Programme at LSE.</p>
</section>
<section id="digital-footprints-2024" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="digital-footprints-2024"><a href="https://digifootprints.co.uk/digital-footprints-2024/" target="_blank">Digital Footprints 2024</a></h3>
<p><strong>Wednesday 8th May 1pm – Thursday 9th May 4pm, University of Bristol</strong></p>
<p>Focusing on digital footprints data for social impact, inviting innovative research that harnesses the potential of these novel datasets to address pressing societal challenges and drive positive change. The conference is organised by Turing Novel Data Linkage for Health and Wellbeing Interest Group.</p>
<p><em>Please note attendance of the conference is subject to a £50 fee.</em></p>
<hr>
<p>See more future events on our <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Events+calendar" target="_blank">confluence calendar</a>❗</p>
<p>Know of any events we should feature next month? Let us know by clicking the “Contribute” button, or <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="knowledge-sharing" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Knowledge Sharing</h1>
</section>
<section id="refactoring-golden-rules" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="refactoring-golden-rules"><a href="https://nhsdigital.github.io/rap-community-of-practice/training_resources/refactoring-guide/?utm_source=p_d_newsletter&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=refactoring_guide" target="_blank">Refactoring Golden Rules</a></h3>
<p>Are you wondering how you can make your code faster, easier to read, and easier to reuse? Getting your code to work is just the first step! After that, you should refactor your code to make it higher quality - more efficient, more robust, more maintainable. But how do you do that? Well, you can start by reading the <a href="https://nhsdigital.github.io/rap-community-of-practice/training_resources/refactoring-guide/?utm_source=p_d_newsletter&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=refactoring_guide">refactoring golden rules</a> on the RAP Community of Practice website!</p>
<hr>
<p>Stay tuned for an update on what seminars &amp; show and tells will look like in the new team. Please bear with us as it is likely to be a learning process! Contact <a href="mailto:amelia.noonan1@nhs.net">Mia Noonan</a> for more information..</p>
</section>
<section id="training-opportunities" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Training Opportunities</h1>
</section>
<section id="applications-for-the-nihr-health-service-modelling-associates-now-open" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="applications-for-the-nihr-health-service-modelling-associates-now-open"><a href="https://sites.google.com/nihr.ac.uk/hsma" target="_blank">Applications for the NIHR Health Service Modelling Associates now open</a></h3>
<p>This free, 15-month course teaches people how to use Operational Research and Data Science techniques to improve services and aid decision making.</p>
<p>The free course requires a time commitment of one day a week for the full programme. All code in the course is in Python, though some other open-source software will be used too - but no prior experience with Python (or any programming experience at all!) is required.</p>
<p>See the <a href="https://sites.google.com/nihr.ac.uk/hsma/apply-to-become-a-hsma?authuser=0" target="_blank">FAQs</a> and direct any further questions to <a href="mailto:penchord@exeter.ac.uk">penchord@exeter.ac.uk</a> and <a href="mailto:s.j.rosser@exeter.ac.uk">s.j.rosser@exeter.ac.uk</a>.</p>
<p>Applications for the course close on the <strong>4th of March 2024</strong>, with the course beginning <strong>Monday 15th April 2024</strong>.</p>
</section>
<section id="become-a-stem-ambassador" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="become-a-stem-ambassador"><a href="https://www.stem.org.uk/stem-ambassadors/become-a-stem-ambassador" target="_blank">Become a STEM ambassador</a></h3>
<p>STEM Ambassadors help young people to understand the real world applications of their learning. Attend an <a href="https://www.eventbrite.com/e/volunteer-information-session-becoming-a-stem-ambassador-tickets-771603405557?aff=odcleoeventsincollection&amp;keep_tld=1" target="_blank">information session</a> on Thursday 22nd February to learn more.</p>
</section>
<section id="stakeholder-mapping-resources" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="stakeholder-mapping-resources"><a href="https://analysisfunction.civilservice.gov.uk/policy-store/stakeholder-mapping/" target="_blank">Stakeholder Mapping Resources</a></h3>
<p>This guidance includes a helpful template and further resources to help you map stakeholders for user engagement.</p>
</section>
<section id="pluralsight" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pluralsight"><a href="https://www.pluralsight.com/" target="_blank">Pluralsight</a></h3>
<p>Tim Roebuck <a href="https://web.yammer.com/main/org/hscic.gov.uk/threads/eyJfdHlwZSI6IlRocmVhZCIsImlkIjoiMjY2Njk0NDQ1MDQ0NTMxMiJ9?trk_copy_link=V2" target="_blank">announced</a> that following delays to resolve contractual issues for a new contract, access has been restored for existing Pluralsight users, and you should been able to continue any previous training.</p>
</section>
<section id="improve-your-markdown-by-contributing-to-the-data-science-website" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="improve-your-markdown-by-contributing-to-the-data-science-website"><a href="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience/" target="_blank">Improve your Markdown by contributing to the Data Science website!</a></h3>
<p>Ever wanted to try your hand at learning Markdown but never really found a reason? Check out this <a href="https://www.markdowntutorial.com/" target="_blank">Markdown tutorial</a> and then try your hand at it by helping improve the newly launched <a href="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience/" target="_blank">Data Science website</a>.</p>
<table class="table">
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_02/amaia_website_newsletter.png" alt="A photoshopped image of Amaia onto a WW2 propaganda poster, saying 'We Need You'" width="350"></td>
<td>We launched the prototype <a href="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience/" target="_blank">Data Science website</a> - but we need your help. <br>We need your contributions (see how to do this <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience/blob/main/CONTRIBUTE.md" target="_blank">here</a>), in particular:<br><br>- Send us a summary of your project (see <a href="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience/our_work/ds218_rap_community_of_practice/" target="_blank">this example</a>)<br>- Follow <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience/blob/main/docs/our_work/template-project.md" target="_blank">this template</a>.<br>- Contribute an article to the blog.<br>- Volunteer to pick up an <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience/issues" target="_blank">issue</a> on GitHub.<br>- Give us feedback about the <a href="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience/" target="_blank">website</a>.<br><br>With the conference season approaching, something up on the web can be useful to point people towards!<br></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Check out all the resources in the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Training+Brochure" target="_blank">Training Brochure</a>! Can you spot something missing? <a href="mailto:datascience@nhs.net">Contact us</a>!</p>
</section>
<section id="need-a-quick-break" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Need a Quick Break?</h1>
</section>
<p><a href="https://mywordle.strivemath.com/?word=zokddgesefp" target="_blank">How many tries will it take you?</a></p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<p><a href="https://forms.office.com/e/JJsmgPmVVJ" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-success btn-lg">Subscribe (nhs.net login)</a><a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">Contribute</a><a href="./newsletter.pdf" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">PDF Version</a></p>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>newsletter</category>
  <category>analytics</category>
  <guid>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_02/newsletter.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Professional Development Newsletter January 2024</title>
  <dc:creator>Harriet Sands and Harry Kelleher</dc:creator>
  <link>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_01/newsletter.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/images/banner_jan.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Welcome to the latest Professional Development newsletter, brought to you by the Data Science skilled team Professional Development Capability team.</p>
<p>The newsletter team are always happy to receive constructive feedback, and we invite you to send us any contributions you may have.</p>
<p>There are some items that are available via legacy systems available to former NHS Digital colleagues. We have marked these with❗</p>
<p>If you cannot access something of interest to you, please <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new" target="_blank">reach out</a>.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading! – PD newsletter team</p>
<section id="highlights" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Highlights</h1>
</section>
<section id="competency-framework-zooming-intodelivery" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="competency-framework-zooming-intodelivery"><u><strong>Competency Framework</strong> – zooming into…Delivery</u></h4>
<p>As we adjust to delivering in the new team structure; using potentially unfamiliar tools like Confluence, JIRA and DevOps, getting to grips with new projects and new stakeholders, it’s the perfect time to refresh our understanding of what makes good delivery.</p>
<p>Delivery is the translation of the insights we produce into actionable outcomes. Keeping a delivery-focussed mindset is key to achieve value for money and improve lives for service users. Without it, we cannot fulfil our mission to drive the digital transformation of the NHS!</p>
<p>Delivery comes in different shapes and sizes, whether it’s being accountable for your own tickets or ensuring your team is focused on the top priorities – each of us play our part.</p>
<p>Check out these top tips from our <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Data+Science+Competency+Framework" target="_blank">Competency Framework</a>❗ :</p>
<ul>
<li>Break down complex objectives into clear tasks to deliver incremental value with each iteration</li>
<li>Regularly sync-up with stakeholders to understand priorities and manage delivery expectations</li>
<li>Be a role model to others by demonstrating a focus on delivery, whilst being open to new ideas and continuous improvement</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>Check out the resources to boost your delivery skills on the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Training+Framework" target="_blank">Training Framework</a>❗and our full collection on the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Training+Brochure" target="_blank">Training Brochure</a>❗ Can you spot something missing? <a href="mailto:datascience@nhs.net">Contact us</a>!</p>
</section>
<section id="events" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Events</h1>
</section>
<p>Lots of exciting things coming up! See the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/calendars" target="_blank">full calendar here</a>❗ , and a small selection below.</p>
<section id="onshdr-health-data-science-seminars" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="onshdr-health-data-science-seminars"><a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/health-data-science-seminar-series-tickets-758986237267" target="_blank">ONS/HDR Health Data Science Seminars</a></h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 25th January, 14:00-15:30, Online</strong></p>
<p>This event, ‘Digital footprints’, will feature presentations from guest speakers: Dr Anya Skatova, Senior Research Fellow at the University of Bristol, Professor Will Dixon, Professor of Digital Epidemiology, The University of Manchester and Professor Tim Chico, Professor of Cardiovascular Medicine, from the University of Sheffield.</p>
</section>
<section id="genomics-england-research-seminars" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="genomics-england-research-seminars"><a href="https://www.genomicsengland.co.uk/events/research-seminar-january-2024" target="_blank">Genomics England Research Seminars</a></h3>
<p><strong>Tuesday 30th January, 14:00-15:00, Online</strong></p>
<p>This seminar series showcases the latest research using data from the National Genomic Research Library. Two projects will be presented: ‘Investigating microRNA-associated variation in the Epileptic Encephalopathies’ and ‘Effects of Ancestry in the 100,000 Genomes Project Cancer Pipelines’. (January is clearly Genomics month, with the <a href="https://festivalofgenomics.com/london/en/page/home" target="_blank">Festival of Genomics &amp; Biodata</a> starting tomorrow!)</p>
</section>
<section id="data-bites-48-getting-things-done-with-data-in-government---smart-data-special" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-bites-48-getting-things-done-with-data-in-government---smart-data-special"><a href="https://www.instituteforgovernment.org.uk/event/data-bites-48-getting-things-done-data-government" target="_blank">Data Bites #48: Getting things done with data in government - smart data special</a></h3>
<p><strong>Monday 26th February, 18:00-19:20, Online &amp; London</strong></p>
<p>In an exciting, quickfire format, each speaker has eight minutes to present on data in government. Next month’s speakers include Ben Goldacre among others.</p>
<hr>
<p>See more future events on our <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/calendars" target="_blank">confluence calendar</a>❗</p>
<p>Know of any events we should feature next month?Let us know by clicking the “Contribute” button, or <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="knowledge-sharing" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Knowledge Sharing</h1>
</section>
<p><strong><a href="https://future.nhs.uk/connect.ti/DataAnalytics/messageShowThread?threadid=12369486" target="_blank">Blog: Delivering user centred dashboards</a></strong></p>
<p><strong>Harry Kelleher</strong>, Lead BI Developer, shares his experience building dashboards that make a difference, and how a product thinking approach has been the key to unlocking system-wide value.</p>
<hr>
<p>Stay tuned for an update on what seminars &amp; show and tells will look like in the new team. Please bear with us as it is likely to be a learning process! Contact <a href="mailto:amelia.noonan1@nhs.net">Mia Noonan</a> for more information..</p>
<section id="training-opportunities" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Training Opportunities</h1>
</section>
<p>How much do you actually know about the NHS? Check out the <a href="https://www.kingsfund.org.uk/health-care-explained/online-course" target="_blank">The NHS explained free online course: how the health system in England really works</a>.</p>
<p>With the release of the <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/generative-ai-framework-for-hmg/generative-ai-framework-for-hmg-html" target="_blank">Generative AI Framework for HMG</a>, Civil Service Learning now includes a set of open learning relating to Generative AI, including a <a href="https://learn.civilservice.gov.uk/courses/E0nDu3fET6q3Tg5yOBFn_g" target="_blank">technical curriculum</a>, that is a helpful collection of free resources from <a href="https://www.cloudskillsboost.google/paths/183" target="_blank">Google</a>, <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/paths/copilot/" target="_blank">Microsoft</a> and <a href="https://explore.skillbuilder.aws/learn/course/external/view/elearning/17256/planning-a-generative-ai-project" target="_blank">AWS</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p>Check out all the resources in the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Training+Brochure" target="_blank">Training Brochure</a>! Can you spot something missing? Contact <a href="mailto:datascience@nhs.net">Harriet Sands</a>.</p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<p><a href="https://forms.office.com/e/JJsmgPmVVJ" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-success btn-lg">Subscribe (nhs.net login)</a><a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">Contribute</a><a href="./newsletter.pdf" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">PDF Version</a></p>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>newsletter</category>
  <category>delivery</category>
  <guid>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_01/newsletter.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
