<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Data Science PD newsletter</title>
<link>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/</link>
<atom:link href="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>A newsletter to share professional development tips and opportunities for people interested in healthcare data science
</description>
<generator>quarto-1.7.29</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Data Science Community for Health and Care Newsletter April 2025</title>
  <dc:creator>Elizabeth Kelly, Sarah Culkin</dc:creator>
  <link>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2025_04/newsletter.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/images/banner_april.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Welcome to the latest newsletter from the Data Science Community for Health and Care, brought to you by the NHS England Data Science Professional Development Functional Team.</p>
<p>The newsletter team are always happy to receive constructive feedback, and we invite you to send us any contributions you may have.</p>
<p>If you cannot access something of interest to you, please <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new" target="_blank">reach out</a>.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading! – newsletter team</p>
<section id="blowing-the-trumpet-for-data-science" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Blowing the Trumpet for Data Science</h1>
</section>
<p>Welcome to the second installment of our <strong>“Interview with a Data Scientist”</strong> series, where we explore the careers and work of the talented members of the NHS England Data Science team. We aim to showcase the fantastic individuals who contribute to the NHS England Data Science Profession and provide valuable insights for those considering a career in Data Science within the healthcare sector.</p>
<p>Our second interview is with Sarah Culkin, a chemist turned data science enthusiast.</p>
<details>
<summary>
Read more…
</summary>
<section id="how-did-you-end-up-in-data-science-at-the-nhs-what-did-you-do-before-and-what-really-sparked-your-interest-in-this-field" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-did-you-end-up-in-data-science-at-the-nhs-what-did-you-do-before-and-what-really-sparked-your-interest-in-this-field">How did you end up in data science at the NHS? What did you do before, and what really sparked your interest in this field?</h2>
<p>I studied chemistry at the University of Leeds; after my undergraduate degree I stayed at Leeds to do a PhD in organic chemistry.</p>
<p>I was researching peptides and proteins so spent quite a lot of time in a lab rather than on a computer. And more time than I would like to admit washing up glassware! But then the department bought a robot to run experiments; this was my first real experience of programming and data handling.</p>
<p>Toward the end of my PhD, I saw a job ad for the Government Operational Research Service (GORS, some would say a forerunner to Data Science). I applied and ended up placed in the Department of Health.</p>
<p>I’ve remained in the health sector and in data ever since (about 17 years) although I have moved to lots of different areas.</p>
<p>My passion for data science was sparked around 2016, and I established its small data science team in the Department of Health. I have held a range of other roles, in the Department of Health and Social Care (DHSC), NHS England and NHSX. I’ve spent time in Leeds Teaching Hospitals Trust and in a data policy role but ultimately leading a data science team is my passion.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-are-you-currently-working-on-are-there-any-projects-that-youre-particularly-excited-about-or-that-you-feel-are-making-a-real-difference-what-impact-are-you-having" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-are-you-currently-working-on-are-there-any-projects-that-youre-particularly-excited-about-or-that-you-feel-are-making-a-real-difference-what-impact-are-you-having">What are you currently working on? Are there any projects that you’re particularly excited about, or that you feel are making a real difference? What impact are you having?</h2>
<p>As deputy director of the data science team in NHS England I, sadly, no longer spend much time day-to-day involved in projects. Instead I lead the team. I spend time focusing upwards and outwards, to raise awareness of the team and bring in new work.</p>
<p>Two current areas of work that excite me:</p>
<p>Firstly, developing data science as a profession.</p>
<p>For example, we set up a PhD intern programme to link the NHS to early career researchers in academia. This programme has now been running for several years and it is highly successful (see lots more info <a href="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience/PhDInterns/">here</a>).</p>
<p>We also now look after a Data Science Masters programme. This is a great opportunity to offer advanced data science training to our colleagues.</p>
<p>I worked to develop the data science <a href="https://future.nhs.uk/DataAnalytics/view?objectID=31311216">competency frameworks</a> and more recently a continuous professional development policy. I think having a clear, fair, well-defined and well promoted profession is important.</p>
<p>More recently I have been involved in school outreach. The sessions at primary schools were particularly memorable; the questions you get asked are wild, funny and brilliant!</p>
<p>The second area that particularly excites me is shaping new work coming into the team.</p>
<p>I am particularly interested to see how data science can support digital transformation in the NHS, as well as operational decisions.</p>
<p>It is interesting to see how different teams work and how data science can help them. I help scope projects so that they meet and maybe even go beyond their needs.</p>
<p>Increasingly we are getting colleagues interested in using AI in their work and this brings new challenges, opportunities and teams to us.</p>
</section>
<section id="if-you-could-give-someone-just-starting-out-in-data-science-a-few-pieces-of-advice-what-would-they-be-and-what-resources-have-you-found-particularly-helpful-along-the-way-that-you-can-share" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="if-you-could-give-someone-just-starting-out-in-data-science-a-few-pieces-of-advice-what-would-they-be-and-what-resources-have-you-found-particularly-helpful-along-the-way-that-you-can-share">If you could give someone just starting out in data science a few pieces of advice, what would they be? And what resources have you found particularly helpful along the way that you can share?</h2>
<p>My advice for aspiring data scientists would be two things:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Get good at explaining complicated, technical, potentially quite dry subjects in a simple engaging way. Think, “can I explain what I’m doing to a 9-year-old in a way that they would understand and would also hold their attention”. Channel your inner kids TV presenter/science journalist!</li>
</ol>
<p>A good way of doing this is to find everyday analogies. Compare a project, process or problem to an everyday situation. Recent things I’ve used when trying to explain something technical have been visiting a restaurant and using an iPhone.</p>
<p>If you can help people to feel clever (rather than prioritising making yourself look clever!) they’re far more likely to engage with (and remember) what you’re trying to describe.</p>
<p>It’s very tempting when you’ve done a complicated piece of work to want to get across how hard it has been, how complicated it was. Sometimes this is needed. But, in general, seek common ground.</p>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>Make sure you really understand the fundamentals of the data science technique or the approach that you are using and its potential weak points as well as benefits, compared to others.</li>
</ol>
<p>When we can run complicated processes and code with a few clicks it’s not always necessary to engage with the underlying statistical model. But to be able to assure yourself and to help you to be able to explain it others, this understanding of the fundamentals, for me, is key. It also helps to critically appraise the next new thing when it comes out. Aim to be a cynical optimist.</p>
</section></details>

<section id="events" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Events</h1>
</section>
<p>Lots of exciting things coming up! See the <a href="https://future.nhs.uk/DataAnalytics/view?objectID=861745" target="_blank">full calendar here</a>, and a small selection below.</p>
<section id="supremacy---data-ethics-and-society-reading-group" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="supremacy---data-ethics-and-society-reading-group"><a href="https://www.tickettailor.com/events/dataethics/1549481/r/nhsteams" target="_blank">Supremacy - Data Ethics and Society Reading Group</a></h3>
<p><strong>Tuesday 29th April, 12:00-14:00, Online</strong></p>
<p>Join us at the Data Ethics &amp; Society Reading Group to discuss Supremacy by Parmy Olson.</p>
<p>We will be holding two sessions over two weeks. The sessions will each focus on a different section of the book- but if you can’t make the one you want to come to, we can still guarantee a great conversation! <a href="https://dataingovernment.blog.gov.uk/2025/02/17/data-ethics-and-society-join-the-conversation-in-2025/" target="_blank">Read more about our changes in our recent Data in Government blog post.</a></p>
<p>The event is FREE to attend, but places are limited so please sign up to reserve your spot! (Registration closes on Friday 18th April at 17:00)</p>
<p><em>Please note this event is for Public Sector workers only</em></p>
</section>
<section id="lse-the-power-of-data-ethics-politics-and-public-interest" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="lse-the-power-of-data-ethics-politics-and-public-interest"><a href="https://www.lse.ac.uk/Events/2025/05/202505081830/data-ethics-politics-and-public-interest?_gl=1*rwgszb*_gcl_au*MTc0NDU0NDcyNC4xNzM4NTkyNjk3*_ga*MjE2MDg0MDMzLjE3Mzg1OTI2OTI.*_ga_LWTEVFESYX*MTc0MDk5NDcxNS42OS4xLjE3NDA5OTgzNzQuMjkuMC4w" target="_blank">LSE: The power of data: ethics, politics, and public interest</a></h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 8th May, 18.30-20.00, In-person and online public event (Auditorium, Centre Building)</strong></p>
<p>Data profoundly influences all of our lives and the social, economic and political systems that govern them. Everywhere we turn we are creating increasing amounts of data that powers decision-making algorithms and shapes our future. It is however important to remember how partial and biased data can be given the priviledged position it has in the perception of absolute truth.</p>
<p>This event will discuss important questions around the role of data science in understanding and shaping the public interest, from access to information to civic participation and business development to democratic processes.</p>
</section>
<section id="ds-game-on-2025" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ds-game-on-2025"><a href="https://datasciencefestival.com/event/dsf-game-on-2025/" target="_blank">DS: Game On 2025</a></h3>
<p><strong>Saturday 17th May, All Day, London</strong></p>
<p>Join us for our 11th festival, DSF Game On 2025! Top tech speakers, incredible partners and a thriving community, all completely free.</p>
<p>The ballot is open for those wanting a chance to get tickets to DSF’s Game On 2025. Click through the link above to find out how to apply, and the (free) tickets to those successful will be sent out in April.</p>
<p>There will be a mixture of talks featured at the festival, covering all things data (science, engineering, etc) and at a variety of technical levels. You can view last years playlist on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLwzX3WM0AfxopbhVhGCA373Xk-7wNhLfq" target="_blank">YouTube here</a> to get an idea of the talks at the events.</p>
</section>
<section id="pint-of-science-2025" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pint-of-science-2025"><a href="https://www.turing.ac.uk/events/pint-science-2025" target="_blank">Pint of Science 2025</a></h3>
<p><strong>Tuesday 20th May, 18:30 - 21:30. Prince Albert Pub, 163 Royal College Street, London, NW1 0SG</strong></p>
<p>We’re told AI is taking an increasingly important role in decision-making, but what does this really mean? And how should we, the people, respond to this? Understanding how AI is <em>really</em> being used for prediction and decision-making is the best tool for interpreting the daily flow of AI news.</p>
<p>Three researchers from the Alan Turing Institute will take to the stage to help. We’ll hear how AI is being used in the real world and how it relates to the big things in life: health, travel safety and (most important of all) the weather. Plus join in with our annual Big Quiz of AI!</p>
</section>
<section id="health-data-science-seminar-series" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="health-data-science-seminar-series"><a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/health-data-science-seminar-series-tickets-1329649059129?aff=ebdsoporgprofile&amp;_gl=1*90qvwn*_up*MQ..*_ga*MTkyMDUyNDM4NC4xNzQ1ODI4MjAy*_ga_TQVES5V6SH*MTc0NTgyODIwMS4xLjAuMTc0NTgyODIwMS4wLjAuMA.." target="_blank">Health Data Science Seminar Series</a></h3>
<p><strong>Wednesday 4th June, 14:00 - 15:30, Online </strong></p>
<p>This series of seminars presents an exciting opportunity to hear about recent developments in health data science, generate ideas and help build the health data science community. It is hosted by the ONS’s Data Science Campus and Health Analysis Team in partnership with Health Data Research UK (HDR UK).</p>
<p>The Health Data Science Seminar series provides a dedicated space for data scientists, policymakers, health professionals, academics, epidemiologists, statisticians and other members of the data science community to come together and explore the potential of data science, to help improve health and health policy. Sign up now and be part of the conversation - it’s free!</p>
<p>Please note, this seminar takes place on Microsoft Teams, with the access link to be sent to all registered attendees at least 24 hours before the start of the event.</p>
<p>If you have any questions about this seminar, please email outreach.engagement.community@ons.gov.uk.</p>
</section>
<section id="big-data-ldn" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="big-data-ldn"><a href="https://www.bigdataldn.com/en-gb.html" target="_blank">Big Data LDN</a></h3>
<p><strong>Wednesday 24th - Thursday 25th September, All Day, London</strong></p>
<p>Big Data LDN is the UK’s leading free to attend data, analytics and AI conference &amp; exhibition.</p>
<p>The two day event is a hub for the Data Community to learn and share best practice, build relationships and find the tools needed to develop an effective data-driven business.</p>
<hr>
<p>See more future events on the <a href="https://future.nhs.uk/DataAnalytics/view?objectID=861745" target="_blank">calendar</a></p>
<p>Know of any events we should feature next month? Let us know by clicking the “Contribute” button, or <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="using-ai-for-early-detection-of-lung-cancer" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Using AI for early detection of lung cancer</h1>
</section>
<p>Looking for an interesting read? The British Journal of General Practice has a paper on <a href="https://bjgp.org/content/early/2025/04/21/BJGP.2023.0489">Artificial intelligence for early detection of lung cancer in GPs’ clinical notes: a retrospective observational cohort study</a>.</p>
<p>The paper looks at developing new prediction tools to improve the risk assessment of lung cancer, by performing text analysis on electronic patient data using natural language processing and machine learning. The processing is applied to general practice files of four networks in the Netherlands.</p>
<hr>
<p>Check out our collection of training resources in the <a href="https://future.nhs.uk/DataAnalytics/view?objectID=861745" target="_blank">Resources Section</a>! Can you spot something missing? <a href="mailto:datascience@nhs.net">Contact us</a>!</p>
<section id="need-a-quick-break" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Need a Quick Break?</h1>
</section>
<p><a href="custom_wordle_link" target="_blank">How many tries will it take you?</a></p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<p><a href="https://forms.office.com/pages/responsepage.aspx?id=slTDN7CF9UeyIge0jXdO48pr_29hyJFKpCZ7SYYvjeFUNUVPMUk0STlDRlJMNklIWEI3V0NZVTZXVS4u&amp;route=shorturl" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-success btn-lg">Subscribe to the community</a><a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">Contribute</a><a href="./newsletter.pdf" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">PDF Version</a></p>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>newsletter</category>
  <category>interview with a data scientist</category>
  <guid>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2025_04/newsletter.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Data Science Community for Health and Care Newsletter March 2025</title>
  <dc:creator>Jennifer Struthers, Joe Wilson, Michelle Nwachukwu</dc:creator>
  <link>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2025_03/newsletter.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/images/banner_march.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Welcome to the latest newsletter from the Data Science Community for Health and Care, brought to you by the NHS England Data Science Professional Development Functional Team.</p>
<p>The newsletter team are always happy to receive constructive feedback, and we invite you to send us any contributions you may have.</p>
<p>If you cannot access something of interest to you, please <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new" target="_blank">reach out</a>.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading! – newsletter team</p>
<section id="the-aerospace-engineer-who-loved-spreadsheets" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>The Aerospace Engineer who Loved Spreadsheets</h1>
</section>
<p>Welcome to the first installment of our <strong>“Interview with a Data Scientist”</strong> series, where we explore the careers and work of the talented members of the NHS England Data Science team. We aim to showcase the fantastic individuals who contribute to the NHS England Data Science Profession and provide valuable insights for those considering a career in Data Science within the healthcare sector.</p>
<p>The first interview is with Joe Wilson, a former Engineer whose desire to make the perfect F1 Fantasy Team during the COVID pandemic drove him to become a Data Scientist who won’t stop talking about Reproducible Analytical Pipelines.</p>
<details>
<summary>
Read more…
</summary>
<section id="how-did-you-end-up-in-data-science-at-the-nhs-what-did-you-do-before-and-what-really-sparked-your-interest-in-this-field" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-did-you-end-up-in-data-science-at-the-nhs-what-did-you-do-before-and-what-really-sparked-your-interest-in-this-field">How did you end up in data science at the NHS? What did you do before, and what really sparked your interest in this field?</h2>
<p>My journey to data science at the NHS is a blend of engineering roots, a pandemic pivot, and a strong personal connection to healthcare.</p>
<p>My academic background began with an Integrated Master’s in Aerospace Engineering. I was captivated by the problem-solving inherent in understanding how complex systems, particularly aircraft, function. This fascination with engineering persists, as evidenced by my continued interest in aerospace content.</p>
<p>A pivotal moment that hinted at my future direction occurred during a second-year Business Simulation module. We were tasked with managing car companies within a simulated European market. I developed a comprehensive spreadsheet to optimise production, enabling us to create cost-effective cars with popular features. I would go on to make many more spreadsheets, including one that calculated my mark margins for upcoming exams to allow me to still graduate with first class honours.</p>
<p>Following graduation, I joined a small engineering firm, where I contributed to the development of control software for automated test rigs. We built custom rigs to test components like aircraft actuators and truck brake assemblies, using the visual programming language LabVIEW. This involved wiring code sections together, and I still recognise LabVIEW’s distinctive interface in various applications, including airport airbridge controls.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, I lost my job around the onset of the COVID-19 pandemic, coinciding with a severe contraction of the job market. During the lockdown, I used the time to learn Python, which sparked a realisation that I wanted to pursue a career in data science. While I’d always enjoyed numbers, spreadsheets, problem-solving, and programming, the pandemic provided the catalyst to connect these interests.</p>
<p>I enrolled in a Data Science conversion Master’s program at Loughborough University, joining the inaugural cohort of the degree. The decision to apply to the NHS was deeply personal. My father was a GP and healthcare consultant, and my then-girlfriend (now wife), was training to be a doctor. The NHS’s mission resonated with me, and I discovered the NHS Digital Graduate Scheme. I applied and was fortunate enough to be accepted.</p>
<p>I began my role at the NHS just two weeks after submitting my Master’s project.</p>
</section>
<section id="once-you-joined-the-nhs-what-was-that-experience-like-what-different-roles-and-teams-have-you-been-a-part-of-and-how-have-they-shaped-your-career" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="once-you-joined-the-nhs-what-was-that-experience-like-what-different-roles-and-teams-have-you-been-a-part-of-and-how-have-they-shaped-your-career">Once you joined the NHS, what was that experience like? What different roles and teams have you been a part of, and how have they shaped your career?</h2>
<p>Joining the NHS was a real whirlwind, but in the best way possible! I’ve been here for three years now, starting at NHS Digital and then transitioning into NHS England after the merger. My first two years were spent on the NHS Digital Graduate Scheme, and since then, I’ve been working as a full-fledged Data Scientist.</p>
<p>That Graduate Scheme was incredible. We were the first cohort of its kind, a group of just under twenty, and we kicked things off with an intense eight-week coding bootcamp. It was a fantastic bonding experience – we’d be hammering away at code and then decompressing with board games during breaks.</p>
<p>My first placement on the NHS Spine project, which is this massive, intricate system connecting all sorts of different NHS systems. Because it’s so complex, everyone was constantly learning, and that made it a really supportive environment for a newbie like me. Plus, I got to see firsthand what a well-oiled DevOps team looked like, which really shaped my approach moving forward, especially when I landed in the Business Intelligence Development Team.</p>
<p>That team was all about building Tableau dashboards and trying to standardise things. My manager asked me to dig into the Tableau API. They had this super slow, manual process for checking dashboards, and I realised we could automate it with Python. So, I built a proof-of-concept testing framework, which was a great chance to put my NHS Spine lessons to work in a totally different area.</p>
<p>My final placement was with the Reproducible Analytical Pipelines (RAP) Squad. We were all about promoting good coding practices for analytics and helping teams automate their workflows. Basically, we were bringing in the best of data and software engineering into the data science and analytics space. In that role, I got to write articles, create training guides, and even run workshops. We also did these ‘Engagements’ with other analytical teams, helping them improve their processes. After a year, I passed my end-of-scheme interview and got promoted to a Band 7 Data Scientist, staying with the RAP Squad and leading those Engagements.</p>
<p>More recently, I moved to the National Secure Data Environment Service Team, or the SDE Data Wranglers. We make sure researchers get the right, pseudonymised data. While there, I also got to work on a side project developing an ML-powered tool to detect potentially sensitive information in huge datasets. It was a fun challenge, working with Docker containers, PySpark, and figuring out how to deploy ML models in a clustered computing environment.</p>
<p>Overall, it’s been a really varied and rewarding experience. Each role has built on the last, and I’ve learned so much about the NHS and the power of data.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-are-you-currently-working-on-are-there-any-projects-that-youre-particularly-excited-about-or-that-you-feel-are-making-a-real-difference-what-impact-are-you-having" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-are-you-currently-working-on-are-there-any-projects-that-youre-particularly-excited-about-or-that-you-feel-are-making-a-real-difference-what-impact-are-you-having">What are you currently working on? Are there any projects that you’re particularly excited about, or that you feel are making a real difference? What impact are you having?</h2>
<p>Right now, I’m embedded within an analytical team focused on commissioning specialised NHS services. It’s a really interesting area, and I’m helping them boost their Reproducible Analytical Pipelines (RAP) compliance, automate some of their manual processes, and bring in some Python expertise to diversify their toolkit.</p>
<p>One project I’m particularly excited about is automating their monthly reporting. We’ve managed to cut the processing time from a week down to just a few minutes, which is a huge win! It’s incredibly rewarding to free up my colleagues’ time, allowing them to focus on more impactful, data-driven insights rather than repetitive tasks.</p>
<p>I’m also personally driven to achieve something new for me; building a pipeline that meets <a href="https://nhsdigital.github.io/rap-community-of-practice/introduction_to_RAP/levels_of_RAP/">Gold RAP compliance</a> standard; essentially, a fully automated and packaged analytical process. We’re facing some interesting challenges, but I’m confident that overcoming them will pave the way for more efficient and robust projects in the future.</p>
</section>
<section id="if-you-could-give-someone-just-starting-out-in-data-science-a-few-pieces-of-advice-what-would-they-be-and-what-resources-have-you-found-particularly-helpful-along-the-way-that-you-can-share" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="if-you-could-give-someone-just-starting-out-in-data-science-a-few-pieces-of-advice-what-would-they-be-and-what-resources-have-you-found-particularly-helpful-along-the-way-that-you-can-share">If you could give someone just starting out in data science a few pieces of advice, what would they be? And what resources have you found particularly helpful along the way that you can share?</h2>
<p>If I could give some advice to someone starting out in data science, I’d say:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Consider a conversion master’s if it’s feasible.</strong> Mine was a game-changer. It accelerated my learning so much, and it gave me a strong portfolio to show potential employers right away.
<ul>
<li><strong>Dive into online resources, but don’t get lost in them.</strong> There’s a wealth of information out there! <a href="https://www.kaggle.com/learn/python">Kaggle Learn</a> is a fantastic starting point.</li>
<li><strong>Master Git and GitHub.</strong> Seriously, this is crucial. I even helped create a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wOk7wDsHD8o">workshop</a> for the NHS-R Community and some <a href="https://nhsdigital.github.io/rap-community-of-practice/training_resources/git/introduction-to-git/">training materials</a> on it, which you can find on the <a href="https://nhsdigital.github.io/rap-community-of-practice/">RAP Community of Practice</a> website. Learning Git and GitHub will also allow you to use GitHub codespaces, and avoid the pain of setting up your local environment.</li>
<li><strong>Don’t just stick to tutorials.</strong> It’s easy to get stuck in tutorial hell. Find a simple, personal project that excites you. Mine was building a tool to optimise my Fantasy F1 team. Passion projects are a great way to build a portfolio and showcase your skills.</li>
</ul>
Basically, combine structured learning with practical application, and don’t be afraid to explore your own interests!</li>
</ul>
</section></details>

<section id="events" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Events</h1>
</section>
<p>Lots of exciting things coming up! See the <a href="https://future.nhs.uk/DataAnalytics/view?objectID=861745" target="_blank">full calendar here</a>, and a small selection below.</p>
<section id="getting-started-with-open-llms" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="getting-started-with-open-llms"><a href="https://www.turing.ac.uk/events/getting-started-open-llms" target="_blank">Getting started with open LLMs</a></h3>
<p><strong>Wednesday 9th April, 10:00 - 12:00. The Alan Turing Institute (London)</strong></p>
<p>This interactive session will introduce participants to open large language models (LLMs) and demonstrate how to apply them effectively in research and real-world scenarios.</p>
<p>We’ll explore essential tools and workflows using platforms like Hugging Face and Ollama, covering model setup, execution, and fine-tuning for various applications.</p>
<p>By the end of the workshop, you’ll gain hands-on experience and a solid foundation to integrate open LLMs into your own projects.</p>
<p>Please email RDrysdale@turing.ac.uk to reserve your spot.</p>
</section>
<section id="how-ai-is-shaping-journalism-and-journalism-is-shaping-ai" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-ai-is-shaping-journalism-and-journalism-is-shaping-ai"><a href="https://www.turing.ac.uk/events/how-ai-shaping-journalism-and-journalism-shaping-ai" target="_blank">How AI is shaping journalism and journalism is shaping AI</a></h3>
<p><strong>Friday 11th April, 17:00-19:15, The Royal Institution of Great Britain, 21 Albemarle Street, London W1S 4BS</strong></p>
<p>AI’s role in journalism goes beyond efficiency—it shapes content creation, mediates disputes, and helps mitigate bias. At the same time, it raises critical concerns about factual accuracy, bias amplification, and the distinction between AI-generated and user-generated content. This session will explore the far-reaching implications of AI-driven content creation, examining how these decisions influence public trust in journalism.</p>
</section>
<section id="supremacy---data-ethics-and-society-reading-group" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="supremacy---data-ethics-and-society-reading-group"><a href="https://www.tickettailor.com/events/dataethics/1549481/r/nhsteams" target="_blank">Supremacy - Data Ethics and Society Reading Group</a></h3>
<p><strong>Tuesday 29th April, 12:00-14:00, Online</strong></p>
<p>Join us at the Data Ethics &amp; Society Reading Group to discuss Supremacy by Parmy Olson.</p>
<p>We will be holding two sessions over two weeks. The sessions will each focus on a different section of the book- but if you can’t make the one you want to come to, we can still guarantee a great conversation! <a href="https://dataingovernment.blog.gov.uk/2025/02/17/data-ethics-and-society-join-the-conversation-in-2025/" target="_blank">Read more about our changes in our recent Data in Government blog post.</a></p>
<p>The event is FREE to attend, but places are limited so please sign up to reserve your spot! (Registration closes on Friday 18th April at 17:00)</p>
<p><em>Please note this event is for Public Sector workers only</em></p>
</section>
<section id="lse-the-power-of-data-ethics-politics-and-public-interest" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="lse-the-power-of-data-ethics-politics-and-public-interest"><a href="https://www.lse.ac.uk/Events/2025/05/202505081830/data-ethics-politics-and-public-interest?_gl=1*rwgszb*_gcl_au*MTc0NDU0NDcyNC4xNzM4NTkyNjk3*_ga*MjE2MDg0MDMzLjE3Mzg1OTI2OTI.*_ga_LWTEVFESYX*MTc0MDk5NDcxNS42OS4xLjE3NDA5OTgzNzQuMjkuMC4w" target="_blank">LSE: The power of data: ethics, politics, and public interest</a></h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 8th May, 18.30-20.00, In-person and online public event (Auditorium, Centre Building)</strong></p>
<p>Data profoundly influences all of our lives and the social, economic and political systems that govern them. Everywhere we turn we are creating increasing amounts of data that powers decision-making algorithms and shapes our future. It is however important to remember how partial and biased data can be given the priviledged position it has in the perception of absolute truth.</p>
<p>This event will discuss important questions around the role of data science in understanding and shaping the public interest, from access to information to civic participation and business development to democratic processes.</p>
</section>
<section id="ds-game-on-2025" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ds-game-on-2025"><a href="https://datasciencefestival.com/event/dsf-game-on-2025/" target="_blank">DS: Game On 2025</a></h3>
<p><strong>Saturday 17th May, All Day, London</strong></p>
<p>Join us for our 11th festival, DSF Game On 2025! Top tech speakers, incredible partners and a thriving community, all completely free.</p>
<p>The ballot is open for those wanting a chance to get tickets to DSF’s Game On 2025. Click through the link above to find out how to apply, and the (free) tickets to those successful will be sent out in April.</p>
<p>There will be a mixture of talks featured at the festival, covering all things data (science, engineering, etc) and at a variety of technical levels. You can view last years playlist on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLwzX3WM0AfxopbhVhGCA373Xk-7wNhLfq" target="_blank">YouTube here</a> to get an idea of the talks at the events.</p>
</section>
<section id="big-data-ldn" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="big-data-ldn"><a href="https://www.bigdataldn.com/en-gb.html" target="_blank">Big Data LDN</a></h3>
<p><strong>Wednesday 24th - Thursday 25th September, All Day, London</strong></p>
<p>Big Data LDN is the UK’s leading free to attend data, analytics and AI conference &amp; exhibition.</p>
<p>The two day event is a hub for the Data Community to learn and share best practice, build relationships and find the tools needed to develop an effective data-driven business.</p>
<hr>
<p>See more future events on the <a href="https://future.nhs.uk/DataAnalytics/view?objectID=861745" target="_blank">calendar</a></p>
<p>Know of any events we should feature next month? Let us know by clicking the “Contribute” button, or <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="confident-presenting" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Confident Presenting</h1>
</section>
<p>The NHS England Data Science Marketing team have been busy at work creating new materials on their website, and as expert markets they want to share them here too!</p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2025_03/confident_presenting.png" alt="A confident presenter, cartoon"></p>
</div>
<p>Do you want to present as speakers like Steve Jobs, Ken Robinson, or Simon Sinek, who are known for their exceptional ability to captivate and engage their audience? Keep reading to discover the techniques they use to deliver impactful and memorable presentations, building on the techniques from our away day workshop. Also make sure to check out some of <a href="https://github.com/user-attachments/files/19533717/C.M_.Presentation.Guide-v28-20250331_111607.pdf">our other resources</a> for presenting!</p>
<section id="confident-presenting-4-simple-presentation-secrets" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="confident-presenting-4-simple-presentation-secrets">💡 <strong>Confident Presenting: 4 Simple Presentation Secrets</strong></h3>
<p>Great presentations are built on how well you engage your audience. Here’s how you can elevate your presentation game:</p>
<p><em>Read more on our blog <a href="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience/articles/2025/03/31/presentation-in-NHSE/">here</a></em></p>
<p>📢 NHS England Data Science Team Comms and Marketing</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="population-and-person-insights-analystx-ds-huddle" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Population and Person Insights: AnalystX DS Huddle</h1>
</section>
<p>Recently, the Data Science Community for Health and Care organised a talk with the Popuation and Person Insights (PaPI) team at NHS England. The PaPI project aims to review, improve, and update the risk stratification models used in PaPI dashboards. These dashboards provide critical insights into health and care services by analysing person-level linked data, including the National Bridges to Health Segmentation Dataset.</p>
<p><a href="https://future.nhs.uk/DataAnalytics/view?objectID=56936784" target="_blank">Check out the recording (and other previous talks) here!</a></p>
<p>And if you would like to be invited to future events of ours, <a href="https://forms.office.com/pages/responsepage.aspx?id=slTDN7CF9UeyIge0jXdO48pr_29hyJFKpCZ7SYYvjeFUNUVPMUk0STlDRlJMNklIWEI3V0NZVTZXVS4u&amp;route=shorturl" target="_blank">sign up to our mailing list!</a></p>
<hr>
<section id="need-a-quick-break" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Need a Quick Break?</h1>
</section>
<p><a href="https://mywordle.strivemath.com/?word=afirc" target="_blank">How many tries will it take you?</a></p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<p><a href="https://forms.office.com/pages/responsepage.aspx?id=slTDN7CF9UeyIge0jXdO48pr_29hyJFKpCZ7SYYvjeFUNUVPMUk0STlDRlJMNklIWEI3V0NZVTZXVS4u&amp;route=shorturl" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-success btn-lg">Subscribe to the community</a><a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">Contribute</a><a href="./newsletter.pdf" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">PDF Version</a></p>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>newsletter</category>
  <category>interview with a data scientist</category>
  <guid>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2025_03/newsletter.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Data Science Community for Health and Care Newsletter February 2025</title>
  <dc:creator>Jennifer Struthers, Amaia Imaz-Blanco</dc:creator>
  <link>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2025_02/newsletter.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/images/banner_feb.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Welcome to the latest newsletter from the Data Science Community for Health and Care, brought to you by the NHS England Data Science Professional Development Functional Team.</p>
<p>The newsletter team are always happy to receive constructive feedback, and we invite you to send us any contributions you may have.</p>
<p>If you cannot access something of interest to you, please <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new" target="_blank">reach out</a>.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading! – newsletter team</p>
<section id="probabilistic-data-linkage-in-nhs-england-goes-open-source" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Probabilistic Data Linkage in NHS England Goes Open Source!</h1>
</section>
<p>The Data Linkage Hub has been developing a probabilistic data linkage pipeline to enhance the quality of data linkage in the NHS. We’re excited to share that the first iteration is now openly available on <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/NHSE_probabilistic_linkage" target="_blank">Github</a>!</p>
<p>Each stage of the pipeline has been shaped by extensive research into best practices, rigorous testing on samples of the real data, feasibility assessments of computational demands, and thorough evaluation. Our approach is incremental, with planned iterative improvements to ensure the highest standards of accuracy, efficiency, and scalability.</p>
<p>While this pipeline is not yet in use, it represents the foundation of what we plan to deploy within the Federated Data Platform (FDP). Our next step is to quality assure the pipeline, refining it further before implementation.</p>
<p>If you’d like to learn more, visit our <a href="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience/our_work/data-linkage-hub/linkage-projects/better-matching/" target="_blank">website</a> or <a href="mailto:jonathan.laidler1@nhs.net" target="_blank">get in touch</a>!</p>
<hr>
<section id="events" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Events</h1>
</section>
<p>Lots of exciting things coming up! See the <a href="https://future.nhs.uk/DataAnalytics/view?objectID=861745" target="_blank">full calendar here</a>, and a small selection below.</p>
<section id="an-alan-turing-institute-workshop-on-ai-ethics-and-governance-in-practice-programme" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="an-alan-turing-institute-workshop-on-ai-ethics-and-governance-in-practice-programme"><a href="https://www.tickettailor.com/events/publicsectoruk/1564159/r/nhs" target="_blank">An Alan Turing Institute workshop on AI Ethics and Governance in Practice programme</a></h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 27th February, 14:00-15:00, Online</strong></p>
<p>This workshop will introduce the AI Ethics and Governance in Practice programme developed by experts of The Alan Turing Institute’s Ethics and Responsible Innovation theme.</p>
<p>This programme provides public sector organisations with the Process-Based-Governance (PBG) Framework, a structured framework to put ethical values and practical principles into practice across the AI project lifecycle. It is an integral part of the UK’s National AI Strategy and expands on the UK Government’s official Public Sector Guidance on AI Ethics and Safety.</p>
<p>NB: This event is only available to public sector employees</p>
</section>
<section id="statistical-methods-for-health-equity-webinar-catalina-vallejos-university-of-edinburgh" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="statistical-methods-for-health-equity-webinar-catalina-vallejos-university-of-edinburgh"><a href="https://www.datascienceforhealthequity.com/event-details/statistical-methods-for-health-equity-webinar-catalina-vallejos-university-of-edinburgh" target="_blank">Statistical Methods for Health Equity Webinar: Catalina Vallejos (University of Edinburgh)</a></h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 6th March, 16:00-17:00, Online</strong></p>
<p>Catalina will talk about “Using Routine Healthcare Data to Predict Future Health,” exploring how electronic health records (EHR) can be leveraged to identify individuals at risk of adverse health events and improve patient outcomes. She will also discuss her work on SPARRAv4, a risk prediction tool soon to be deployed across Scotland to support primary care interventions.</p>
</section>
<section id="rethinking-good-technology-feminism-ai-and-ethical-futures" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="rethinking-good-technology-feminism-ai-and-ethical-futures"><a href="https://www.lse.ac.uk/Events/2025/03/202503111830/feminism-AI-and-ethical-futures" target="_blank">Rethinking good technology: feminism, AI and ethical futures</a></h3>
<p><strong>Tuesday 11th March, 18:30-20:00, Online and In-Person (Old Theatre, Old Building, LSE, London)</strong></p>
<p>What does it mean for technology to be ‘good’ in an age dominated by AI? Can a feminist perspective help guide us towards more ethical digital futures?</p>
<p>In this event Eleanor Drage talks about HEAT, a somewhat anarchic regulation tool that takes a feminist approach to helping companies meet the EU AI Act’s obligations. The toolkit has been developed as part of a project led by Drage, which is committed to an in-depth response to regulation that goes beyond mere compliance by working towards a pro-justice and sustainable future with AI.</p>
</section>
<section id="ai-uk-2025" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ai-uk-2025"><a href="https://www.turing.ac.uk/events/ai-uk-2025" target="_blank">AI UK 2025</a></h3>
<p><strong>Monday 17th - Tuesday 18th March, All Day, London</strong></p>
<p>Hosted by The Alan Turing Institute, AI UK is an in-depth exploration of how data science and AI can be used to solve real-world challenges. Our diverse programme was thematically structured around the latest innovations from across the AI ecosystem. With a broad range of interactive content, it covers the latest thinking on fundamental AI, digital twins, algorithmic bias, AI ethics – and much more.</p>
<p><em>NB: This is not a free event</em></p>
</section>
<section id="an-overview-of-causal-machine-learning-methodology-in-electronic-health-records-ehr" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="an-overview-of-causal-machine-learning-methodology-in-electronic-health-records-ehr"><a href="https://www.turing.ac.uk/events/overview-causal-machine-learning-methodology-electronic-health-records-ehr" target="_blank">An overview of causal machine learning methodology in Electronic Health Records (EHR)</a></h3>
<p><strong>Wednesday 19th March, 12:00-13:00, Online</strong></p>
<p>Dr Maurice O’Connell will give a talk on current work with Dr Matthew Sperrin and the DynAIRx team in the area of statistics and causal inference and causal machine learning.</p>
<p>Maurice will talk about causal inference methodology development applied to electronic health records in the areas of deprescribing or continuing/initiating medications in individuals and populations with polypharmacy and multimorbidity and selecting individuals with polypharmacy and multimorbidity for structured medication reviews.</p>
</section>
<section id="ds-game-on-2025" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ds-game-on-2025"><a href="https://datasciencefestival.com/event/dsf-game-on-2025/" target="_blank">DS: Game On 2025</a></h3>
<p><strong>Saturday 17th May, All Day, London</strong></p>
<p>Join us for our 11th festival, DSF Game On 2025! Top tech speakers, incredible partners and a thriving community, all completely free.</p>
<p>The ballot is open for those wanting a chance to get tickets to DSF’s Game On 2025. Click through the link above to find out how to apply, and the (free) tickets to those successful will be sent out in April.</p>
<p>There will be a mixture of talks featured at the festival, covering all things data (science, engineering, etc) and at a variety of technical levels. You can view last years playlist on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLwzX3WM0AfxopbhVhGCA373Xk-7wNhLfq" target="_blank">YouTube here</a> to get an idea of the talks at the events.</p>
</section>
<section id="big-data-ldn" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="big-data-ldn"><a href="https://www.bigdataldn.com/en-gb.html" target="_blank">Big Data LDN</a></h3>
<p><strong>Wednesday 24th - Thursday 25th September, All Day, London</strong></p>
<p>Big Data LDN is the UK’s leading free to attend data, analytics and AI conference &amp; exhibition.</p>
<p>The two day event is a hub for the Data Community to learn and share best practice, build relationships and find the tools needed to develop an effective data-driven business.</p>
<p><strong>The Call For Papers closes on 14 March</strong> and all applicants will be notified by the end of April whether their talk has been accepted. <a href="https://www.bigdataldn.com/en-gb/blog/event-news/call-for-papers-2025.html" target="_blank">Find out more here.</a></p>
<hr>
<p>See more future events on the <a href="https://future.nhs.uk/DataAnalytics/view?objectID=861745" target="_blank">calendar</a>.</p>
<p>Know of any events we should feature next month? Let us know by clicking the “Contribute” button, or <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="knowledge-sharing" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Knowledge Sharing</h1>
</section>
<section id="codecarbon" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="codecarbon">CodeCarbon</h3>
<p>It’s well known that LLM’s such as ChatGPT use a lot of energy, with estimates varying widely from 5 to 200+ times more energy than a Google search. With the popularity of LLM’s for everyday use growing, the total energy consumption is rising. Being aware of the energy consumption of your code is not only more important than ever, it is also easier than ever to do so.</p>
<p><a href="https://mlco2.github.io/codecarbon/" target="_blank">CodeCarbon</a> is a <a href="https://github.com/mlco2/codecarbon" target="_blank">open-source</a> Python package designed to help you estimate the carbon footprint of computing tasks, particularly for machine learning and other high-performance computing workloads. It does this by estimating your hardware electricity power consumption (GPU + CPU + RAM) and applies the carbon intensity of the region where the computing is done. More is explained about this calculation in the <a href="https://mlco2.github.io/codecarbon/methodology.html" target="_blank">Methodology section</a> of the documentation.</p>
<p>Add this (or any other tracker you know of!) to your next pipeline and start taking steps toward more sustainable computing.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="nhs-python-community---what-is-python" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="nhs-python-community---what-is-python">NHS Python Community - What is Python?</h3>
<p>Curious about Python in healthcare? Or maybe you’re tired of answering the same questions about it? The NHS Python Community has relaunched its newsletter on Substack, kicking things off with a post answering their most frequently asked questions:</p>
<p>✅ What is Python?</p>
<p>✅ Why is Python used in health and care?</p>
<p>✅ Why should I learn Python?</p>
<p>✅ What is open source?</p>
<p><a href="https://nhspycom.substack.com/p/faqs-part-1-what-is-python" target="_blank">Check out their first post here</a> and subscribe to stay updated with future insights delivered straight to your inbox!</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="ai-journal-articles" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>AI Journal Articles</h1>
</section>
<p>There’s a never ending list of new journal papers coming out every day - here’s a few we have flagged as interesting that came out in the past month or so!</p>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13545"><strong>LLMs Can Plan Only If We Tell Them</strong> - Bilgehan Sel, Ruoxi Jia, Ming Jin</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18585"><strong>Thoughts Are All Over the Place: On the Underthinking of o1-Like LLMs</strong> - Yue Wang <em>et al.</em></a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13946"><strong>Hallucination Mitigation using Agentic AI Natural Language-Based Frameworks</strong> - Diego Gosmar, Deborah A. Dahl</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00873"><strong>Language Models Use Trigonometry to Do Addition</strong> - Subhash Kantamneni, Max Tegmark</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.03373"><strong>Demystifying Long Chain-of-Thought Reasoning in LLMs</strong> - Edward Yeo <em>et al.</em></a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/39910272/"><strong>GPT-4 assistance for improvement of physician performance on patient care tasks: a randomized controlled trial</strong> - Ethan Goh <em>et al.</em></a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10849"><strong>Superhuman performance of a large language model on the reasoning tasks of a physician</strong> - Peter G. Brodeur <em>et al.</em></a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.nber.org/papers/w31422"><strong>Combining Human Expertise with Artificial Intelligence: Experimental Evidence from Radiology</strong> - Nikhil Agarwal <em>et al.</em></a></p></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>Seen a cool paper or article recently you would like to spotlight? <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=">Send us a contribution!</a></p>
<section id="need-a-quick-break" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Need a Quick Break?</h1>
</section>
<p><a href="https://mywordle.strivemath.com/?word=wfidj" target="_blank">How many tries will it take you?</a></p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<p><a href="https://forms.office.com/pages/responsepage.aspx?id=slTDN7CF9UeyIge0jXdO48pr_29hyJFKpCZ7SYYvjeFUNUVPMUk0STlDRlJMNklIWEI3V0NZVTZXVS4u&amp;route=shorturl" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-success btn-lg">Subscribe to the community</a><a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">Contribute</a><a href="./newsletter.pdf" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">PDF Version</a></p>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>newsletter</category>
  <guid>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2025_02/newsletter.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Data Science Community for Health and Care Newsletter January 2025</title>
  <dc:creator>Jennifer Struthers</dc:creator>
  <link>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2025_01/newsletter.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/images/banner_jan.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Welcome to 2025 and welcome to the latest newsletter from the Data Science Community for Health and Care, brought to you by the NHS England Data Science Professional Development Functional Team.</p>
<p>The newsletter team are always happy to receive constructive feedback, and we invite you to send us any contributions you may have.</p>
<p>If you cannot access something of interest to you, please <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new" target="_blank">reach out</a>.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading! – newsletter team</p>
<section id="llms-as-a-judge" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>LLMs as a Judge</h1>
</section>
<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2025_01/llm_as_a_judge.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Large Language Models (LLMs) like ChatGPT are increasingly being used across the NHS, but did you know you can use LLMs to evaluate other LLMs?</p>
<p>LLM-as-a-Judge is a versatile technique we have been researching in the NHS England Data Science Team. To find out exactly how this technique works, you can read our new article here: <a href="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience/articles/2024/12/31/LLM-as-a-Judge/" target="_blank">What is LLM-as-a-Judge and how can we use it? - NHS England Data Science</a></p>
<p>This is just one of many interesting articles written by the Data Science Team. You can find a full list of our articles <a href="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience/articles/" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
<hr>
<section id="events" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Events</h1>
</section>
<p>Lots of exciting things coming up! See the <a href="https://future.nhs.uk/DataAnalytics/view?objectID=861745" target="_blank">full calendar here</a>, and a small selection below.</p>
<section id="ons-health-data-science-seminar-series-health-policy-development" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ons-health-data-science-seminar-series-health-policy-development"><a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/health-data-science-seminar-series-tickets-1104444205349" target="_blank">ONS Health Data Science Seminar Series: Health Policy Development</a></h3>
<p><strong>Wednesday 5th February, 14:00 - 15:30, Online</strong></p>
<p>Professor Knight will present ‘Impact from Health Data’, demonstrating how health data can create impact across neurology, integrated care, and community care. The talk will cover evaluating apps, and care pathways and the use of incidental findings.</p>
<p>Mr Jain will present ‘The role of regulation in health technologies’, providing insights and lessons from the Regulatory Horizons Council who has developed a range of reports, including those on the regulation of medical devices and AI as a medical device.</p>
</section>
<section id="rethinking-good-technology-feminism-ai-and-ethical-futures" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="rethinking-good-technology-feminism-ai-and-ethical-futures"><a href="https://www.lse.ac.uk/Events/2025/03/202503111830/feminism-AI-and-ethical-futures" target="_blank">Rethinking good technology: feminism, AI and ethical futures</a></h3>
<p><strong>Tuesday 11th March, 18:30-20:00, Online and In-Person (Old Theatre, Old Building, LSE, London)</strong></p>
<p>What does it mean for technology to be ‘good’ in an age dominated by AI? Can a feminist perspective help guide us towards more ethical digital futures?</p>
<p>In this event Eleanor Drage talks about HEAT, a somewhat anarchic regulation tool that takes a feminist approach to helping companies meet the EU AI Act’s obligations. The toolkit has been developed as part of a project led by Drage, which is committed to an in-depth response to regulation that goes beyond mere compliance by working towards a pro-justice and sustainable future with AI.</p>
</section>
<section id="ai-uk-2025" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ai-uk-2025"><a href="https://www.turing.ac.uk/events/ai-uk-2025" target="_blank">AI UK 2025</a></h3>
<p><strong>Monday 17th - Tuesday 18th March, All Day, London</strong></p>
<p>Hosted by The Alan Turing Institute, AI UK is an in-depth exploration of how data science and AI can be used to solve real-world challenges. Our diverse programme was thematically structured around the latest innovations from across the AI ecosystem. With a broad range of interactive content, it covers the latest thinking on fundamental AI, digital twins, algorithmic bias, AI ethics – and much more.</p>
<p><em>NB: This is not a free event</em></p>
</section>
<section id="data-science-festival-mayday-2025" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-science-festival-mayday-2025"><a href="https://datasciencefestival.com/event/mayday-2025/" target="_blank">Data Science Festival: MayDay 2025</a></h3>
<p><strong>Saturday 17th May, All Day, London</strong></p>
<p>Join us for our 11th festival, DSF MayDay 2025! Top tech speakers, incredible partners and a thriving community, all completely free.</p>
<p>The ballot is open for those wanting a chance to get tickets to DSF’s MayDay 2025. Click through the link above to find out how to apply, and the (free) tickets to those successful will be sent out in April.</p>
<p>There will be a mixture of talks featured at the festival, covering all things data (science, engineering, etc) and at a variety of technical levels. You can view last years playlist on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLwzX3WM0AfxopbhVhGCA373Xk-7wNhLfq" target="_blank">YouTube here</a> to get an idea of the talks at the events.</p>
</section>
<section id="big-data-ldn" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="big-data-ldn"><a href="https://www.bigdataldn.com/en-gb.html" target="_blank">Big Data LDN</a></h3>
<p><strong>Wednesday 24th - Thursday 25th September, All Day, London</strong></p>
<p>Big Data LDN is the UK’s leading free to attend data, analytics and AI conference &amp; exhibition.</p>
<p>The two day event is a hub for the Data Community to learn and share best practice, build relationships and find the tools needed to develop an effective data-driven business.</p>
<p><strong>The Call For Papers closes on 14 March</strong> and all applicants will be notified by the end of April whether their talk has been accepted. <a href="https://www.bigdataldn.com/en-gb/blog/event-news/call-for-papers-2025.html" target="_blank">Find out more here.</a></p>
<hr>
<p>See more future events on the <a href="https://future.nhs.uk/DataAnalytics/view?objectID=861745" target="_blank">calendar</a></p>
<p>Know of any events we should feature next month? Let us know by clicking the “Contribute” button, or <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="ai-opportunities-action-plan" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>AI Opportunities Action Plan</h1>
</section>
<p>On the 13th January the Government published the AI Opportunities Action Plan, outlining how they want to have Britain shape the AI revolution. The plan outlines how Britain must invest in the foundations of AI, push hard on cross-economy AI adoption and position the UK to be an AI maker, not an AI taker.</p>
<p>The plan outlines 50 points that the government should take up in order to achieve its goals, and concludes that while the task is not small the benefits are likely to be transformational to both the economic growth of the country and the lives of those across the UK.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/ai-opportunities-action-plan/ai-opportunities-action-plan" target="_blank">Read the full plan here, and get clued up on the future of AI in our country.</a></p>
<hr>
<section id="analystx-data-science-huddles-call-for-presenters" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>AnalystX Data Science Huddles: Call for Presenters</h1>
</section>
<p>If you’ve signed up to our mailing list (<a href="https://forms.office.com/pages/responsepage.aspx?id=slTDN7CF9UeyIge0jXdO48pr_29hyJFKpCZ7SYYvjeFUNUVPMUk0STlDRlJMNklIWEI3V0NZVTZXVS4u&amp;route=shorturl" target="_blank">sign up here if not!</a>) you will hopefully at some point have received an invite to one of our AnalystX Data Science Huddles! These are monthly (or so) calls where we have invited speakers to talk about some of the work they do or a project they have been involved with. They are 1 hour sessions, with around 40 mins devoted to presenting and around 20 mins for questions.</p>
<p>Presenting at one of these calls will spread the word on the work you have done, and make connections with like-minded people across lots of different areas of healthcare data science.</p>
<p>We’re currently looking for people to talk at one of these calls from March onwards, so if you’d like to share your work, contact us at <a href="mailto:england.datascience@nhs.net">england.datascience@nhs.net</a> with the subject <strong>DS Huddle Presenter</strong> and we will get it organised!</p>
<hr>
<section id="need-a-quick-break" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Need a Quick Break?</h1>
</section>
<p><a href="https://mywordle.strivemath.com/?word=zokxx" target="_blank">How many tries will it take you?</a></p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<p><a href="https://forms.office.com/pages/responsepage.aspx?id=slTDN7CF9UeyIge0jXdO48pr_29hyJFKpCZ7SYYvjeFUNUVPMUk0STlDRlJMNklIWEI3V0NZVTZXVS4u&amp;route=shorturl" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-success btn-lg">Subscribe to the community</a><a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">Contribute</a><a href="./newsletter.pdf" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">PDF Version</a></p>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>newsletter</category>
  <guid>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2025_01/newsletter.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Data Science Community for Health and Care Newsletter December 2024</title>
  <dc:creator>Jennifer Struthers, Amaia Imaz-Blanco</dc:creator>
  <link>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_12/newsletter.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/images/banner_dec.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Welcome to the latest newsletter from the Data Science Community for Health and Care, brought to you by the NHS England Data Science Professional Development Functional Team.</p>
<p>The newsletter team are always happy to receive constructive feedback, and we invite you to send us any contributions you may have.</p>
<p>If you cannot access something of interest to you, please <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new" target="_blank">reach out</a>.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading! – newsletter team</p>
<section id="microsoft-hack" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Microsoft Hack</h1>
</section>
<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_12/amaia_hack_image.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The NHS England Data Science team, as well as a range of other analysts from across the organisation, attended an AI Hackathon at Microsoft, organised by the Data Science Team together with Microsoft and Kainos, with the key stakeholders being the NHS Websites Services Team. In this article, the author shares her experiences at the event.</p>
<p>Last week, the long awaited Hack for Health hosted at the beautiful Story Club, in Paddington London, by Microsoft and NHSE finally happened! At the hackathon, every team had either a Kainos or Microsoft representative, as well as a range of participants from across NHS England, including a strong Data Science Team presence, with several of our team members in each group. And unlike a usual hackathon, this one had stakeholders and well defined use cases, we were all working to one common goal.</p>
<p><a href="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience/articles/2024/12/04/microsoft-hackathon/" target="_blank">Continue reading…</a></p>
<section id="christmas-challenges" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Christmas Challenges</h1>
</section>
<section id="gchq-christmas-challenge" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="gchq-christmas-challenge">GCHQ Christmas Challenge</h2>
<p>GCHQ have released their annual <a href="https://www.gchq.gov.uk/files/GCHQ%20Christmas%20Challenge%202024.pdf" target="_blank">Christmas Challenge</a>. While aimed at children aged 11-18 we had a great time puzzling this one out during a morning Christmas meeting - perfect for a family Christmas quiz night!</p>
</section>
<section id="rss-christmas-quiz-puzzles" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="rss-christmas-quiz-puzzles">RSS Christmas Quiz + Puzzles</h2>
<p>The Royal Statistical Society have published their Christmas quiz and puzzles. There are even prizes for answering - the top three entries received by the deadline (<strong>20:00 Sunday 5th January 2025</strong>) will receive a donation of up to £150 to a charity of good cause of their choice.</p>
<p>The Section A quiz questions can be found <a href="https://rss.org.uk/news-publication/news-publications/2024/general-news/rss-christmas-quiz-2024-questions-and-puzzles-to-p/" target="_blank">here</a>, while the Section B puzzles can be found in PDF format <a href="https://rss.org.uk/RSS/media/File-library/Quiz/2024-RSS-XMAS-QUIZ_section-B.pdf" target="_blank">here</a> on linked on their own site: <a href="thexmaspuzzles.com" target="_blank">thexmaspuzzles.com</a>.</p>
<p><em>Note: This site may not be accessible through work laptops</em></p>
</section>
<section id="bbc-bitesize-ai-or-real-christmas-edition" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bbc-bitesize-ai-or-real-christmas-edition">BBC Bitesize: AI or real? Christmas edition!</h2>
<p>Artificial intelligence is already very impressive, with many AI images and videos so flawless that it can be difficult to tell what’s fake and what’s real. But as it continues to develop, will this become an impossible task?</p>
<p>Challenge yourself with this Christmas edition of <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/bitesize/articles/zv74tcw" target="_blank">AI or real</a>!</p>
</section>
<section id="christmas-crossword" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="christmas-crossword">Christmas Crossword</h2>
<p>Love crosswords? Love Machine Learning and AI? Last year Ivan Reznikov published a <a href="https://medium.com/@ivanreznikov/data-science-christmas-crossword-puzzle-327dec18cfab" target="_blank">Christmas Data Science Crossword Puzzle</a>.</p>
<p>Your family will love solving this together after Christmas dinner and definitely not throw wrapping paper at your head!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="https://medium.com/@ivanreznikov/data-science-christmas-crossword-puzzle-327dec18cfab" target="_blank"><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_12/crossword.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></a></p>
<figcaption>Christmas Crossword: click the image to go to the site</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="rpysoc-relive-the-experience" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>RPySOC: Relive the experience</h1>
</section>
<p>As mentined in last month’s newsletter, the RPySOC conference was hosted, bringing together enthusiasts of all things R, Python and Open Source software from all over the country. In the spirit of things being open and freely available, the talks and slides have been made available to you all to watch in your own time!</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/nhs-r-community/conference-2024?tab=readme-ov-file" target="_blank">Link to slides held in GitHub</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLXCrMzQaI6c2vQUabRSOg9_FCxp6x6cVg" target="_blank">Link to recordings hosted on YouTube</a></li>
</ul>
<section id="resources" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Resources</h1>
</section>
<p>For some, the festive period can allow a little bit of a reprieve from projects and meetings: the perfect time to do that training you always wanted to do but never had the time for. Consider blocking out some time for yourself to hit your learning goals!</p>
<section id="intro-to-coding" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="intro-to-coding"><a href="https://future.nhs.uk/DataAnalytics/view?objectID=56293968" target="_blank">Intro to Coding</a></h2>
<p>The team have been busy updating the resources page of the FutureNHS site (free account required to access), including a new section full of resources on how to get started with Python.</p>
<p>There are so many great resources to get you started on a data science journey.</p>
</section>
<section id="intro-to-llms" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="intro-to-llms"><a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/llm_tutorial" target="_blank">Intro to LLMs</a></h2>
<p>Sam and Adam Hollings have a public repository which will walk you through some simple LLM implementations. It uses free software and can all be run inside Google Collab, for maximum accessibility. It could not be easier to start learning about this essential area of data science!</p>
<hr>
<p>Check out our collection of training resources in the <a href="https://future.nhs.uk/DataAnalytics/view?objectID=56293968" target="_blank">Resources Section</a>! Can you spot something missing? <a href="mailto:datascience@nhs.net">Contact us</a>!</p>
</section>
<section id="need-a-quick-break" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Need a Quick Break?</h1>
</section>
<p><a href="https://mywordle.strivemath.com/?word=pfvhd" target="_blank">How many tries will it take you?</a></p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<p><a href="https://forms.office.com/pages/responsepage.aspx?id=slTDN7CF9UeyIge0jXdO48pr_29hyJFKpCZ7SYYvjeFUNUVPMUk0STlDRlJMNklIWEI3V0NZVTZXVS4u&amp;route=shorturl" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-success btn-lg">Subscribe to the community</a><a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">Contribute</a><a href="./newsletter.pdf" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">PDF Version</a></p>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>newsletter</category>
  <category>festive edition</category>
  <guid>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_12/newsletter.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Data Science Community for Health and Care Newsletter November 2024</title>
  <dc:creator>Jennifer Struthers, William Poulett</dc:creator>
  <link>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_11/newsletter.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/images/banner_nov.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Welcome to the latest newsletter from the Data Science Community for Health and Care, brought to you by the NHS England Data Science Professional Development Functional Team.</p>
<p>The newsletter team are always happy to receive constructive feedback, and we invite you to send us any contributions you may have.</p>
<p>If you cannot access something of interest to you, please <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new" target="_blank">reach out</a>.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading! – newsletter team</p>
<section id="rpysoc-conference-musings" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>RPySOC: Conference Musings</h1>
</section>
<p><em>written by Jennifer Struthers</em></p>
<hr>
<p>If you are a regular reader of this newsletter you might have seen the <a href="https://nhsrcommunity.com/conference24.html" target="_blank">RPySOC event</a> plugged each month, which was at long last held last week. The conference was a celebration of all things R/Python/Open-Source, and everyone there was excited to show off the projects they had been involved in over the last year.</p>
<p>There were at least 100 people gathered in the Birmingham International Conference Centre, and more present online where the talks were being live-streamed. People seemed to be saying hello to colleagues that they hadn’t seen in a while, and sitting down at tables to meet new people and discuss all things healthcare and coding.</p>
<p>I went along to present my <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/opensource_maternity_dashboard_project" target="_blank">project on experimenting with open-source dashboarding tools and packages</a>, which I had undertaken earlier this year to develop my data visualisation and general coding skills. It was a brief talk, with just a 15 minute timeslot, but I got surprisingly more nervous as the morning went on. I’ve given variants of this presentation before, and I was confident in answering any questions on it, really I should have been fine. However this was the first time since I was in university that I had stood in front of people and spoken to them, instead of hidden behind my computer screen talking to my slides. Strange how something like hybrid working has completely changed something as fundamental as giving a presentation.</p>
<p>Luckily, my fears were unfounded. The stage lights were so bright I couldn’t see anyone anyway and I could pretend I was still at my desk, talking at my slides like normal. Before I knew it I was back at my table and could breathe and enjoy the rest of the conference, while typing away to answer all the questions and comments that had come through during my talk.</p>
<p>There was a Slack channel organised for questions which meant that online viewers had the same chance to ask questions as in-person attendees, and the speakers could take their time afterwards to answer extra questions and give links. Almost every single presentation included links to public GitHub repositories, and people were actively encouraged to check out the code, and re-use whatever they wanted to.</p>
<p>The whole conference was focused on sharing, collaborating and supporting others, regardless of where they were at in the coding journey. It was a great gathering of a community (full of provided food and coffee!), and what really struck me was how keen everyone was to get involved, give people pointers, and congratulate them on the work they had done. The talks were evenly distributed between Python and R users, and everything pitched at a level anyone with a coding interest could understand. If you’ve got a project you’re working on and are keen to share the results in front of an audience, I would definitely recommend next year’s RPySOC!</p>
<p>The conference organisers will be sharing the recordings of the talks, along with slides and links, at a later date so that the knowledge can be shared on and on.</p>
<hr>
<section id="data-science-discussion" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Data Science Discussion</h1>
</section>
<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_11/sci_comm.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The data science team at NHS England hold Data Science Discussions on a monthly (ish!) basis. These discussions are typically informal, and in a small group to encourage as much discussion as possible. The most recent Data Science Discussion was delivered by Ben Wallace, one of the senior data scientists within the team.</p>
<p>Ben was keen to introduce the idea of science communication and how to get your ideas across correctly. We discussed how to explain complex topics such as lossy compression in an easily understandable manor. Through examples we discussed when explanations were too complex, too simple, or just right, before having a go ourselves at explaining tricky data science terms.</p>
<p>Interested in learning more about science communication? Check out these resources below:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.howtogiveatalk.com/" target="_blank">How to Give A Talk (blog)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/storytellingwithdata" target="_blank">Storytelling with Data (Youtube channel)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.mpls.ox.ac.uk/public-engagement/latest/free-short-online-course-how-to-communicate-scientific-uncertainty" target="_blank">How to communicate scientific uncertainty (free online course from University of Oxford)</a></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<section id="community-shout-outs" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Community Shout Outs</h1>
</section>
<p>There are a myriad of data science communities doing excellent work to link people, share resources and support people in their careers and personal projects: check out some of them below and get involved!</p>
<section id="nhs-r" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="nhs-r">NHS-R</h2>
<p>The <a href="https://nhsrcommunity.com/" target="_blank">NHS-R Community</a> started in 2018 to promote the use of R in the NHS and the community has grown rapidly ever since. It is a community that is broader than the NHS as members come from public sector organisations across the UK, including Local Authorities and Civil Service, as well as academics and voluntary sector people who have an interest in healthcare and R.</p>
</section>
<section id="nhs-pycom" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="nhs-pycom">NHS-PyCom</h2>
<p>Led by enthusiasts and advocates, the <a href="https://nhs-pycom.net/" target="_blank">NHS Python Community for Healthcare</a> is an open community of practice that champions the use of the Python programming language and open code in the NHS and healthcare sector. Join them on <a href="https://join.slack.com/t/nhs-pycom/shared_invite/zt-z6h1hszo-3_w68FdalVM2EATVVdgCuw" target="_blank">Slack</a>, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC_jacmsGNZQR5BPP7h0EtXw/video">YouTube</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/nhs-python-community/posts/" target="_blank">LinkedIn</a> and <a href="https://github.com/nhs-pycom" target="_blank">GitHub</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="rainbowr" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="rainbowr">rainbowR</h2>
<p><a href="https://rainbowr.org/" target="_blank">rainbowR</a> is a community that supports, promotes and connects LGBTQ+ people who code in the R language, and spreads awareness of LGBTQ+ issues through data-driven activism. They are currently running a book club, get involved! <a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1y7SOWE3IW-fpR_5Cd4mK-CMUpFZ-hvhY4cTj34JqTVE/viewform?edit_requested=true" target="_blank">Join the community.</a></p>
</section>
<section id="analystx" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analystx">AnalystX</h2>
<p><a href="https://analystx.uk/" target="_blank">AnalystX</a> are here to connect and empower the data and analytics community, providing a safe space for professionals to collaborate in a radical way across the health system. They host lots of <a href="https://analystx.uk/resources" target="_blank">resources</a> on their site, including links to their <a href="https://communities.analystx.uk/" target="_blank">sub-communities</a> of Data Science, Data Engineering, GeoHealth and more!</p>
</section>
<section id="the-turing-way" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-turing-way">The Turing Way</h2>
<p><a href="https://book.the-turing-way.org/index.html" target="_blank">The Turing Way</a> is an open science, open collaboration, and community-driven project. We involve and support a diverse community of contributors to make data science accessible, comprehensible and effective for everyone. Our goal is to provide all the information that researchers, data scientists, software engineers, policymakers, and other practitioners in academia, industry, government and the public sector need to ensure that the projects they work on are easy to reproduce and reuse.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="call-for-content" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Call for Content!</h1>
</section>
<p>Got a project to showcase? An event to plug? A tip to share?</p>
<p>We want to hear from you! This newsletter is a community effort and we want to showcase and spread the word about all of the good work being done across it.</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" target="_blank">Click here</a>, or at the bottom of the page to submit your contribution!</p>
<hr>
<section id="need-a-quick-break" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Need a Quick Break?</h1>
</section>
<p><a href="https://mywordle.strivemath.com/?word=pfrly" target="_blank">How many tries will it take you?</a></p>
<hr>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<p><a href="https://forms.office.com/pages/responsepage.aspx?id=slTDN7CF9UeyIge0jXdO48pr_29hyJFKpCZ7SYYvjeFUNUVPMUk0STlDRlJMNklIWEI3V0NZVTZXVS4u&amp;route=shorturl" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-success btn-lg">Subscribe to the community</a><a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">Contribute</a><a href="./newsletter.pdf" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">PDF Version</a></p>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>newsletter</category>
  <category>RPySOC</category>
  <category>Data Science Discussion</category>
  <guid>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_11/newsletter.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Data Science Community for Health and Care Newsletter October 2024</title>
  <dc:creator>Jennifer Struthers</dc:creator>
  <link>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_10/newsletter.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/images/banner_oct.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Welcome to the latest newsletter from the Data Science Community for Health and Care, brought to you by the NHS England Data Science Professional Development Functional Team.</p>
<p>The newsletter team are always happy to receive constructive feedback, and we invite you to send us any contributions you may have.</p>
<p>If you cannot access something of interest to you, please <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new" target="_blank">reach out</a>.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading! – newsletter team</p>
<section id="check-out-our-website" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Check out our website!</h1>
</section>
<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_10/ds_community_header.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Over the past few months the team behind this newsletter have been busy redesigning and revamping <a href="https://future.nhs.uk/connect.ti/DataAnalytics/view?objectId=54053296" target="_blank">our site</a> on the FutureNHS platform, and it’s finally ready to share!</p>
<p>This is where you can find any and all of our resources, past event recordings and calendar of upcoming events! You will need a (free) FutureNHS account in order to access it.</p>
<p>Don’t have an account? Just follow the link to the site and complete the “create an account” instructions.</p>
<p>Any requests? Comments are enabled on the site, simply scroll to the bottom and let us know what you think!</p>
<hr>
<section id="events" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Events</h1>
</section>
<p>Lots of exciting things coming up! See the <a href="https://future.nhs.uk/DataAnalytics/view?objectID=861745" target="_blank">full calendar here</a>, and a small selection below.</p>
<section id="bold-innovation-showcase" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bold-innovation-showcase"><a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/bold-innovation-showcase-tickets-983890461857" target="_blank">BOLD Innovation Showcase</a></h3>
<p><strong>Wednesday 6th November 2024, 9:30-16:30, London</strong></p>
<p>Welcome to the BOLD Innovation Showcase! Join us at the De Vere Grand Connaught Rooms for a day filled with groundbreaking ideas and cutting-edge technologies. This in-person event is your chance to connect with industry leaders, innovators, and visionaries. Get ready to be inspired, network with like-minded individuals, and discover the future of innovation. Don’t miss out on this exciting opportunity to be a part of something truly special. See you there!</p>
</section>
<section id="making-health-data-resources-discoverable-through-the-health-data-research-gateway" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="making-health-data-resources-discoverable-through-the-health-data-research-gateway"><a href="https://www.turing.ac.uk/events/making-health-data-resources-discoverable-through-health-data-research-gateway" target="_blank">Making health data resources discoverable through the Health Data Research Gateway</a></h3>
<p><strong>Tuesday 12th November, 13:30-14:30, Online</strong></p>
<p>The Health Data Research Gateway (the Gateway) is a central location to discover health data and other resources vital for research. To date, more than 850 descriptions of datasets (metadata) from 70+ data custodians have been uploaded to the Gateway, along with 2500+ registered users and over 1000 data uses added to the Gateway data use register.</p>
<p>Throughout the last year, the HDR UK Technology Team has been working on a major new version of the platform. This presentation will outline how the Gateway’s new functionality will help users discover, explore and access health and health-related data, software and research analysis, publications, diseases, phenotypes and other shareable resources.</p>
</section>
<section id="nhs-rpysoc-2024-conference" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="nhs-rpysoc-2024-conference"><a href="https://nhsrcommunity.com/events.html" target="_blank">NHS RPySOC 2024 Conference</a></h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 21st-22nd November, 9am-5pm, in-person (Birmingham) / Online</strong></p>
<p>The <strong>NHS RPySOC 2024 conference</strong> is open for registration now! It will be on <strong>21st &amp; 22nd November in Birmingham</strong>. This is jointly hosted by the NHS R Community and NHS.pycom, and also promotes Open Source.</p>
<ul>
<li>Day 1 will be a mixture of presentations, workshops and lightening talks</li>
<li>Day 2 will be ‘Unconference’ with suggestions for topics being taken on day 1.</li>
</ul>
<p>It’s a great chance to show off our work, share our learning with a like minded community and learn a few things yourself, such as the state of the industry and how techniques are being applied elsewhere.</p>
<p>You can either attend:</p>
<ul>
<li>In-Person (The ICC, Hall 11, Birmingham B1 2EA (Sold Out: Waiting List Only)</li>
<li>Online</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>See more future events on the <a href="https://future.nhs.uk/DataAnalytics/view?objectID=861745" target="_blank">calendar</a></p>
<p>Know of any events we should feature next month? Let us know by clicking the “Contribute” button, or <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="data-science-discussion-professional-development-edition" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Data Science Discussion: Professional Development Edition</h1>
</section>
<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_10/dsd_header.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Last month we ran another Data Science Discussion, an event where we have a host prepare a topic for discussion and then we split into breakout rooms to allow more people to have their say. These discussions aren’t recorded, we want to make everyone feel as comfortable as possible to discuss their thoughts and ideas on whatever topic we are talking about.</p>
<p>Most recently our discussion focussed on professional development in our current roles, and how we can support others to take advantage of the opportunities they have.</p>
<p>One discussion point that came up in a few groups was the difference between purposeful development time versus just doing the job and where the line is drawn between them. It was felt that a lot of the work we do involves researching and learning about different techniques and methods, and that this could really also be considered professional development.</p>
<p>A theme that also came up across groups was the lack of time available for dedicated professional development for topics and areas that are separate from the day to day work. A lot of people felt like they had limited time for self-directed study, and that getting the job done took priority which led to professional development taking a back seat. In order to mitigate this, people suggested blocking out calendar time in advance in order to pre-book learning time, although sticking to this can be hard if you’re busy.</p>
<p>We had members from various NHS teams present at this discussion and there was also a definite split, with some teams feeling like they were allowed a lot more time and were encouraged to take development opportunities more than others. This highlighted a bit of a difference in team culture, and there was discussion about how those who are allotted more time could support those without.</p>
<p>The most engaging discussion point? Whether a hot dog is a sandwich. We’re still split on it.</p>
<hr>
<p>Want to get the calendar invite for the next one? <a href="https://forms.office.com/pages/responsepage.aspx?id=slTDN7CF9UeyIge0jXdO48pr_29hyJFKpCZ7SYYvjeFUNUVPMUk0STlDRlJMNklIWEI3V0NZVTZXVS4u&amp;route=shorturl" target="_blank">Sign up to our mailing list</a>.</p>
<p>Want to host a Discussion? <a href="mailto:datascience@nhs.net">Contact us</a> and let us know!</p>
<hr>
<section id="competitions-and-challenges" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Competitions and Challenges</h1>
</section>
<section id="british-heart-foundation-kaggle-competition" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="british-heart-foundation-kaggle-competition">British Heart Foundation Kaggle Competition</h2>
<p>Got a competitive edge but a heart of gold?</p>
<p>The British Heart Foundation Data Science Centre have set up a Kaggle competition, in collaboration with researchers from the ition on Kaggle The University of Edinburgh. The challenge aims to assess whether artificial intelligence/machine learning can be used to identify and classify disorders of heart rhythm from synthetic ECG images which have been created to incorporate common artefacts.</p>
<p>The top scoring teams will be invited to participate in a British Heart Foundation Data Science Centre webinar about the challenge and the best performing will be invited to present their results at the British Cardiovascular Society (BCS) meeting in June 2025. Participation in these activities will require code sharing.</p>
<p>Find out more information and how to enter <a href="https://www.kaggle.com/c/bhf-data-science-centre-ecg-challenge">here</a>. This competition is currently open and runs until Monday 16th of December 2024.</p>
</section>
<section id="gandalf-game" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="gandalf-game">Gandalf Game</h2>
<p>Test your LLM prompt skills by tricking Gandalf into revealing the secret password for each level. Each level gets progressively harder, with Gandalf first just giving the password to anyone that asks and later more creative approaches are needed.</p>
<p>Played before? There’s new adventures! Try Reverse Gandalf, where you tell Gandalf how to defend against password seeking users.</p>
<p>You can check it out here: <a href="https://gandalf.lakera.ai/intro" target="_blank">Gandalf Wizard AI</a></p>
</section>
<section id="ai-vs-human-who-wrote-it-best" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ai-vs-human-who-wrote-it-best">AI vs Human: Who wrote it best?</h2>
<p>Can you tell when something has been written by a machine? Can you write like a machine?</p>
<p>Check out <a href="https://gptzero.me/" target="_blank">GPTZero</a>, a free online AI checker which estimates its confidence that the text you input is or isn’t AI generated. Think you can fool it? Try writing a short paragraph in the style of ChatGPT, and see if you can get it to think what you’ve written was really written by an LLM. Or flip the script: give your favourite LLM prompts to see if it can produce text that passes as human.</p>
<p>Was this text written by AI? Test it out!</p>
<hr>
<p>Check out our collection of training resources in the <a href="https://future.nhs.uk/DataAnalytics/view?objectID=861745" target="_blank">Resources Section</a>! Can you spot something missing? <a href="mailto:datascience@nhs.net">Contact us</a>!</p>
</section>
<section id="need-a-quick-break" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Need a Quick Break?</h1>
</section>
<p><a href="https://mywordle.strivemath.com/?word=hwdle" target="_blank">How many tries will it take you?</a></p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<p><a href="https://forms.office.com/pages/responsepage.aspx?id=slTDN7CF9UeyIge0jXdO48pr_29hyJFKpCZ7SYYvjeFUNUVPMUk0STlDRlJMNklIWEI3V0NZVTZXVS4u&amp;route=shorturl" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-success btn-lg">Subscribe to the community</a><a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">Contribute</a><a href="./newsletter.pdf" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">PDF Version</a></p>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>newsletter</category>
  <category>professional development</category>
  <category>data science discussion</category>
  <guid>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_10/newsletter.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Professional Development Newsletter September 2024</title>
  <dc:creator>Jennifer Struthers</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Divya Balasubramanian</dc:creator>
  <link>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_09/newsletter.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/images/banner_sept.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Welcome to the latest Professional Development newsletter, brought to you by the Data Science skilled team Professional Development Functional Team.</p>
<p>The newsletter team are always happy to receive constructive feedback, and we invite you to send us any contributions you may have.</p>
<p>There are some legacy NHS Digital items which we have identified with❗</p>
<p>If you cannot access something of interest to you, please <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new" target="_blank">reach out</a>.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading! – PD newsletter team</p>
<section id="civil-service-data-challenge-success" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Civil Service Data Challenge Success!</h1>
</section>
<p><em>Divya Balasubramanian (below, third from left) recently led her team to an amazing second place at the Civil Service Data Challenge. Read about the challenge and her experience below.</em></p>
<p float="center">
<img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_09/Public sector team.jfif" alt="Public Sector Team" width="465"> <img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_09/logo_chatgpt.jpg" alt="AI Generated Logo for " width="310">
</p>
<p>I was a part of one of the teams who were finalists at the <a href="https://datachallenge.uk/">civil service data challenge</a> (CSDC) which is an annual event where teams come together to pitch innovative ideas to secure funding. Think of it like Dragon’s Den or Shark Tank but with friendlier judges who are all senior data leaders from across the public sector. A multidisciplinary team chosen from the applicants across public sector were tasked to build a product roadmap for RouteCare, an NHS geospatial tool, that can be pitched for funding. We were among the four finalists, and we came a close second place (still gutted!). While it meant we didn’t receive the funding, it was a huge achievement for the team! We were also the only all-women-panel which inspired several members of the audience who kindly congratulated us for our presentation - a highlight for me.</p>
<p>Now for some behind the scenes. This was not a hackathon but an entire “side” project involving multiple stakeholders. Once we were selected after the semi-finals, each team was allocated a mentor from the judging panel and ours was John Quinn, Chief Information Officer, NHS England. This helped in securing senior management buy-in straightaway, however expanded the vision of the product. John’s involvement opened several doors for us including obtaining buy-in from Helen Balsdon, Chief Nursing Information Officer, NHS England and partnership with Google to further build this tool.</p>
<p>We however lost a few team members to churn, and I took on the leadership of the tool. This was an excellent opportunity to pick up skills including different styles of leadership (technical and motivational), influencing senior stakeholders, collaboration with team members with diverse backgrounds, commercial negotiation and most of all, public speaking (presenting to a 200-member audience whilst being filmed isn’t my idea of fun).</p>
<p>I would highly recommend applying for the next cohort of CSDC if you would like an overall development opportunity which is unique and will certainly be a valuable experience for your career!</p>
<hr>
<section id="events" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Events</h1>
</section>
<p>Lots of exciting things coming up! <a href="mailto:datascience@nhs.net">Contact Us</a> if there’s a specific event you think would be great advertise in the next newsletter!</p>
<section id="ons-local-presents-health-foundation-local-authority-dashboard" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ons-local-presents-health-foundation-local-authority-dashboard"><a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/ons-local-presents-health-foundation-local-authority-dashboard-tickets-1009106945037?aff=ebdsoporgprofile&amp;_gl=1*ktmjn*_up*MQ..*_ga*MTAyMzgwNDY5OS4xNzI3MjYwMTgx*_ga_TQVES5V6SH*MTcyNzI2MDE4MC4xLjAuMTcyNzI2MDE4MC4wLjAuMA.." target="_blank">ONS Local presents: Health Foundation local authority dashboard</a></h3>
<p><strong>Tuesday 1st October, 09:15-10:00, Online</strong></p>
<p>The presentation will be focused on the Health Foundation Local Authority Dashboard, an interactive tool which brings together data and insights on the state of health and health inequalities across all local authorities in England.</p>
<p>This event is open to all; we anticipate it will be of most interest to anyone working on health indicators at a local level.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-turing-lectures-can-we-trust-ai" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-turing-lectures-can-we-trust-ai"><a href="https://www.turing.ac.uk/events/turing-lectures-can-we-trust-ai" target="_blank">The Turing Lectures: Can we trust AI?</a></h3>
<p><strong>Monday 14th October, 19:30-21:30, In person (London) AND online</strong></p>
<p>Is AI eroding public confidence in technology? Can AI be trustworthy? In the second Turing Lecture, Abeba Birhane will unpack the biases in data and its downstream impact on AI systems and shows how it can lead to unfair outcomes in our daily lives.</p>
<p>She’ll look at why this happens, why it’s such a big issue and how researchers, activists and policy makers are tackling the problem.</p>
<p>By the end of this talk, you’ll have an improved understanding of the AI systems that increasingly shape our world. You’ll be better equipped to ask critical questions about AI technologies and understand why rigorous testing of AI systems and accountability of tech corporations is so crucial - no matter your background, you’ll learn something valuable.</p>
<p><strong>Online: Free</strong></p>
<p><strong>In person: £10 (covers drinks and nibbles)</strong></p>
</section>
<section id="data-science-festival-oktoberfest" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-science-festival-oktoberfest"><a href="https://datasciencefestival.com/event/oktoberfest-2024/" target="_blank">Data Science Festival: Oktoberfest</a></h3>
<p><strong>Saturday 19th October 2024, 9am-5pm, CodeNode London</strong></p>
<p>Apply for a FREE ballot entry to this years DSF Oktoberfest. Top tech speakers, incredible partners and a thriving community. There will be a mixture of talks featured at the festival, covering all things data (science, engineering, etc) and a variety of technical levels.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLwzX3WM0AfxopbhVhGCA373Xk-7wNhLfq" target="_blank">Check out highlights from last year here.</a></p>
</section>
<section id="nhs-rpysoc-2024-conference" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="nhs-rpysoc-2024-conference"><a href="https://nhsrcommunity.com/events/nhs-r-nhs-pycom-open-source-conference-nhs-rpysoc-2024-2024-ticket-for-in-person-attendance-on-thursday-21-november-2024/" target="_blank">NHS RPySOC 2024 Conference</a></h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 21st-22nd November, 9am-5pm, in-person (Birmingham) / Online</strong></p>
<p>The <strong>NHS RPySOC 2024 conference</strong> is open for registration now! It will be on <strong>21st &amp; 22nd November in Birmingham</strong>. This is jointly hosted by the NHS R Community and NHS.pycom, and also promotes Open Source.</p>
<ul>
<li>Day 1 will be a mixture of presentations, workshops and lightening talks</li>
<li>Day 2 will be ‘Unconference’ with suggestions for topics being taken on day 1.</li>
</ul>
<p>It’s a great chance to show off our work, share our learning with a like minded community and learn a few things yourself, such as the state of the industry and how techniques are being applied elsewhere.</p>
<p>You can either attend:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://nhsrcommunity.com/events/nhs-r-nhs-pycom-open-source-conference-nhs-rpysoc-2024-2024-ticket-for-in-person-attendance-on-thursday-21-november-2024/">In-Person (The ICC, Hall 11, Birmingham B1 2EA</a> (Sold Out: Waiting List Only)</li>
<li><a href="https://nhsrcommunity.com/events/nhs-r-nhs-pycom-open-source-conference-2024-rpysoc-2024-ticket-for-virtual-attendance-on-thursday-21-november-2024/">Online</a></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>See more future events on our <a href="https://future.nhs.uk/DataAnalytics/view?objectID=54053296" target="_blank">FutureNHS page</a> - scroll down to “Our Events” to see the calendar</p>
<p>Know of any events we should feature next month? Let us know by clicking the “Contribute” button, or <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="knowledge-sharing" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Knowledge Sharing</h1>
</section>
<section id="python-in-an-hour" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="python-in-an-hour">Python in an hour</h2>
<p>Have you been stuck in an Excel rut for years and want to try out something new? Or maybe you have a team you are trying to convince of the wonders of python, but need to show them quickly what it can do.</p>
<p>Check out the <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/python-in-an-hour" target="_blank">Python in an Hour Git repo</a>. It can be run either on GitHub codespaces, or Google Colab, completely for free - you just need an account. See a simple data pipeline, from importing, to procesing, to outputting graphs, all done just with a few clicks.</p>
</section>
<section id="past-analystx-ds-huddles" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="past-analystx-ds-huddles">Past AnalystX DS Huddles</h2>
<p>Check out some recordings of previous talks we have been hosting - also known as Huddles! These talks cover a range of data science topics with a range of speakers, both internal and external to the NHS.</p>
<p>Check them out on our <a href="https://future.nhs.uk/DataAnalytics/view?objectID=56936784" target="_blank">FutureNHS page</a>.</p>
<p>Have a topic you’d be keen to share? <a href="mailto:datascience@nhs.net?subject=PD%20FT%20AnalystX%20DS%20Huddle">Contact us</a> and let us know!</p>
<hr>
<p>Check out all the resources in the <a href="https://future.nhs.uk/DataAnalytics/view?objectID=56293968" target="_blank">Resources</a> page on our FutureNHS page! Can you spot something missing? <a href="mailto:datascience@nhs.net">Contact us</a>!</p>
</section>
<section id="need-a-quick-break" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Need a Quick Break?</h1>
</section>
<p><a href="https://mywordle.strivemath.com/?word=earjp" target="_blank">How many tries will it take you?</a></p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<p><a href="https://forms.office.com/pages/responsepage.aspx?id=slTDN7CF9UeyIge0jXdO48pr_29hyJFKpCZ7SYYvjeFUNUVPMUk0STlDRlJMNklIWEI3V0NZVTZXVS4u&amp;route=shorturl" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-success btn-lg">Subscribe to the community</a><a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">Contribute</a><a href="./newsletter.pdf" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">PDF Version</a></p>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>newsletter</category>
  <category>Civil Service Data Challenge</category>
  <guid>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_09/newsletter.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Professional Development Newsletter August 2024</title>
  <dc:creator>Jennifer Struthers</dc:creator>
  <link>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_08/newsletter.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/images/banner_august.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Welcome to the latest Professional Development newsletter, brought to you by the Data Science skilled team Professional Development Functional Team.</p>
<p>The newsletter team are always happy to receive constructive feedback, and we invite you to send us any contributions you may have.</p>
<p>There are some legacy NHS Digital items which we have identified with❗</p>
<p>If you cannot access something of interest to you, please <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new" target="_blank">reach out</a>.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading! – PD newsletter team</p>
<section id="haca-2024-relive-the-experience" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>HACA 2024: Relive the experience</h1>
</section>
<section id="haca-2024-relive-the-experience-1" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="haca-2024-relive-the-experience-1">HACA 2024: Relive the experience</h2>
<p>Couldn’t make the event in person? Had to pick between two presentations on at the same time? No worries - the Health and Care Analytics conference hosted in July recorded all their presentations and has now uploaded them onto their YouTube channel, and can be easily accessed from <a href="https://haca-conference.nhs.uk/programme/" target="_blank">their site</a>.</p>
<p>HACA was also full of amazing posters on a wide range of topics, so many it was hard to read them all! You can check out the posters on <a href="https://haca-conference.nhs.uk/haca-24-posters/" target="_blank">their site</a> as well.</p>
</section>
<section id="events" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Events</h1>
</section>
<p>Lots of exciting things coming up! See the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/calendars" target="_blank">full calendar here</a>❗, and a small selection below.</p>
<section id="code-dependent---data-ethics-and-society-reading-group" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="code-dependent---data-ethics-and-society-reading-group"><a href="https://www.tickettailor.com/events/dataethics/1292240/r/gss" target="_blank">Code Dependent - Data Ethics and Society Reading Group</a></h3>
<p><strong>Wednesday 4th September, 13:00-14:00, Teams</strong></p>
<p>We will be discussing Code Dependent by Madhumita Murgia:</p>
<p>The lives of a British poet, an Uber Eats courier in Pittsburgh, an Indian doctor, and a Chinese activist in exile are linked by their unexpected encounters with AI. In this book Madhumita Murgia, AI Editor at the FT, highlights the voices of ordinary people, to show how automated systems are reshaping lives all over the world, from technology that marks children as future criminals to an app that is helping to give diagnoses to a remote trial community.</p>
<p>See <a href="https://data-ethics-and-society.github.io/data-ethics-and-society-reading-group/" target="_blank">our GitHub page</a> for more information. Registration closes Friday 23rd August 17:00</p>
</section>
<section id="health-data-science-seminar-series-transforming-healthcare-ai-in-health-data-science" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="health-data-science-seminar-series-transforming-healthcare-ai-in-health-data-science"><a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/health-data-science-seminar-series-tickets-947750486217?aff=ebdssbdestsearch" target="_blank">Health Data Science Seminar Series: Transforming Healthcare: AI in Health Data Science</a></h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 12th September 2024, 14:00 - 15:30, Teams</strong></p>
<p>This series of seminars presents an exciting opportunity to hear about recent developments in health data science, generate ideas and help build the health data science community. It is hosted by the ONS’s Data Science Campus and Health Analysis Team in partnership with Health Data Research UK (HDR UK).</p>
<p>The Health Data Science Seminar series provides a dedicated space for data scientists, policymakers, health professionals, academics, epidemiologists, statisticians and other members of the data science community to come together and explore the potential of data science, to help improve health and health policy.</p>
<p>This event will feature presentations from guest speakers including:</p>
<p>Dr Siegfried Karl Wagner - Ophthalmologist and senior research fellow, University College London Professor Christopher Yau - Professor of Artificial Intelligence and Turing AI Fellow, University of Oxford</p>
</section>
<section id="python-elt-with-dlt-zero-to-hero-workshop" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="python-elt-with-dlt-zero-to-hero-workshop"><a href="https://lu.ma/ozfm3thk" target="_blank">Python ELT with dlt: Zero to Hero workshop</a></h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 19th September, Thursday 26th September, 17:00-19:00, Online</strong></p>
<p>A zero-to-hero workshop for learning ELT, dlt and advanced features around it. The goal is to have you walk away with the ability and understanding to build robust ELT pipelines. This will essentially upskill your Python EL ability from just learning to senior data (platform) engineer level.</p>
<p>This is a two-part workshop, with a target audience of data platform engineers, Python First data engineers, and Python normies who want to learn best practice data engineering.</p>
</section>
<section id="data-science-festival-oktoberfest" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-science-festival-oktoberfest"><a href="https://datasciencefestival.com/event/oktoberfest-2024/" target="_blank">Data Science Festival: Oktoberfest</a></h3>
<p><strong>Saturday 19th October 2024, 9am-5pm, CodeNode London</strong></p>
<p>Apply for a FREE ballot entry to this years DSF Oktoberfest. Top tech speakers, incredible partners and a thriving community. There will be a mixture of talks featured at the festival, covering all things data (science, engineering, etc) and a variety of technical levels.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLwzX3WM0AfxopbhVhGCA373Xk-7wNhLfq" target="_blank">Check out highlights from last year here.</a></p>
</section>
<section id="nhs-rpysoc-2024-conference" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="nhs-rpysoc-2024-conference"><a href="https://nhsrcommunity.com/events/nhs-r-nhs-pycom-open-source-conference-nhs-rpysoc-2024-2024-ticket-for-in-person-attendance-on-thursday-21-november-2024/" target="_blank">NHS RPySOC 2024 Conference</a></h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 21st-22nd November, 9am-5pm, in-person (Birmingham) / Online</strong></p>
<p>The <strong>NHS RPySOC 2024 conference</strong> is open for registration now! It will be on <strong>21st &amp; 22nd November in Birmingham</strong>. This is jointly hosted by the NHS R Community and NHS.pycom, and also promotes Open Source.</p>
<ul>
<li>Day 1 will be a mixture of presentations, workshops and lightening talks</li>
<li>Day 2 will be ‘Unconference’ with suggestions for topics being taken on day 1.</li>
</ul>
<p>It’s a great chance to show off our work, share our learning with a like minded community and learn a few things yourself, such as the state of the industry and how techniques are being applied elsewhere.</p>
<p>You can either attend:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://nhsrcommunity.com/events/nhs-r-nhs-pycom-open-source-conference-nhs-rpysoc-2024-2024-ticket-for-in-person-attendance-on-thursday-21-november-2024/">In-Person (The ICC, Hall 11, Birmingham B1 2EA</a> (Sold Out: Waiting List Only)</li>
<li><a href="https://nhsrcommunity.com/events/nhs-r-nhs-pycom-open-source-conference-2024-rpysoc-2024-ticket-for-virtual-attendance-on-thursday-21-november-2024/">Online</a></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>See more future events on our <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Events+calendar" target="_blank">confluence calendar</a>❗</p>
<p>Know of any events we should feature next month? Let us know by clicking the “Contribute” button, or <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="data-science-discussion-democracy" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Data Science Discussion: Democracy</h1>
</section>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_08/robot_parliament.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Cartoon image of a future UK parliament filled with robots</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Recently, we held another Data Science Discussion, where we encourage people to look into a different area or use case of data science than they might strictly look at in their day job and spark discussion on a peer-to-peer level.</p>
<p>This time we delved into the intriguing topic of data science and democracy, hosted by Mia Noonan.</p>
<p>Mia kicked off the discussion by asking the group to consider the different ways data science could interact with and potentially reshape the political landscape. One of the key ideas presented was the concept of AI-driven profiles that could be created based on an individual’s opinions and values, with the potential to vote on bills and acts on their behalf. This led to a lively debate on the implications of such a system, and what type of democracy we’d like to see AI help facilitate- representative, direct or deliberative.</p>
<p>Throughout the session, the group expressed a healthy dose of skepticism, particularly regarding the biases inherent in large language models (LLMs) and AI systems. Concerns were raised about the potential for AI to reflect and even exacerbate existing biases, as well as the broader implications for democracy and personal agency. The discussion highlighted the complex and often controversial nature of combining AI with politics, but also the potential for innovative applications that could transform how we engage with governance.</p>
<p>The Professional Development Functional Team is excited to continue hosting these monthly Data Science Discussions. If you have a data science topic you’re passionate about and would like to share with others, please reach out to us to host a session. The format is designed to be collaborative and conversational, with most of the session taking place in breakout rooms, so all you need is a spark of inspiration to get the conversation started.</p>
<p>Interested in learning a bit more about this topic?</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CyGWML6cI_k" target="_blank">A TED talk on ‘automating’ politicians</a></li>
<li><a href="https://blogs.bath.ac.uk/iprblog/2024/02/22/how-ai-could-help-citizens-assemblies-make-well-informed-decisions/" target="_blank">How LLMs could help citizens assemblies</a></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>Stay tuned for an update on what seminars &amp; show and tells will look like in the new team. Please bear with us as it is likely to be a learning process! Contact <a href="mailto:amelia.noonan1@nhs.net">Mia Noonan</a> for more information.</p>
<section id="training-opportunities" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Training Opportunities</h1>
</section>
<section id="large-language-model-tutorial" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="large-language-model-tutorial">Large Language Model Tutorial</h2>
<p>Curious about how you could create your own LLM but worried it’ll be too complicated or costly? Adam and Sam Hollings have put together an LLM tutorial to walk you through some simple implementations. The software is all free and runs inside Google Collab, so it won’t cost you anything. Some ability with python will be helpful, and an interest in data science and LLMs will help!</p>
<p>Instructions for set up, or for contacting the owners can be found in <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/llm_tutorial" target="_blank">this GitHub repository</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="technical-writing-courses" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="technical-writing-courses">Technical Writing Courses</h2>
<p>Sometimes when we spend most days writing code we forget a huge part of our jobs is communicating our work and documenting it. <a href="https://developers.google.com/tech-writing" target="_blank">Google have a collection of courses and learning resources</a> aiming to improve your technical documentation skills. Learn how to plan and author technical documents. You can also learn about the role of technical writers at Google.</p>
</section>
<section id="need-a-quick-break" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Need a Quick Break?</h1>
</section>
<p><a href="https://mywordle.strivemath.com/?word=hcxln" target="_blank">How many tries will it take you?</a></p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<p><a href="https://forms.office.com/pages/responsepage.aspx?id=slTDN7CF9UeyIge0jXdO48pr_29hyJFKpCZ7SYYvjeFUNUVPMUk0STlDRlJMNklIWEI3V0NZVTZXVS4u&amp;route=shorturl" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-success btn-lg">Subscribe to the community</a><a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">Contribute</a><a href="./newsletter.pdf" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">PDF Version</a></p>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>newsletter</category>
  <guid>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_08/newsletter.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Professional Development Newsletter July 2024</title>
  <dc:creator>Jennifer Struthers</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Warren Davies</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Liz Kelly</dc:creator>
  <link>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_07/newsletter.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/images/banner_july.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Welcome to the latest Professional Development newsletter, brought to you by the Data Science skilled team Professional Development Functional Team.</p>
<p>The newsletter team are always happy to receive constructive feedback, and we invite you to send us any contributions you may have.</p>
<p>There are some legacy NHS Digital items which we have identified with❗</p>
<p>If you cannot access something of interest to you, please <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new" target="_blank">reach out</a>.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading! – PD newsletter team</p>
<section id="health-and-care-analytics-conference" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Health and Care Analytics Conference</h1>
</section>
<p><em>This month some of the NHS England Data Science team went to the Health and Care Analytics Conference (HACA) 2024, hosted in Telford. The team had various talks, posters and workshops delivered at the conference about our work and projects. Warren Davies reports back.</em></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_07/warren_talk.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>NHS England RAP Star Warren Davies giving a talk at HACA on RAP Principles</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>At the HACA conference 2024 I gave a talk on RAP to a huge crowd, over 4,000 people, great people, the best people. OK more like 70. And I also helped run workshops on Python and RAP. I highly recommend the experience overall. I gained the following XP:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>+10 Planning</strong> – it’s tricky to plan when you don’t know in advance the size and experience of the audience (in the workshops we opted to give a flavour of what was possible, along with some simple exercises people could follow along with).</p></li>
<li><p><strong>+10 Schmoozing</strong> – it is actually very easy. People are very happy to talk about their work and how you might be able to help them.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>+20 Resilience</strong> – public speaking can be nerve wracking but that is OK, it’s just weakness leaving the body.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>But you also have the opportunity to help other people. It’s easy to take for granted in NHS England that we basically have a huge bunch of geniuses at our beck and call that that we can pester and learn from every day. But not every analyst in the wider NHS and health world is so lucky. Within trusts and regional organisations, there are often small teams - or even individuals - who do similar work to us but don’t have the kind of support we do.</p>
<p>With events like HACA we have the chance to connect with them, and point them to resources and communities they might not know about. Which not only helps them, but gives you a warm fuzzy feeling inside too (incidentally, it also ticks a whole load of those “Sharing knowledge” boxes on the competency framework…).</p>
<p>You should definitely go next time. You will build your networking skills, help people out, and get loads of great examples you can use when you apply for that promotion. Plus, everyone loves a road trip right?</p>
<section id="school-placement" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>School Placement</h1>
</section>
<p>In July, the NHS England Data Science Professional Development Functional Team hosted a school placement, hosting five students from a London based secondary school to teach them about our work and show them some of the skills they would need to start a career in data science. Liz Kelly describes her experience, working to prepare this week to show the school pupils what our team does, and give them a taste of how it might be to work with us.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_07/school.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Some really happy cartoon kids on a school placement, ready to learn about the NHS England Data Science team.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>This was a rewarding yet difficult task, involving a lot of admin, paperwork, and even a conversation with NHS England lawyers to check we were dotting all our i’s and crossing all our t’s. Naturally, after all this, there were still the dreaded tech setup issues (<em>sigh</em>). But Chaeyoon did an amazing job at fixing them in record time, so the students could still get the most out of their placement.</p>
<p>As a graduate in the Data Science team, I know first-hand how valuable it is for colleagues to take time to explain the various cogs in the NHS system. Because let’s be honest, it’s a bit complicated. So, we made sure to cover as many areas as possible to help with this understanding.</p>
<p>About half of the data scientists (a total of 22) met students during the placement week, alongside more indirect engagements from others such as helping with the training materials. The students rotated through four data science teams and were introduced to two methods of data science ways of working: python programming and collaborative works on GitHub. At the end of the placement week, they had a mock interview and an optional task to build a classifier function with if-else conditions to find which group (from the placement sessions) they could match to the session information. It is incredible to think some of the students had never touched programming before and yet, by the end of the week, they had a basic understanding of Python!</p>
<p>I personally enjoyed the challenge of organising the timetable for the students and leading them through workshops and career talks. Who doesn’t love a good to-do list! And since I don’t cover this kind of outreach in my day-to-day role, this was an excellent opportunity. I could tick off those leadership and mentoring competencies, not to mention dealing with complexity (those pesky access and tech issues). I will admit, teaching a group over Teams is trickier than I thought, especially interactive sessions. The students were eager to discuss and answer questions but sometimes their meeting room microphone didn’t quite catch what they were saying … or perhaps it was just me and the London accent.</p>
<p>As this was the first of its kind, it took a while to discover all the rules and policies. Now we have done this once, subsequent placements should be a lot easier to host. We have collated the resources used <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/PD_kanban_board/blob/main/PD%20Outreach/Host%20a%20placement.md" target="_blank">here</a>, currently accessible to those in NHSE DS GitHub team. We are working to collate and publish our resources more widely in the future.</p>
<p>As soon as we say “I work for the NHS”, peoples first thoughts are frontline staff, not data scientists. It wasn’t until I was graduating university that I stumbled across data science roles in the NHS and even then, it was purely accidental. When I think back to my time at school I would have loved to do this work experience week in the NHS.</p>
<p>I know I am not alone when I say just how important it is to introduce young people to Data Science, particularly in the NHS. This provides them with more avenues to follow and more ideas of what is out there. It makes the world of possibilities just that bit bigger.</p>
<p>Once again, thank you to everyone involved. I’m sure you’ll agree the placement week was a success, just perhaps short of a few tea and biscuit breaks. The students are not used to being at a desk all day!</p>
<section id="events" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Events</h1>
</section>
<p>Lots of exciting things coming up! See the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/calendars" target="_blank">full calendar here</a>❗</p>
<section id="practical-applications-of-generative-ai-building-a-chatbot-answering-questions-about-your-documents." class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="practical-applications-of-generative-ai-building-a-chatbot-answering-questions-about-your-documents."><a href="https://datasciencefestival.com/session/dunnhumby-talk/" target="_blank">Practical applications of Generative AI: building a chatbot answering questions about your documents.</a></h3>
<p><strong>Tuesday 13th August 2024, 13:00 - 14:00, Online</strong></p>
<p>The recent explosion on the scene of Generative AI and Large Language Models (LLMs) is creating a vast array of opportunities. There is more than one way to leverage this recent breakthrough. You can create a chatbot by directly “plugging” to a LLM and start asking questions. However, LLMs are limited to the information available in the data they have seen during their training. So how to build a chatbot that will be able to answer questions related to documents that the model has never seen. One solution is to use a technique called “Retrieval Augmented Generation” (RAG). After an introduction of Generative AI and transformers, we will go through the RAG logic and explore its benefits and potential drawbacks. The talk is intended for anyone interested in generative AI and its potential applications.</p>
</section>
<section id="translational-science-methods-club-explainable-ai" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="translational-science-methods-club-explainable-ai"><a href="https://www.turing.ac.uk/events/translational-science-methods-club-explainable-ai" target="_blank">Translational Science Methods Club: Explainable AI</a></h3>
<p><strong>Tuesday 20th Aug 2024, 15:30 - 17:00, Virtual Seminar</strong></p>
<p>The theme of this T-SciM event will be explainable AI (XAI). This refers to a range of approaches that seek to design or evaluate ways to make the outputs of artificial intelligence algorithms more interpretable. Such explainability is important to better understand the mechanisms underlying the models computations and determine how trustworthy and generalisable their results are.</p>
<p>We will be joined by 3 speakers, who will give short talks introducing their work on XAI, followed by a panel discussion with questions and prompts from the audience.</p>
<p>Speakers include: Dr Ahmed Salih, Dr Tapabrata (Rohan) Chakraborty and Sophie Martin (ex-PhD intern with the NHSE DS team).</p>
</section>
<section id="health-data-science-seminar-series-transforming-healthcare-ai-in-health-data-science" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="health-data-science-seminar-series-transforming-healthcare-ai-in-health-data-science"><a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/health-data-science-seminar-series-tickets-947750486217?aff=ebdssbdestsearch" target="_blank">Health Data Science Seminar Series: Transforming Healthcare: AI in Health Data Science</a></h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 12th September 2024, 14:00 - 15:30, Teams</strong></p>
<p>This series of seminars presents an exciting opportunity to hear about recent developments in health data science, generate ideas and help build the health data science community. It is hosted by the ONS’s Data Science Campus and Health Analysis Team in partnership with Health Data Research UK (HDR UK).</p>
<p>The Health Data Science Seminar series provides a dedicated space for data scientists, policymakers, health professionals, academics, epidemiologists, statisticians and other members of the data science community to come together and explore the potential of data science, to help improve health and health policy.</p>
<p>This event will feature presentations from guest speakers including:</p>
<p>Dr Siegfried Karl Wagner - Ophthalmologist and senior research fellow, University College London Professor Christopher Yau - Professor of Artificial Intelligence and Turing AI Fellow, University of Oxford</p>
</section>
<section id="data-science-festival-oktoberfest" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-science-festival-oktoberfest"><a href="https://datasciencefestival.com/event/oktoberfest-2024/" target="_blank">Data Science Festival: Oktoberfest</a></h3>
<p><strong>Saturday 19th October 2024, 9am-5pm, CodeNode London</strong></p>
<p>Apply for a FREE ballot entry to this years DSF Oktoberfest. Top tech speakers, incredible partners and a thriving community. There will be a mixture of talks featured at the festival, covering all things data (science, engineering, etc) and a variety of technical levels.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLwzX3WM0AfxopbhVhGCA373Xk-7wNhLfq" target="_blank">Check out highlights from last year here.</a></p>
</section>
<section id="nhs-rpysoc-2024-conference---registration-opened" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="nhs-rpysoc-2024-conference---registration-opened"><a href="https://nhsrcommunity.com/events/nhs-r-nhs-pycom-open-source-conference-nhs-rpysoc-2024-2024-ticket-for-in-person-attendance-on-thursday-21-november-2024/" target="_blank">NHS RPySOC 2024 Conference - registration opened</a></h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 21st-22nd November, 9am-5pm, in-person (Birmingham) / Online</strong></p>
<p>The <strong>NHS RPySOC 2024 conference</strong> is open for registration now! It will be on <strong>21st &amp; 22nd November in Birmingham</strong>. This is jointed hosted by the NHS R Community and NHS.pycom, and also promotes Open Source.</p>
<ul>
<li>Day 1 will be a mixture of presentations, workshops and lightening talks</li>
<li>Day 2 <strong>(in-person only)</strong> will be ‘Unconference’ with suggestions for topics being taken on day 1.</li>
</ul>
<p>It’s a great chance to show off our work, share our learning with a like minded community and learn a few things yourself, such as the state of the industry and how techniques are being applied elsewhere.</p>
<p>You can either attend:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://nhsrcommunity.com/events/nhs-r-nhs-pycom-open-source-conference-nhs-rpysoc-2024-2024-ticket-for-in-person-attendance-on-thursday-21-november-2024/">In-Person (The ICC, Hall 11, Birmingham B1 2EA</a></li>
<li><a href="https://nhsrcommunity.com/events/nhs-r-nhs-pycom-open-source-conference-2024-rpysoc-2024-ticket-for-virtual-attendance-on-thursday-21-november-2024/">Online</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong><a href="https://nhsrway.nhsrcommunity.com/conference.html#rpysoc-24-conference---call-for-abstracts" target="_blank">Got something to present? Abstract submissions deadline extended to Monday 12th August!</a></strong></p>
<hr>
<p>See more future events on our <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Events+calendar" target="_blank">confluence calendar</a>❗ Know of any events we should feature next month? Let us know by clicking the “Contribute” button, or <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="digital-health-hive" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Digital Health Hive</h1>
</section>
<p>Yorkshire based, and interested in joining a community of patients, healthcare professionals and decision makers, companies, and researchers with an interest in digital health, and engaging and interacting with one another to develop digital health research and tools? Join the Digital Health Hive by completing <a href="https://forms.office.com/e/B0gNDcYYNT" target="_blank">this form</a> or emailing <a href="mailto:digitalhealthhive@leeds.ac.uk">digitalhealthhive@leeds.ac.uk</a></p>
<div class="text-center">
<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_07/digital_health_hive.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div>
<hr>
<section id="need-a-quick-break" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Need a Quick Break?</h1>
</section>
<p><a href="https://mywordle.strivemath.com/?word=yzvdy" target="_blank">How many tries will it take you?</a></p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<p><a href="https://forms.office.com/pages/responsepage.aspx?id=slTDN7CF9UeyIge0jXdO48pr_29hyJFKpCZ7SYYvjeFUNUVPMUk0STlDRlJMNklIWEI3V0NZVTZXVS4u&amp;route=shorturl" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-success btn-lg">Subscribe to the community</a><a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">Contribute</a><a href="./newsletter.pdf" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">PDF Version</a></p>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>newsletter</category>
  <guid>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_07/newsletter.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Professional Development Newsletter June 2024</title>
  <dc:creator>Jennifer Struthers</dc:creator>
  <link>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_06/newsletter.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/images/banner_june.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Welcome to the latest Professional Development newsletter, brought to you by the Data Science skilled team Professional Development Functional Team.</p>
<p>The newsletter team are always happy to receive constructive feedback, and we invite you to send us any contributions you may have.</p>
<p>There are some legacy NHS Digital items which we have identified with❗</p>
<p>If you cannot access something of interest to you, please <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new" target="_blank">reach out</a>.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading! – PD newsletter team</p>
<section id="highlights" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Highlights</h1>
</section>
<section id="national-competency-framework-tool" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="national-competency-framework-tool"><a href="https://future.nhs.uk/DataAnalytics/view?objectID=163018181" target="_blank">National Competency Framework Tool</a></h2>
<p>The Professional Development Function Team want to promote the National Competency Framework Tool to help shape your objectives for the year ahead.</p>
<p>You can use this tool in any way you like:</p>
<ul>
<li>Do a full self-assessment to build a personal profile of yourself, marking areas where you want to target your development and understanding where you measure up against job bands.</li>
<li>Review areas where you are interested in developing; we recommend checking out the additional modules of the framework covering:
<ul>
<li>Specialised technical skills that you may have developed in a unique role within a team, like Data Visualisation, Machine Learning, or Data Automation.</li>
<li>Broader professional skill areas such as Behaviours, Leadership and Management, and Working in Team that apply across roles regardless of background.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>See where you stand for other job areas like Data Analysis and Data Engineering.</li>
</ul>
<p>While this framework is still in the early stages of adoption, feedback is key to help the Professional Development Function Team and the National Competency Framework team develop more resources. Let us know if and how you are using the tool, or any other ways we can help you use the National Competency Framework <a href="https://forms.office.com/e/XGuTzWcB5j" target="_blank">through this form</a></p>
</section>
<section id="masters-in-research-mres-in-data-science-analytics-for-health" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="masters-in-research-mres-in-data-science-analytics-for-health">Masters in Research (MRes) in Data Science &amp; Analytics for Health</h2>
<p>Applications now open for this funded course -the short application form can be found <a href="https://forms.office.com/e/21dmLrdn4k" target="_blank">here</a>. For more information, please see this <a href="https://nhs.sharepoint.com/:w:/r/sites/X24_DataAnalytics/Shared%20Documents/CPD%20opportunities/Masters%20in%20Research%20frequently%20asked%20questions%20doc.docx?d=w189258124ad541b89217f28fa199c587&amp;csf=1&amp;web=1&amp;e=BlEfB8&amp;xsdata=MDV8MDJ8amVubmlmZXIuc3RydXRoZXJzMUBuaHMubmV0fDNiYjM0YTJlNDBiZTQxZDBhZWFiMDhkYzk2NzgwYTdlfDM3YzM1NGIyODViMDQ3ZjViMjIyMDdiNDhkNzc0ZWUzfDB8MHw2Mzg1NTA2OTA3MjgyMzA0NzF8VW5rbm93bnxUV0ZwYkdac2IzZDhleUpXSWpvaU1DNHdMakF3TURBaUxDSlFJam9pVjJsdU16SWlMQ0pCVGlJNklrMWhhV3dpTENKWFZDSTZNbjA9fDB8fHw%3d&amp;sdata=RW1RSE9sOCsrbS9OZG82L1Y5bnBEeXRFMlZhaldoTkJwWE9GZXZLRFRhYz0%3d">FAQ document</a>. This is a fantastic opportunity for those who want to deepen their expertise in data science and analytics, with a specific focus on a health data research project. The syllabus will include campus-based or remote lectures and practical-based training in:</p>
<ul>
<li>Machine learning</li>
<li>Artificial Intelligence</li>
<li>Programming for Data Science</li>
<li>Data Science &amp; Analytics for Causal Inference and Prediction</li>
</ul>
<p>A workplace-based research project, undertaken within NHS England, supported by the NHS England Data Science Team. A Masters course is a significant personal investment of time, a day a week will be allocated to attend university and it is anticipated that there will be three to six hours per week worth of additional study. Potential applicants should consider this before applying. It is also a substantial investment from NHS England and will therefore be subject to a rigorous, fair and transparent selection process.</p>
<p>Applications will close <strong>August 4th</strong>, and the course is due to start in <strong>October</strong>. If you have any questions, please get in touch with <a href="mailto:s.culkin@nhs.net">Sarah Culkin</a> or <a href="mailto:rupert.chaplin1@nhs.net">Rupert Chaplin</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="events" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Events</h1>
</section>
<p>Lots of exciting things coming up! See the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/calendars" target="_blank">full calendar here</a>❗</p>
<section id="data-and-ai-ethics-community-meeting-ethical-considerations-in-data-linkage-with-splink" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-and-ai-ethics-community-meeting-ethical-considerations-in-data-linkage-with-splink"><a href="https://www.tickettailor.com/events/publicsectoruk/1289987" target="_blank">Data and AI Ethics Community meeting: Ethical Considerations in Data Linkage with Splink</a></h3>
<p><strong>Tuesday 2nd July 13:00-14:00, Teams</strong></p>
<p>Splink is a Ministry of Justices open-source software which uses unsupervised machine learning to link together millions of data records belonging to justice system users. This talk will cover the many and varied ethical considerations of performing data linkage with Splink, how we address these within our work and improvements we are planning for the future. The Data Linkage Hub at NHSE is exploring the use of Splink as a probabilistic data linkage tool. Reach out if you want to know more and familiarize yourself with our pipeline.</p>
</section>
<section id="linking-analysts-in-leeds" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="linking-analysts-in-leeds">Linking Analysts In Leeds</h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 4th July 13:00-14:30, BEC Ground Floor 7&amp;8 Wellington Place and Teams</strong></p>
<p>Linking Analysts In Leeds is an opportunity for analysts working in different civil service departments in Wellington Place in Leeds to meet-up, make links, and share learning.</p>
<p>This session will involves speakers from DataCamp running a session showcasing <a href="https://www.datacamp.com" target="_blank">DataCamp</a> and the extensive training resources it offers.</p>
<p>If you wish to join the meeting please complete the following form (this covers in person and online): <a href="https://forms.office.com/pages/responsepage.aspx?id=PPdSrBr9mkqOekokjzE54W_NLvrah2tMkR4LC77BWoFUMFhKUlBEOTlBU0dQM0g2UUIyMVo4QzNWTi4u" target="_blank">Linking Analysts In Leeds - July</a></p>
</section>
<section id="london-data-week-2024" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="london-data-week-2024"><a href="https://londondataweek.org/" target="_blank">London Data Week 2024</a></h3>
<p><strong>1st-7th July 2024, Online and in person</strong></p>
<p>London Data Week is a city-wide, distributed festival of events focusing on all things data. Data is a major part of our everyday lives, and shapes many of the decisions we make – as well as the decisions that are made about us – whether we know it or not. We believe that everyone should have a seat at the table when it comes to data, and that is the guiding principle behind our core values: to be collaborative, open and inclusive. So, we invite you to be part of the conversation by joining us and our event partners at a London Data Week event.</p>
<p>Find out more about London Data Week and what events are being held <a href="https://londondataweek.org/" target="_blank">here</a></p>
</section>
<section id="health-and-care-analytics-conference-2024" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="health-and-care-analytics-conference-2024"><a href="https://haca-conference.nhs.uk/" target="_blank">Health and Care Analytics Conference 2024</a></h3>
<p><strong>23rd-24th July 2024, Telford International Centre</strong></p>
<p>The HACA conference is a celebration of the great work of health and care analysts bringing together analysts and leaders and decision makers to showcase how analysts can help leaders make high quality decisions.</p>
<p>The programme is now published - <a href="https://haca-conference.nhs.uk/programme/" target="_blank">check out what events and talks you might be interested in!</a> Beforehand, have a look at some of their <a href="https://haca-conference.nhs.uk/e-labs/" target="_blank">E-Labs, running 8th-10th July</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="nhs-rpysoc-2024-conference---registration-opened" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="nhs-rpysoc-2024-conference---registration-opened"><a href="https://nhsrcommunity.com/events/nhs-r-nhs-pycom-open-source-conference-nhs-rpysoc-2024-2024-ticket-for-in-person-attendance-on-thursday-21-november-2024/" target="_blank">NHS RPySOC 2024 Conference - registration opened</a></h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 21st-22nd November, 9am-5pm, in-person (Birmingham) / Online</strong></p>
<p>The <strong>NHS RPySOC 2024 conference</strong> is open for registration now! It will be on <strong>21st &amp; 22nd November in Birmingham</strong>. This is jointed hosted by the NHS R Community and NHS.pycom, and also promotes Open Source.</p>
<ul>
<li>Day 1 will be a mixture of presentations, workshops and lightening talks</li>
<li>Day 2 <strong>(in-person only)</strong> will be ‘Unconference’ with suggestions for topics being taken on day 1.</li>
</ul>
<p>It’s a great chance to show off our work, share our learning with a like minded community and learn a few things yourself, such as the state of the industry and how techniques are being applied elsewhere.</p>
<p>You can either attend:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://nhsrcommunity.com/events/nhs-r-nhs-pycom-open-source-conference-nhs-rpysoc-2024-2024-ticket-for-in-person-attendance-on-thursday-21-november-2024/">In-Person (The ICC, Hall 11, Birmingham B1 2EA</a></li>
<li><a href="https://nhsrcommunity.com/events/nhs-r-nhs-pycom-open-source-conference-2024-rpysoc-2024-ticket-for-virtual-attendance-on-thursday-21-november-2024/">Online</a></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>See more future events on our <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Events+calendar" target="_blank">confluence calendar</a>❗ Know of any events we should feature next month? Let us know by clicking the “Contribute” button, or <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="interview-with-a-data-scientist" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Interview with a Data Scientist</h1>
</section>
<p>Mia Noonan is a Senior Data Scientist in the NHS England Data Science team, who first joined the company as a member of the 2021 graduate cohort.</p>
<p><strong>Thank you for agreeing to be the first “Interview with a Data Scientist” for the PD newsletter! I was wondering, could you tell me a bit about your background and what motivated you to pursue a career in data science in the NHS?</strong></p>
<p>M: I did economics and politics at Uni, but after a year in finance thought this isn’t for me as I didn’t really gel with the sort of work that I was doing at the time. In contrast, I found myself really interested by the work that the IT department was doing because I could see the impact that it had on my day-to-day. For example, there was one task where I had to process a load of invoices and that would take me all afternoon and then one day they just went, <em>“Oh yeah, we’ve automated that”</em> and I was like <em>“what?!”</em> – and immediately wanted to be on the side which was doing that!</p>
<p>So that was one of my main motivations to go into computer science, and I decided to do a computer science Master’s at Bath. It was quite an intense year, but it gave me the upskilling that I needed to go into more technical roles. I got introduced to data science right at the end of that year from my final research project. It was an NLP project where I had to analyse the transcription of everything that’s said in parliament, to understand where MPs are focusing their attention. I really enjoyed it because it was a bridge between economics, politics and computer science.</p>
<p>Once I did that project I thought, <em>yeah, this is this is super cool, this is exactly where I want to be</em>. Someone I was speaking to mentioned that there was a data science team in the NHS and I was like <em>wow, I didn’t know</em> - but immediately wanted to be a part of it! I was lucky enough to get a placement in the data science team through the NHS Digital graduate scheme, and the rest is history…!</p>
<p><strong>What specific professional development tools or resources did you find most helpful in skilling up on your time of the graduate scheme?</strong></p>
<p>M: I had Kin as a line manager, so that was great. He was very, very good at articulating <a href="https://www.atlassian.com/blog/productivity/how-to-write-smart-goals" target="_blank">SMART goals</a>, and I think that really helped because the goals were so well laid out, a lot of the competencies I could just tick off on the job due to the variety of work in the data linkage enhancement team. I was lucky with my placement, my line manager, and had a lot of the things I could just do on the job, which was great.</p>
<p>In terms of technical skills, <a href="https://www.pluralsight.com/" target="_blank">Pluralsight</a> would be my bread and butter in terms of a tool and a resource to turn to just to upskill. If I’m like <em>“oh, I don’t know what an S3 bucket is, I need to do some AWS training”</em>, if there’s a specific technical skill I need to learn, I’d go to that.</p>
<p>I think I find that I probably sometimes upskill a little bit easier when I’m doing something on the job and practically applying it straight away. I really try and actively seek out the opportunities to go and upskill in other areas. I try not to be passive about my development goals and seek out the opportunities, and if there’s something that interests me, follow up on it.</p>
<p><strong>What keeps you motivated and passionate about your work and data science with the NHS?</strong></p>
<p>M: It’s really exciting just being able to continuously learn new things and be on the forefront of new disruptive technologies. I like the fact that the work we’re doing is making a real difference to the NHS, it’s great.</p>
<p>Being surrounded by such great team members also makes a big difference. The team has got so much knowledge inside of it that it’s easy to organically learn things from people. It’s a positive learning environment and has a culture of safety and openness, there’s no one in the team I would feel hesitant going to ask a question to.</p>
<p>And then also having that culture of wanting everyone to do well, makes you want to do well because you want to contribute back and create that positive cycle for the whole team and feel like you’re contributing towards that.</p>
<p><strong>The current graduates will be embarking on their End of Scheme in the next fortnight or so. What is a piece of advice that you have for them?</strong></p>
<p>M: In terms of something that’s relevant to this point in terms of their career and passing their End of Scheme I would say that my biggest piece of advice would be don’t stop being curious about things. They’ve had a really intense upskilling period where they’ve gone through two years of intense rotations, being exposed to those different areas, but don’t stop that momentum just because you’ve rolled off the scheme. Go out, speak to loads of different teams, different people, keep networking. Keep trying different projects, different things because you’ll learn more and more about what interests and motivates you, because two years sounds like a long time, but it’s really short.</p>
<p><em>This interview was edited for brevity</em></p>
<hr>
<section id="training-opportunities" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Training Opportunities</h1>
</section>
<section id="nhs-england-and-microsoft---digital-accessibility-fundamentals-training" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="nhs-england-and-microsoft---digital-accessibility-fundamentals-training"><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-gb/collections/xee0tzym2j7zqm" target="_blank">NHS England and Microsoft - Digital Accessibility Fundamentals Training</a></h2>
<p>NHS England have teamed up with Microsoft to put some training together on Accessibility Fundamentals. For more information and details on how to sign up for the training, check out the <a href="https://nhs.sharepoint.com/sites/thehub/_layouts/15/Event.aspx?ListGuid=dc2bb1a1-a738-4cfd-87a6-500fce05afe2&amp;ItemId=1595" target="_blank">post on the NHS England Hub</a>.</p>
<p>There has also been added information for the event onto the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Accessibility+Hub#AccessibilityHub-HighlightedContent" target="_blank">Accessibility Hub!</a>❗</p>
</section>
<section id="microsoft-learn-for-github" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="microsoft-learn-for-github"><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/github/" target="_blank">Microsoft Learn for GitHub</a></h2>
<p>Check out the GitHub training available on Microsoft Learn, modules available include:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-git/" target="_blank">Introduction to Git</a></li>
<li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/learn-continuous-integration-github-actions/" target="_blank">Learn continuous integration with GitHub Actions</a></li>
<li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/manage-sensitive-data-security-policies/" target="_blank">Manage sensitive data and security policies within GitHub</a></li>
<li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/create-custom-github-actions/" target="_blank">Create and publish custom GitHub actions</a></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>Check out all the resources in the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Training+Brochure" target="_blank">Training Brochure</a>! Can you spot something missing? <a href="mailto:datascience@nhs.net">Contact us</a>!</p>
</section>
<section id="need-a-quick-break" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Need a Quick Break?</h1>
</section>
<p><a href="https://mywordle.strivemath.com/?word=oyzow" target="_blank">How many tries will it take you?</a></p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<p><a href="https://forms.office.com/pages/responsepage.aspx?id=slTDN7CF9UeyIge0jXdO48pr_29hyJFKpCZ7SYYvjeFUNUVPMUk0STlDRlJMNklIWEI3V0NZVTZXVS4u&amp;route=shorturl" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-success btn-lg">Subscribe to the community</a><a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">Contribute</a><a href="./newsletter.pdf" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">PDF Version</a></p>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>newsletter</category>
  <category>interview with a data scientist</category>
  <guid>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_06/newsletter.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Professional Development Newsletter May 2024</title>
  <dc:creator>Jennifer Struthers</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sam Hollings</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ben Wallace</dc:creator>
  <link>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_05/newsletter.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/images/banner_may.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Welcome to the latest Professional Development newsletter, brought to you by the Data Science skilled team Professional Development Functional Team.</p>
<p>The newsletter team are always happy to receive constructive feedback, and we invite you to send us any contributions you may have.</p>
<p>There are some legacy NHS Digital items which we have identified with❗</p>
<p>If you cannot access something of interest to you, please <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new" target="_blank">reach out</a>.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading! – PD newsletter team</p>
<section id="events" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Events</h1>
</section>
<p>Lots of exciting things coming up! We are working on revamping the calendar and hope to have something out soon!</p>
<section id="analystx-huddle-ai-enabled-shared-care-records-using-google-cloud-to-transform-healthcare-in-yorkshire-and-humber" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analystx-huddle-ai-enabled-shared-care-records-using-google-cloud-to-transform-healthcare-in-yorkshire-and-humber"><a href="https://gbr01.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/ap/t-59584e83/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fteams.microsoft.com%2Fl%2Fmeetup-join%2F19%253ameeting_YWI5NDM0N2UtMWQyOC00ZGYwLTk0OWQtMThhOGQ4YmU3ODI0%2540thread.v2%2F0%3Fcontext%3D%257b%2522Tid%2522%253a%252237c354b2-85b0-47f5-b222-07b48d774ee3%2522%252c%2522Oid%2522%253a%2522339b2ca8-d397-48dd-a7e3-193ac2e2c2b3%2522%257d&amp;data=05%7C02%7Cjennifer.struthers1%40nhs.net%7Cc37ce647b0734e48efd108dc78400247%7C37c354b285b047f5b22207b48d774ee3%7C0%7C0%7C638517463533546585%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=Kg05YcJ4HCy%2BahlbnxDV4LgCACU7C4bEAyM9hterY3Y%3D&amp;reserved=0" target="_blank">AnalystX Huddle – AI-Enabled Shared Care Records: Using Google Cloud to transform healthcare in Yorkshire and Humber</a></h3>
<p><strong>Tuesday 21st May, 2pm-3pm, Teams</strong></p>
<p>Humber Teaching NHS Foundation Trust, Google Cloud and Deloitte are partnering to drive digital transformation in healthcare and foster innovation in the Yorkshire region with integrated shared care records, and now leveraging Generative AI for EHR search and clinical summarization. Join us for an insightful discussion focused on how Google Cloud is revolutionizing healthcare delivery in the Yorkshire and Humber region. Learn how cutting-edge cloud technologies are improving patient care, streamlining operations, and driving innovation across the NHS.</p>
</section>
<section id="analysis-without-data" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analysis-without-data"><a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/analysis-without-data-tickets-895208000227?aff=odcleoeventsincollection" target="_blank">Analysis without Data</a></h3>
<p><strong>Tuesday 21st May, 12-1pm, Online</strong></p>
<p>This session outlines work by the Ministry of Justice (MoJ)’s Better Outcomes through Linked Data (BOLD) programme Homelessness Pilot colleagues in Department for Levelling Up, Housing and Communities (DLUHC). The Better Outcomes through Linked Data programme aims to demonstrate the benefits of linked data across government. In DLUHC’s Homelessness Pilot Team, our challenge was a lack of full data access for sensitivity reasons. To overcome this, we developed a Reproducible Analytical Pipeline (RAP) for our offending and repeat homelessness projects. For the rough sleeping and drug treatment project, we took a pragmatic approach to writing a report using only aggregated data that was suppressed.</p>
<p>We shall talk about our approaches, including constructing dummy data, modular coding using Quarto (an alternative to RMarkdown) and robust statistical methods such as trimmed means.</p>
</section>
<section id="using-data-science-and-ai-to-transform-delivery-in-the-prison-system" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="using-data-science-and-ai-to-transform-delivery-in-the-prison-system"><a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/using-data-science-and-ai-to-transform-delivery-in-the-prison-system-tickets-885509080497?aff=odcleoeventsincollection" target="_blank">Using Data Science and AI to transform delivery in the prison system</a></h3>
<p><strong>Wednesday 29th May, 2-3pm, Online</strong></p>
<p>Join colleagues from the Ministry of Justice (MoJ) who work alongside other government departments and agencies to bring the principles of justice to life for everyone in society. “We are one of the largest departments with a large proportion of staff working directly to the public and tens of thousands of prison staff making decisions every day about prisoners in their care. In the Prison Data Science team, we aim to support operational decision-making by developing and deploying innovative data science tools.</p>
<p>In this session, we will show examples of how we’ve used data science and AI to transform processes within prison services”</p>
</section>
<section id="innovation-in-analysis-with-professor-sir-ian-diamond" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="innovation-in-analysis-with-professor-sir-ian-diamond"><a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/innovation-in-analysis-with-professor-sir-ian-diamond-tickets-904642649517?aff=odcleoeventsincollection" target="_blank">Innovation in analysis with Professor Sir Ian Diamond</a></h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 30th May, 2:30-3:30pm, Online</strong></p>
<p>Join us to reflect on the innovative topics raised throughout a fantastic AiG Month and consider the importance of innovations to government analysis and where you can get support - no matter which profession or department you work in!</p>
<p>Join this session with, Professor Sir Ian Diamond - Head of the Analysis Function and National Statistician - to hear about the innovations that have caught his eye, and what he thinks are the most interesting and important innovations coming down the road.</p>
</section>
<section id="dark-data---data-ethics-and-society-reading-group" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="dark-data---data-ethics-and-society-reading-group"><a href="https://www.tickettailor.com/events/dataethics/1193123/r/nhs" target="_blank">Dark Data - Data Ethics and Society Reading Group</a></h3>
<p><strong>Tuesday 4th June, 1-2pm, Online (Teams)</strong></p>
<p>Join the Public Sector Data Ethics &amp; Society Reading Group to discuss David Hand’s book ‘Dark Data’. <a href="https://www.tickettailor.com/events/dataethics/1193123/r/nhs" target="_blank">Sign up now to reserve your spot</a> (and receive details of the 40% discount off the paperback we’ve scooped😎).</p>
</section>
<section id="london-data-week-2024" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="london-data-week-2024"><a href="https://londondataweek.org/" target="_blank">London Data Week 2024</a></h3>
<p><strong>1st-7th July 2024, Online and in person</strong></p>
<p>London Data Week is a city-wide, distributed festival of events focusing on all things data. Data is a major part of our everyday lives, and shapes many of the decisions we make – as well as the decisions that are made about us – whether we know it or not. We believe that everyone should have a seat at the table when it comes to data, and that is the guiding principle behind our core values: to be collaborative, open and inclusive. So, we invite you to be part of the conversation by joining us and our event partners at a London Data Week event.</p>
<p>Find out more about London Data Week and what events are being held <a href="https://londondataweek.org/" target="_blank">here</a></p>
</section>
<section id="nhs-rpysoc-2024-conference-21st-nov-birmingham---registration-opened" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="nhs-rpysoc-2024-conference-21st-nov-birmingham---registration-opened"><a href="https://nhsrcommunity.com/events/nhs-r-nhs-pycom-open-source-conference-nhs-rpysoc-2024-2024-ticket-for-in-person-attendance-on-thursday-21-november-2024/" target="_blank">NHS RPySOC 2024 Conference (21st Nov, Birmingham) - registration opened</a></h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 21st-22nd November, 9am-5pm, in-person (Birmingham) / Online</strong></p>
<p>The <strong>NHS RPySOC 2024 conference</strong> is open for registration now! It will be on <strong>21st &amp; 22nd November in Birmingham</strong>. This is jointed hosted by the NHS R Community and NHS.pycom, and also promotes Open Source.</p>
<ul>
<li>Day 1 will be a mixture of presentations, workshops and lightening talks</li>
<li>Day 2 <strong>(in-person only)</strong> will be ‘Unconference’ with suggestions for topics being taken on day 1.</li>
</ul>
<p>It’s a great chance to show off our work, share our learning with a like minded community and learn a few things yourself, such as the state of the industry and how techniques are being applied elsewhere.</p>
<p>You can either attend:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://nhsrcommunity.com/events/nhs-r-nhs-pycom-open-source-conference-nhs-rpysoc-2024-2024-ticket-for-in-person-attendance-on-thursday-21-november-2024/">In-Person (The ICC, Hall 11, Birmingham B1 2EA</a></li>
<li><a href="https://nhsrcommunity.com/events/nhs-r-nhs-pycom-open-source-conference-2024-rpysoc-2024-ticket-for-virtual-attendance-on-thursday-21-november-2024/">Online</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Abstract submissions haven’t been opened yet.</strong></p>
<hr>
<p>Know of any events we should feature next month? Let us know by clicking the “Contribute” button, or <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="data-science-community" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Data Science Community</h1>
</section>
<section id="ai-quality-community-of-practice" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ai-quality-community-of-practice">AI Quality Community of Practice</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_05/AI_CoP.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>A group of data scientists engaging with the AIQCoP</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The AI Quality Community of Practice was launched on Thursday 16th May, a community primarily of testing and assurance professionals focused on the assurance of healthcare AI.</p>
<p>Data Science’s Will Poulett and Ben Wallace gave presentations on research they’d been doing in the AiQCoP, (formally INSTANT) including work on an academic paper which will be presented in IEEE in Athens at the end of the month.</p>
<p>AIQCOP will be closely collaborating with data science in the future, but the best way to get involved right now is to sign up to the <a href="https://engage.cloud.microsoft/main/groups/eyJfdHlwZSI6Ikdyb3VwIiwiaWQiOiIxODQ1ODE2MDMzMjgifQ/about" target="_blank">Viva Engage group</a> and send any papers or articles their way! You can also check out the <a href="https://nhs.sharepoint.com/sites/X26_AssuranceCOE/SitePages/AI-%26-Quality-Assurance.aspx?csf=1&amp;web=1&amp;e=HTahJY&amp;xsdata=MDV8MDJ8fGViMDUyZDJlMWEwYjQxMDUwOTVlMDhkYzUyZjEwOGJmfDM3YzM1NGIyODViMDQ3ZjViMjIyMDdiNDhkNzc0ZWUzfDB8MHw2Mzg0NzY0NDIzNjcxMDEyNzh8VW5rbm93bnxWR1ZoYlhOVFpXTjFjbWwwZVZObGNuWnBZMlY4ZXlKV0lqb2lNQzR3TGpBd01EQWlMQ0pRSWpvaVYybHVNeklpTENKQlRpSTZJazkwYUdWeUlpd2lWMVFpT2pFeGZRPT18MXxMMk5vWVhSekx6RTVPalU0WXpObFkyRXlMVFk1TXpVdE5ERTFZaTA1TkRrNExXWTVZVE0wTm1Sa01UYzJZMTlrTTJNeE9EUTJOeTFoWkRZeExUUTFaVEl0T1RZNU5TMDFZVFF6TkdRMFlURXlPVEZBZFc1eExtZGliQzV6Y0dGalpYTXZiV1Z6YzJGblpYTXZNVGN4TWpBME56UXpOVFkzT1E9PXwyMWY2ZDg2M2UzNzc0ZmNmMDk1ZTA4ZGM1MmYxMDhiZnxmZmE1YTczMTNjY2I0ZWE5OTEwZjZmMjFjMjE0NjE2Nw%3D%3D&amp;sdata=QWVoVk9uOFhHUVZwdCs2SEdsY3EzakxXdEVrTzJCcnB1UTlSeFI1QXpNdz0%3D&amp;ovuser=37c354b2-85b0-47f5-b222-07b48d774ee3%2Canusha.jose%40nhs.net&amp;OR=Teams-HL&amp;CT=1712133835361&amp;clickparams=eyJBcHBOYW1lIjoiVGVhbXMtRGVza3RvcCIsIkFwcFZlcnNpb24iOiI1MC8yNDAyMTUyODYxNiIsIkhhc0ZlZGVyYXRlZFVzZXIiOmZhbHNlfQ%3D%3D&amp;SafelinksUrl=https%3A%2F%2Fnhs.sharepoint.com%2Fsites%2FX26_AssuranceCOE%2FSitePages%2FAI-&amp;-Quality-Assurance.aspx=" target="_blank">sharepoint website</a> or email them at <a href="mailto:nhsdigital.instant@nhs.net">nhsdigital.instant@nhs.net</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="rap-community-of-practice" class="level1">
<h1>RAP Community of Practice</h1>
<p>The <a href="https://nhsdigital.github.io/rap-community-of-practice/?utm_source=p_d_newsletter&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=PR_requests" target="_blank">RAP Community of Practice</a> promotes good coding practice and aims to support analytical teams by developing learning materials, however it’s not a solo effort! Many RAP Champions have worked with the team in recent years and the current RAP Squad wants to encourage everyone to contribute to the Community, whether it be by sending a <a href="https://github.com/NHSDigital/rap-community-of-practice/pulls" target="_blank">Pull Request</a>, raising an <a href="https://github.com/NHSDigital/rap-community-of-practice/issues/new" target="_blank">Issue</a>, or even <a href="mailto:england.rapchampions@nhs.net" target="_blank">emailing them!</a></p>
<p>Help make the RAP <em>Community</em> of Practice a <em>community</em> endeavour!</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="training-opportunities" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Training Opportunities</h1>
</section>
<section id="the-turing-online-learning-platform" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-turing-online-learning-platform"><a href="https://www.turing.ac.uk/courses" target="_blank">The Turing Online Learning Platform</a></h2>
<p>The Turing Online Learning Platform offers a range of <strong>free</strong> online course from AI fairness on social media to an introduction to transparent machine learning. <a href="https://www.turing.ac.uk/courses" target="_blank">Check them all out here</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="microsoft-enterprise-skills-initiative" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="microsoft-enterprise-skills-initiative"><a href="https://esi.microsoft.com/landing" target="_blank">Microsoft Enterprise Skills Initiative</a></h2>
<p>Using your nhs.net email account, you have access to a variety of Microsoft courses for free, as well as <a href="https://esi.microsoft.com/getcertification" target="_blank">certifications</a>. These range from a beginner friendly course titled <em>Deploy and consume models with Azure Machine Learning</em> to an advanced course titled <em>Write advanced Transact-SQL queries</em>.</p>
<hr>
<p>We are currently updating our resource list and reviewing the content: please let us know of any resources you think would be useful! Check out all the resources in the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Training+Brochure" target="_blank">Training Brochure</a>! Can you spot something missing? <a href="mailto:datascience@nhs.net">Contact us</a>!</p>
</section>
<section id="need-a-quick-break" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Need a Quick Break?</h1>
</section>
<p><a href="https://mywordle.strivemath.com/?word=cfrss" target="_blank">How many tries will it take you?</a></p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<p><a href="https://forms.office.com/pages/responsepage.aspx?id=slTDN7CF9UeyIge0jXdO48pr_29hyJFKpCZ7SYYvjeFUNUVPMUk0STlDRlJMNklIWEI3V0NZVTZXVS4u&amp;route=shorturl" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-success btn-lg">Subscribe to the community</a><a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">Contribute</a><a href="./newsletter.pdf" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">PDF Version</a></p>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>newsletter</category>
  <guid>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_05/newsletter.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 20 May 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Professional Development Newsletter April 2024</title>
  <dc:creator>Jennifer Struthers</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Giulia Mantovani</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Harriet Sands</dc:creator>
  <link>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_04/newsletter.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/images/banner_april.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Welcome to the latest Professional Development newsletter, brought to you by the Data Science Professional Development Functional Team.</p>
<p>The newsletter team are always happy to receive constructive feedback, and we invite you to send us any contributions you may have.</p>
<p>There are some legacy NHS Digital items which we have identified with❗</p>
<p>If you cannot access something of interest to you, please <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new" target="_blank">reach out</a>.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading! – PD newsletter team</p>
<section id="highlights" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Highlights</h1>
</section>
<section id="now-accessible-to-all" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="now-accessible-to-all">Now Accessible to All!</h3>
<p>After trialing the use of the <a href="https://github.com/NHSDigital" target="_blank">NHS Digital GitHub</a> to aid in the creation of the newsletter, it has now been officially moved to the publically accessible <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland" target="_blank">NHS England GitHub</a>.</p>
<p>We strongly encourage contributions to the newsletter from all our colleagues, which can be submitted through <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" target="_blank">clicking here</a> or any of the “Contribute” buttons around the site.</p>
</section>
<section id="mentoring-scheme-expression-of-interest" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="mentoring-scheme-expression-of-interest">Mentoring Scheme Expression of Interest</h3>
<p>The Professional Development Function Team are investigating the interest in starting up a Mentorship Scheme between senior and junior NHS Data Science colleagues.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.southampton.ac.uk/professional-development/mentoring/benefits-of-a-mentoring-relationship.page" target="_blank">Mentorship benefits both parties</a>: mentees are provided with guidance from someone who has once been in their shoes and mentors gain insights from a new perspective, and gain experience in staff management and development. If you are interested in becoming a mentor <strong>and/or</strong> mentee, please fill out the <a href="https://forms.office.com/pages/responsepage.aspx?id=slTDN7CF9UeyIge0jXdO45Vp0C6IOYJOjBrGZlr3xANUMkRSNTg1UElOVUJXRzJaS1VGQklPMUY1Ti4u" target="_blank">expression of interest form</a>.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="events" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Events</h1>
</section>
<p>Lots of exciting things coming up! See the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/calendars" target="_blank">full calendar here</a>❗, and a small selection below.</p>
<section id="hdr-uk-advanced-computer-science-summit-ai-and-healthcare" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="hdr-uk-advanced-computer-science-summit-ai-and-healthcare"><a href="https://www.hdruk.ac.uk/events/hdr-uk-advanced-computer-science-summit-ai-and-healthcare/" target="_blank">HDR UK Advanced Computer Science Summit: AI and Healthcare</a></h3>
<p><strong>24 April 2024, 10:00AM - 3:30PM, Online</strong></p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.hdruk.ac.uk/events/hdr-uk-advanced-computer-science-summit-ai-and-healthcare/" target="_blank">HDR UK Advanced Computer Science Summit: AI and Healthcare</a> aims to anticipate advances in technologies that are on the horizon and discuss the impact these may have on health data research.</p>
<p>Cool speakers include but are not limited to:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/elham-kashefi-76b9286/">Elham Kashefi</a> (Chief Scientist for the <a href="https://www.nqcc.ac.uk/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Press-release-Announcement-of-the-appointment-of-the-Chief-Scientist-for-the-NQCC.pdf">UK’s National Quantum Computing Centre</a> will discuss quantum computation)</li>
<li><a href="https://profiles.ucl.ac.uk/78197-honghan-wu">Honghan Wu</a> (Associate Professor at the Institute of Health Informatics at UCL will lead on NLP and using text technologies and Knowledge Graph techniques to analyze health data)</li>
<li><a href="https://www.ed.ac.uk/profile/dr-william-whiteley">William Whiteley</a> (Professor of Neurology and Epidemiology at the University of Edinburgh will discuss replicating RCTs by use of data at large scale)</li>
<li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/mobuolafoluwa-onayade/">Mobuolafoluwa Onayade</a> (Health Data Scientist and Analyst at Swansea University will be presenting on The use of Causal Machine Learning (CausalML) as an upgrade to Traditional Machine Learning)</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="the-turing-roche-knowledge-share-series-fairness-in-ai-for-health" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-turing-roche-knowledge-share-series-fairness-in-ai-for-health"><a href="https://www.turing.ac.uk/events/turing-roche-knowledge-share-series-fairness-ai-health">The Turing-Roche Knowledge Share Series: Fairness in AI for Health</a></h3>
<p><strong>Tuesday 30th April, 3-4pm, Online</strong></p>
<p>Join the Turing-Roche Partnership’s virtual event series for partnership updates, knowledge sharing and new perspectives. This event will explore the theme of fairness in AI, with relation to health, and hear from Leandra Bräuninger, a PhD student at University College London and Adarsh Srivastava, Head of Data and Analytics Quality Assurance at Roche.</p>
</section>
<section id="digital-footprints-2024" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="digital-footprints-2024"><a href="https://digifootprints.co.uk/digital-footprints-2024/" target="_blank">Digital Footprints 2024</a></h3>
<p><strong>Wednesday 8th May 1pm – Thursday 9th May 4pm, University of Bristol</strong></p>
<p>Focusing on digital footprints data for social impact, inviting innovative research that harnesses the potential of these novel datasets to address pressing societal challenges and drive positive change. The conference is organised by Turing Novel Data Linkage for Health and Wellbeing Interest Group.</p>
<p><em>Please note attendance of the conference is subject to a £50 fee.</em></p>
</section>
<section id="data-science-festival-mayday-2024" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-science-festival-mayday-2024"><a href="https://datasciencefestival.com/event/mayday-2024/" target="_blank">Data Science Festival MayDay 2024</a></h3>
<p><strong>Saturday 18th May, 9-6pm, CodeNode, London</strong></p>
<p>Enter the ballot for a chance to grab a <em>free</em> ticket to this years’ Data Science Festival, hosted in London. Many speakers and sessions to be announced, but already lined up are talks on Gender Bias in Machine Learning and Leveraging GANs for Building Synthetic Data.</p>
</section>
<section id="dark-data---data-ethics-and-society-reading-group" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="dark-data---data-ethics-and-society-reading-group"><a href="https://www.tickettailor.com/events/dataethics/1193123/r/nhs" target="_blank">Dark Data - Data Ethics and Society Reading Group</a></h3>
<p><strong>Tuesday 4th June, 1-2pm, Online (Teams)</strong></p>
<p>Join the Public Sector Data Ethics &amp; Society Reading Group to discuss David Hand’s book ‘Dark Data’. <a href="https://www.tickettailor.com/events/dataethics/1193123/r/nhs" target="_blank">Sign up now to reserve your spot</a> (and receive details of the 40% discount off the paperback we’ve scooped😎).</p>
<hr>
<p>See more future events on our <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Data+Science+Events" target="_blank">confluence calendar</a>❗</p>
<p>Know of any events we should feature next month? Let us know by clicking the “Contribute” button, or <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="knowledge-sharing" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Knowledge Sharing</h1>
</section>
<section id="data-science-discussions" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-science-discussions">Data Science Discussions</h3>
<center>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_04/DS_Discussion.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Data Scientists discussing a fun topic over coffee, building relationships and expanding their knowledge base</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</center>
<p>On Thursday 11th April we had our first Data Science discussion, hosted by Will Poulett. Data Science Discussions are a new event, focussed on peer to peer discussions on a broad range of Data Science topics. For this discussion Will asked everyone attending to research a future application of AI that interested them, and also consider how it could be later applied to healthcare. The discussion began with Will presenting his case: <a href="https://www.projectceti.org/" target="_blank">Project CETI</a>, who are applying advanced machine learning and state-of-the-art robotics to listen to and translate the communication of sperm whales. Check out his slide deck <a href="https://nhs.sharepoint.com/:f:/r/sites/msteams_2768a1/Shared%20Documents/FT%20-%20Professional%20Development/PD%20Events/Data%20Science%20Discussions?csf=1&amp;web=1&amp;e=Tbm3Gq" target="_blank">here</a>. We then broke up into smaller groups to further discuss his case and our own.</p>
<p>The Professional Development Functional Team hope to hold Data Science Discussions monthly. If you have an area of Data Science you’re interested in sharing, and encouraging others to look into too, please <a href="mailto:datascience@nhs.net">contact us</a> to host a session! Most of the session is held in break out rooms, and so all you need to do is spark discussion.</p>
</section>
<section id="rap-drop-in-sessions-now-on-tuesdays" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="rap-drop-in-sessions-now-on-tuesdays">RAP Drop In Sessions (Now on Tuesdays)</h3>
<p>The RAP Squad hold a <a href="https://teams.microsoft.com/l/meetup-join/19:meeting_NGE5Mjc5ZGQtYjJkZi00OGQ4LWJmYmMtOGIxYzI3NWQ3NWZi@thread.v2/0?context=%7B%22Tid%22:%2237c354b2-85b0-47f5-b222-07b48d774ee3%22,%22Oid%22:%226a6e419b-5da0-48cb-854e-e7cca39c57e2%22%7D" target="_blank">weekly drop in session on Teams</a>,<strong>Tuesdays 10-11am</strong>, for anything and all things RAP (Reproducibile Analytical Pipelines). Come along to ask questions, get tips, or share instances of best practice in your team!</p>
<p>Check out the <a href="https://nhsdigital.github.io/rap-community-of-practice/?utm_source=p_d_newsletter&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=homepage">RAP Community of Practice website</a> to learn more, including <a href="https://nhsdigital.github.io/rap-community-of-practice/introduction_to_RAP/gov-policy-on-rap/?utm_source=p_d_newsletter&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=gov_policy">information on what the government has been saying about RAP</a> (spoiler: it’s fast becoming the required way of working with data).</p>
<hr>
<p>Stay tuned for an update on what seminars &amp; show and tells will look like in the new team. Please bear with us as it is likely to be a learning process! Contact <a href="mailto:amelia.noonan1@nhs.net">Mia Noonan</a> for more information.</p>
</section>
<section id="training-opportunities" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Training Opportunities</h1>
</section>
<section id="the-turing-way-book-dash" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-turing-way-book-dash">The Turing Way Book Dash</h3>
<p><a href="https://the-turing-way.netlify.app/community-handbook/bookdash/bookdash-events.html"><strong>The Turing Way Book Dash</strong></a> is a collaborative event where you’ll work with others to add to and improve <strong>The Turing Way book</strong> and become a part of its community.</p>
<p>The online contribution sessions (collaborative co-working format) and the social networking session will take place from <strong>3 to 6 June 2024</strong>, and two community share-out events on <strong>7 June 2024</strong>. <a href="https://the-turing-way.netlify.app/community-handbook/bookdash/bookdash-events">See details</a>. There may also be an opportunity to join an in-person hub in your area - please indicate your interest in the application.</p>
<p><strong>Application</strong> <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1FdrlFh_4yw7XsqoG-yQt8zbEH9J8wHVhKl3ZfNz_NBk/edit">Please see the application form here</a>. Submission deadline is <strong>Friday 26th April 2024</strong> and the application form may take around 30 minutes to complete.</p>
<p><strong>Who should apply?</strong> Everyone that has expertise that The Turing Way project can benefit from. The skills and contributions that they’re looking for include, but are not limited to:</p>
<ul>
<li>Tools, methods, and case studies from reproducibility in Data Science 🛠️</li>
<li>Science communication skills: skills in writing, editing, and/or exciting interactive communications 📝</li>
<li>Project design and management skills 📊</li>
<li>Approaches and principles for collaboration in data science 🤝</li>
<li>Collaboratively writing new chapters 📝</li>
<li>Reviewing others’ contributions or editing the current chapters 📋</li>
<li>Updating how the book looks online (e.g., website design, CSS, logos, layout) 🖥️</li>
<li>Documenting other contributions as illustrations or stories 📸</li>
</ul>
<p>Participants will be expected to attend at least one co-working session (2.5 hours each) per day virtually.</p>
<hr>
<p>Check out all the resources in the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Training+Brochure" target="_blank">Training Brochure</a> ❗ Can you spot something missing? <a href="mailto:datascience@nhs.net">Contact us</a>!</p>
</section>
<section id="need-a-quick-break" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Need a Quick Break?</h1>
</section>
<p><a href="https://mywordle.strivemath.com/?word=mivuj">How many tries will it take you?</a></p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<p><a href="https://forms.office.com/pages/responsepage.aspx?id=slTDN7CF9UeyIge0jXdO48pr_29hyJFKpCZ7SYYvjeFUNUVPMUk0STlDRlJMNklIWEI3V0NZVTZXVS4u&amp;route=shorturl" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-success btn-lg">Subscribe to the community</a><a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">Contribute</a><a href="./newsletter.pdf" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">PDF Version</a></p>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>newsletter</category>
  <guid>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_04/newsletter.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Professional Development Newsletter March 2024</title>
  <dc:creator>Jennifer Struthers, Giulia Mantovani</dc:creator>
  <link>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_03/newsletter.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/images/banner_march.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Welcome to the latest Professional Development newsletter, brought to you by the Data Science skilled team Professional Development Functional Group.</p>
<p>The newsletter team are always happy to receive constructive feedback, and we invite you to send us any contributions you may have.</p>
<p>There are some legacy NHS Digital items which we have identified with❗</p>
<p>If you cannot access something of interest to you, please <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new" target="_blank">reach out</a>.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading! – PD newsletter team</p>
<section id="highlights" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Highlights</h1>
</section>
<section id="leadership-competency-framework" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="leadership-competency-framework">Leadership Competency Framework</h3>
<p>NHS England has <a href="https://www.england.nhs.uk/leaders/" target="_blank">published the leadership competency framework</a> which comprises a set of leadership competencies incorporating the skills, values and behaviours required in NHS board roles and establishes what good looks like in leadership terms, providing a new and consistent national standard of leadership. Many of us are very far from those positions, but it does not hurt to aim high. But also, it is good to know what is expected of our leaders. These are the six leadership competency domains that you can learn about reading the framework:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Driving high-quality and sustainable outcomes</li>
<li>Setting strategy and delivering long-term transformation</li>
<li>Promoting equality and inclusion, and reducing health and workforce inequalities</li>
<li>Providing robust governance and assurance</li>
<li>Creating a compassionate, just and positive culture</li>
<li>Building a trusted relationship with partners and communities</li>
</ol>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="events" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Events</h1>
</section>
<p>Lots of exciting things coming up! See the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/calendars" target="_blank">full calendar here</a>❗, and a small selection below.</p>
<section id="ai-uk-fringe-events" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ai-uk-fringe-events"><a href="https://ai-uk.turing.ac.uk/fringe-events/" target="_blank">AI UK Fringe Events</a></h3>
<p><strong>4th-29th March, various times, In person across the UK and online</strong></p>
<p>At a series of events AI UK Fringe brings together leaders in academia from across the UK’s AI ecosystem to demonstrate, exhibit and update on their ground-breaking work. Attendees at our AI UK Fringe events will be able to network with local colleagues and peers and take part in specialist debates and roundtables relevant to their regions. Browse this year’s events below and make sure to register your place.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-person-centred-healthcare-record---pipe-dream-or-inevitability" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-person-centred-healthcare-record---pipe-dream-or-inevitability"><a href="https://www.tickettailor.com/events/publicdigital/1167958?mc_cid=c757cfd211&amp;mc_eid=f15dd17114" target="_blank">The person-centred healthcare record - pipe dream or inevitability?</a></h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 18th April, 6-7:30pm, in person in London or on Zoom</strong></p>
<p>Successive administrations have tried and failed to implement a person-centred healthcare record, but can it be done? Join us to hear four digital healthcare experts debate the question of how interoperable access to patient data could or should be delivered, looking at political, commercial, and technical considerations.</p>
</section>
<section id="lunch-and-learn" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="lunch-and-learn">Lunch and Learn</h3>
<p><strong>Monday 22nd April, 12-1pm, Wellington Place: Town Hall Collaboration Space</strong></p>
<p>Andy Jackson has recently released news of new lunch and learn seminars held in person in Leeds. The next one will feature a guest speaker from ONS - Population Demographics. Watch your email for more information.</p>
</section>
<section id="digital-footprints-2024" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="digital-footprints-2024"><a href="https://digifootprints.co.uk/digital-footprints-2024/" target="_blank">Digital Footprints 2024</a></h3>
<p><strong>Wednesday 8th May 1pm – Thursday 9th May 4pm, University of Bristol</strong></p>
<p>Focusing on digital footprints data for social impact, inviting innovative research that harnesses the potential of these novel datasets to address pressing societal challenges and drive positive change. The conference is organised by Turing Novel Data Linkage for Health and Wellbeing Interest Group.</p>
<p><em>Please note attendance of the conference is subject to a £50 fee.</em></p>
</section>
<section id="data-science-festival-mayday-2024" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-science-festival-mayday-2024"><a href="https://datasciencefestival.com/event/mayday-2024/" target="_blank">Data Science Festival MayDay 2024</a></h3>
<p><strong>Saturday 18th May, 9-6pm, CodeNode, London</strong></p>
<p>Enter the ballot for achance to grab a <em>free</em> ticket to this years’ Data Science Festival, hosted in London. Many speakers and sessions to be announced, but already lined up are talks on Gender Bias in Machine Learning and Leveraging GANs for Building Synthetic Data.</p>
</section>
<section id="dark-data---data-ethics-and-society-reading-group" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="dark-data---data-ethics-and-society-reading-group"><a href="https://www.tickettailor.com/events/dataethics/1193123/r/nhs" target="_blank">Dark Data - Data Ethics and Society Reading Group</a></h3>
<p><strong>Tuesday 4th June, 1-2pm, Online (Teams)</strong></p>
<p>Join the Public Sector Data Ethics &amp; Society Reading Group to discuss David Hand’s book ‘Dark Data’. <a href="https://www.tickettailor.com/events/dataethics/1193123/r/nhs" target="_blank">Sign up now to reserve your spot</a> (and receive details of the 40% discount off the paperback we’ve scooped😎).</p>
<hr>
<p>See more future events on our <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Data+Science+Events" target="_blank">confluence calendar</a>❗</p>
<p>Know of any events we should feature next month? Let us know by clicking the “Contribute” button, or <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="knowledge-sharing" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Knowledge Sharing</h1>
</section>
<section id="generative-ai-in-a-research-context" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="generative-ai-in-a-research-context">Generative AI in a research context</h3>
<p>Generative AI is increasingly used to draft, edit, annotate and debug code. It’s not just industry software developers who are taking advantage of the tools it has to offer. Those who develop and use software for academic research are benefitting from them too. So how do you make the best use of generative AI for coding in a research context? As software engineers with The Alan Turing Institute’s <a href="https://www.turing.ac.uk/work-turing/research/research-engineering-group" target="_blank">Research Engineering Group</a> (REG) and <a href="https://www.turing.ac.uk/work-turing/studentships/enrichment" target="_blank">PhD Enrichment scheme</a>, we’ve been asking ourselves just this question. <a href="https://www.turing.ac.uk/blog/using-generative-ai-write-code-guide-researchers" target="_blank">Here</a>, we share our thoughts, along with some tips for researchers.</p>
</section>
<section id="github-vs-gitlab-terminology-differences" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="github-vs-gitlab-terminology-differences"><a href="https://nhsdigital.github.io/rap-community-of-practice/training_resources/git/github_gitlab_terminology/?utm_source=p_d_newsletter&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=github_gitlab" target="_blank">GitHub vs Gitlab Terminology Differences</a></h3>
<p>GitHub and GitLab are two very similar yet different platforms and that can lead to some confusion between teams who are familiar with one but not the other when some key pieces of terminology have been changed slightly between them. The RAP Community of Pracice have recently released a quick summary of some of these terminology differences. Read over this and you’ll never get your MRs and PRs mixed up again!</p>
<hr>
<p>Stay tuned for an update on what seminars &amp; show and tells will look like in the new team. Please bear with us as it is likely to be a learning process! Contact <a href="mailto:amelia.noonan1@nhs.net">Mia Noonan</a> for more information..</p>
</section>
<section id="training-opportunities" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Training Opportunities</h1>
</section>
<section id="pluralsight-access" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pluralsight-access"><a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Pluralsight+Access" target="_blank">Pluralsight Access</a></h3>
<p>After the reinstation of the Pluralsight license, a confluence page on how to access it (whether or not you had access before) has been set up. Check it out to gain access to all of the Pluralsight training resources again.</p>
<hr>
<p>Check out all the resources in the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Training+Brochure" target="_blank">Training Brochure</a>! Can you spot something missing? <a href="mailto:datascience@nhs.net">Contact us</a>!</p>
</section>
<section id="need-a-quick-break" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Need a Quick Break?</h1>
</section>
<p><a href="https://mywordle.strivemath.com/?word=icuhw" target="_blank">How many tries will it take you?</a></p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<p><a href="https://forms.office.com/pages/responsepage.aspx?id=slTDN7CF9UeyIge0jXdO48pr_29hyJFKpCZ7SYYvjeFUNUVPMUk0STlDRlJMNklIWEI3V0NZVTZXVS4u&amp;route=shorturl" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-success btn-lg">Subscribe to the community</a><a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">Contribute</a><a href="./newsletter.pdf" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">PDF Version</a></p>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>newsletter</category>
  <category>leadership</category>
  <guid>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_03/newsletter.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Professional Development Newsletter February 2024</title>
  <dc:creator>Harriet Sands and Jennifer Struthers</dc:creator>
  <link>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_02/newsletter.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/images/banner_feb.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Welcome to the latest Professional Development newsletter, brought to you by the Data Science skilled team Professional Development Capability team <strong>- now in a new format!</strong></p>
<p>The newsletter team are always happy to receive constructive feedback, and we invite you to send us any contributions you may have.</p>
<p>There are some legacy NHS Digital items which we have identified with❗</p>
<p>If you cannot access something of interest to you, please <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new" target="_blank">reach out</a>.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading! – PD newsletter team</p>
<section id="highlights" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Highlights</h1>
</section>
<section id="your-professional-development---job-descriptions" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="your-professional-development---job-descriptions"><u><strong>Your Professional Development</strong> - Job Descriptions </u></h4>
<p>When preparing for future career opportunities here at NHSE, it’s a good idea to understand the job descriptions for each role you hope to apply for.</p>
<p>Take a look at the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Data+Science+Job+Descriptions" target="_blank">current data science job descriptions saved on Confluence</a> which detail the requirements and expectations for the various roles we may look to recruit for in the team. These will be used for recruitment in the immediate future.</p>
<p>Familiarising yourself with these specifications can help you shape your professional development plans and tailor the training opportunities you seek out.</p>
<p>Please note that in the longer term these job descriptions may change to be aligned to the <a href="https://future.nhs.uk/DataAnalytics/view?objectID=31311216">National Competency Framework</a> and this will be communicated to the team.</p>
</section>
<section id="health-and-care-analytics-conference-2024---call-for-abstracts" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="health-and-care-analytics-conference-2024---call-for-abstracts"><u><strong>Health and Care Analytics Conference 2024</strong> - Call for Abstracts</u></h4>
<p>Have some interesting work to share? The <a href="https://haca-conference.nhs.uk/" target="_blank">HACA Conference 2024</a> is officially accepting applications to present (in the form of a talk or poster) at the 2024 conference, hosted 23rd-24th July at Telford International Centre. The deadline to submit is <strong>Thursday February 29th 2024</strong>. Check out the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/HACA+2024" target="_blank">HACA 2024 Confluence page</a>❗ to see the steps and track submissions.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="events" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Events</h1>
</section>
<p>Lots of exciting things coming up! See the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/calendars" target="_blank">full calendar here</a>❗</p>
<section id="severe-mental-illness-physical-disease" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="severe-mental-illness-physical-disease"><a href="https://www.hdruk.ac.uk/events/severe-mental-illness-and-physical-disease/" target="_blank">Severe Mental Illness &amp; Physical Disease</a></h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 29th February 10:00 - 13:00, Online</strong></p>
<p>Hosted by researchers at the Usher Institute, The University of Edinburgh, with contributions from DataMind, the Health Data Research Hub for Mental Health we will hear from researchers working on projects relating to severe mental illness and receipt of cardiovascular care as well as people with lived experience, clinicians and public health and government representatives.</p>
</section>
<section id="making-a-difference-using-data-to-improve-care" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="making-a-difference-using-data-to-improve-care"><a href="event link" target="_blank">Making a difference: Using Data to Improve Care</a></h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 29th February 2024 13:00 - 16:00, Online</strong></p>
<p>Join us for the HDR UK Midlands &amp; Health Innovation East Midlands Insight Sharing Webinar. Highlights include: Dementia and the correlation with cardiovascular diseases, Leveraging administrative healthcare data to enhance drug approval in rare disease, EU data infrastructure for Rare Disease.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-career-live" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-career-live"><a href="https://nhsengland.sharepoint.com/sites/thehub/SitePages/Help-us-inspire-students-to-join-the-NHS.aspx" target="_blank">What Career? Live</a></h3>
<p><strong>Friday 1st and Saturday 2nd March, NEC Birmingham</strong></p>
<p>NHS Health Careers is looking for people to help inspire students to join the NHS by attending this national careers event. If you’re interested, <a href="mailto:laura.monks2@nhs.net">email Laura Monks</a> by <strong>Monday 26th February</strong> .</p>
</section>
<section id="policy-making-for-the-age-of-ai" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="policy-making-for-the-age-of-ai"><a href="https://thestrandgroup.kcl.ac.uk/event/policy-making-for-the-age-of-ai/" target="_blank">Policy Making for the Age of AI</a></h3>
<p><strong>Wednesday 6th March, 18:30, King’s College London</strong></p>
<p>The sixty-eigth Strand Group will take place at 18.30 on Wednesday 6th March 2024 when Sarah Munby, Permanent Secretary of the Department for Science, Innovation and Technology, will give her second lecture as Visiting Professor on ‘Policy Making in the Age of AI.’</p>
</section>
<section id="the-politics-and-philosophy-of-ai" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-politics-and-philosophy-of-ai"><a href="https://www.lse.ac.uk/Events/2024/03/202403191830/ai" target="_blank">The politics and philosophy of AI</a></h3>
<p><strong>Tuesday 19th March 2024 18:30 to 20:00, London School of Economics &amp; Online</strong></p>
<p>As artificial intelligence (AI) moves beyond the realm of science fiction, it is already having a profound impact on our economies, societies and politics. To make sense of the transformative power and disruptive potential of AI, we are joined by thinkers at the cutting edge of the technological frontier for an in-depth discussion of its multifaceted impact. Speakers include the ‘godfather of AI’, Geoffrey Hinton; Kate Vredenburgh, Assistant Professor in the Department of Philosophy, Logic and Scientific Method at LSE and Robin Archer, the Director of the postgraduate programme in political sociology and the Director of the Ralph Miliband Programme at LSE.</p>
</section>
<section id="digital-footprints-2024" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="digital-footprints-2024"><a href="https://digifootprints.co.uk/digital-footprints-2024/" target="_blank">Digital Footprints 2024</a></h3>
<p><strong>Wednesday 8th May 1pm – Thursday 9th May 4pm, University of Bristol</strong></p>
<p>Focusing on digital footprints data for social impact, inviting innovative research that harnesses the potential of these novel datasets to address pressing societal challenges and drive positive change. The conference is organised by Turing Novel Data Linkage for Health and Wellbeing Interest Group.</p>
<p><em>Please note attendance of the conference is subject to a £50 fee.</em></p>
<hr>
<p>See more future events on our <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Events+calendar" target="_blank">confluence calendar</a>❗</p>
<p>Know of any events we should feature next month? Let us know by clicking the “Contribute” button, or <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="knowledge-sharing" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Knowledge Sharing</h1>
</section>
<section id="refactoring-golden-rules" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="refactoring-golden-rules"><a href="https://nhsdigital.github.io/rap-community-of-practice/training_resources/refactoring-guide/?utm_source=p_d_newsletter&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=refactoring_guide" target="_blank">Refactoring Golden Rules</a></h3>
<p>Are you wondering how you can make your code faster, easier to read, and easier to reuse? Getting your code to work is just the first step! After that, you should refactor your code to make it higher quality - more efficient, more robust, more maintainable. But how do you do that? Well, you can start by reading the <a href="https://nhsdigital.github.io/rap-community-of-practice/training_resources/refactoring-guide/?utm_source=p_d_newsletter&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=refactoring_guide">refactoring golden rules</a> on the RAP Community of Practice website!</p>
<hr>
<p>Stay tuned for an update on what seminars &amp; show and tells will look like in the new team. Please bear with us as it is likely to be a learning process! Contact <a href="mailto:amelia.noonan1@nhs.net">Mia Noonan</a> for more information..</p>
</section>
<section id="training-opportunities" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Training Opportunities</h1>
</section>
<section id="applications-for-the-nihr-health-service-modelling-associates-now-open" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="applications-for-the-nihr-health-service-modelling-associates-now-open"><a href="https://sites.google.com/nihr.ac.uk/hsma" target="_blank">Applications for the NIHR Health Service Modelling Associates now open</a></h3>
<p>This free, 15-month course teaches people how to use Operational Research and Data Science techniques to improve services and aid decision making.</p>
<p>The free course requires a time commitment of one day a week for the full programme. All code in the course is in Python, though some other open-source software will be used too - but no prior experience with Python (or any programming experience at all!) is required.</p>
<p>See the <a href="https://sites.google.com/nihr.ac.uk/hsma/apply-to-become-a-hsma?authuser=0" target="_blank">FAQs</a> and direct any further questions to <a href="mailto:penchord@exeter.ac.uk">penchord@exeter.ac.uk</a> and <a href="mailto:s.j.rosser@exeter.ac.uk">s.j.rosser@exeter.ac.uk</a>.</p>
<p>Applications for the course close on the <strong>4th of March 2024</strong>, with the course beginning <strong>Monday 15th April 2024</strong>.</p>
</section>
<section id="become-a-stem-ambassador" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="become-a-stem-ambassador"><a href="https://www.stem.org.uk/stem-ambassadors/become-a-stem-ambassador" target="_blank">Become a STEM ambassador</a></h3>
<p>STEM Ambassadors help young people to understand the real world applications of their learning. Attend an <a href="https://www.eventbrite.com/e/volunteer-information-session-becoming-a-stem-ambassador-tickets-771603405557?aff=odcleoeventsincollection&amp;keep_tld=1" target="_blank">information session</a> on Thursday 22nd February to learn more.</p>
</section>
<section id="stakeholder-mapping-resources" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="stakeholder-mapping-resources"><a href="https://analysisfunction.civilservice.gov.uk/policy-store/stakeholder-mapping/" target="_blank">Stakeholder Mapping Resources</a></h3>
<p>This guidance includes a helpful template and further resources to help you map stakeholders for user engagement.</p>
</section>
<section id="pluralsight" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pluralsight"><a href="https://www.pluralsight.com/" target="_blank">Pluralsight</a></h3>
<p>Tim Roebuck <a href="https://web.yammer.com/main/org/hscic.gov.uk/threads/eyJfdHlwZSI6IlRocmVhZCIsImlkIjoiMjY2Njk0NDQ1MDQ0NTMxMiJ9?trk_copy_link=V2" target="_blank">announced</a> that following delays to resolve contractual issues for a new contract, access has been restored for existing Pluralsight users, and you should been able to continue any previous training.</p>
</section>
<section id="improve-your-markdown-by-contributing-to-the-data-science-website" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="improve-your-markdown-by-contributing-to-the-data-science-website"><a href="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience/" target="_blank">Improve your Markdown by contributing to the Data Science website!</a></h3>
<p>Ever wanted to try your hand at learning Markdown but never really found a reason? Check out this <a href="https://www.markdowntutorial.com/" target="_blank">Markdown tutorial</a> and then try your hand at it by helping improve the newly launched <a href="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience/" target="_blank">Data Science website</a>.</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_02/amaia_website_newsletter.png" alt="A photoshopped image of Amaia onto a WW2 propaganda poster, saying 'We Need You'" width="350"></td>
<td>We launched the prototype <a href="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience/" target="_blank">Data Science website</a> - but we need your help. <br>We need your contributions (see how to do this <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience/blob/main/CONTRIBUTE.md" target="_blank">here</a>), in particular:<br><br>- Send us a summary of your project (see <a href="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience/our_work/ds218_rap_community_of_practice/" target="_blank">this example</a>)<br>- Follow <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience/blob/main/docs/our_work/template-project.md" target="_blank">this template</a>.<br>- Contribute an article to the blog.<br>- Volunteer to pick up an <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience/issues" target="_blank">issue</a> on GitHub.<br>- Give us feedback about the <a href="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience/" target="_blank">website</a>.<br><br>With the conference season approaching, something up on the web can be useful to point people towards!<br></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Check out all the resources in the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Training+Brochure" target="_blank">Training Brochure</a>! Can you spot something missing? <a href="mailto:datascience@nhs.net">Contact us</a>!</p>
</section>
<section id="need-a-quick-break" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Need a Quick Break?</h1>
</section>
<p><a href="https://mywordle.strivemath.com/?word=zokddgesefp" target="_blank">How many tries will it take you?</a></p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<p><a href="https://forms.office.com/pages/responsepage.aspx?id=slTDN7CF9UeyIge0jXdO48pr_29hyJFKpCZ7SYYvjeFUNUVPMUk0STlDRlJMNklIWEI3V0NZVTZXVS4u&amp;route=shorturl" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-success btn-lg">Subscribe to the community</a><a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">Contribute</a><a href="./newsletter.pdf" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">PDF Version</a></p>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>newsletter</category>
  <category>analytics</category>
  <guid>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_02/newsletter.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Professional Development Newsletter January 2024</title>
  <dc:creator>Harriet Sands and Harry Kelleher</dc:creator>
  <link>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_01/newsletter.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/images/banner_jan.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Welcome to the latest Professional Development newsletter, brought to you by the Data Science skilled team Professional Development Capability team.</p>
<p>The newsletter team are always happy to receive constructive feedback, and we invite you to send us any contributions you may have.</p>
<p>There are some items that are available via legacy systems available to former NHS Digital colleagues. We have marked these with❗</p>
<p>If you cannot access something of interest to you, please <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new" target="_blank">reach out</a>.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading! – PD newsletter team</p>
<section id="highlights" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Highlights</h1>
</section>
<section id="competency-framework-zooming-intodelivery" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="competency-framework-zooming-intodelivery"><u><strong>Competency Framework</strong> – zooming into…Delivery</u></h4>
<p>As we adjust to delivering in the new team structure; using potentially unfamiliar tools like Confluence, JIRA and DevOps, getting to grips with new projects and new stakeholders, it’s the perfect time to refresh our understanding of what makes good delivery.</p>
<p>Delivery is the translation of the insights we produce into actionable outcomes. Keeping a delivery-focussed mindset is key to achieve value for money and improve lives for service users. Without it, we cannot fulfil our mission to drive the digital transformation of the NHS!</p>
<p>Delivery comes in different shapes and sizes, whether it’s being accountable for your own tickets or ensuring your team is focused on the top priorities – each of us play our part.</p>
<p>Check out these top tips from our <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Data+Science+Competency+Framework" target="_blank">Competency Framework</a>❗ :</p>
<ul>
<li>Break down complex objectives into clear tasks to deliver incremental value with each iteration</li>
<li>Regularly sync-up with stakeholders to understand priorities and manage delivery expectations</li>
<li>Be a role model to others by demonstrating a focus on delivery, whilst being open to new ideas and continuous improvement</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>Check out the resources to boost your delivery skills on the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Training+Framework" target="_blank">Training Framework</a>❗and our full collection on the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Training+Brochure" target="_blank">Training Brochure</a>❗ Can you spot something missing? <a href="mailto:datascience@nhs.net">Contact us</a>!</p>
</section>
<section id="events" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Events</h1>
</section>
<p>Lots of exciting things coming up! See the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/calendars" target="_blank">full calendar here</a>❗ , and a small selection below.</p>
<section id="onshdr-health-data-science-seminars" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="onshdr-health-data-science-seminars"><a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/health-data-science-seminar-series-tickets-758986237267" target="_blank">ONS/HDR Health Data Science Seminars</a></h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 25th January, 14:00-15:30, Online</strong></p>
<p>This event, ‘Digital footprints’, will feature presentations from guest speakers: Dr Anya Skatova, Senior Research Fellow at the University of Bristol, Professor Will Dixon, Professor of Digital Epidemiology, The University of Manchester and Professor Tim Chico, Professor of Cardiovascular Medicine, from the University of Sheffield.</p>
</section>
<section id="genomics-england-research-seminars" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="genomics-england-research-seminars"><a href="https://www.genomicsengland.co.uk/events/research-seminar-january-2024" target="_blank">Genomics England Research Seminars</a></h3>
<p><strong>Tuesday 30th January, 14:00-15:00, Online</strong></p>
<p>This seminar series showcases the latest research using data from the National Genomic Research Library. Two projects will be presented: ‘Investigating microRNA-associated variation in the Epileptic Encephalopathies’ and ‘Effects of Ancestry in the 100,000 Genomes Project Cancer Pipelines’. (January is clearly Genomics month, with the <a href="https://festivalofgenomics.com/london/en/page/home" target="_blank">Festival of Genomics &amp; Biodata</a> starting tomorrow!)</p>
</section>
<section id="data-bites-48-getting-things-done-with-data-in-government---smart-data-special" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-bites-48-getting-things-done-with-data-in-government---smart-data-special"><a href="https://www.instituteforgovernment.org.uk/event/data-bites-48-getting-things-done-data-government" target="_blank">Data Bites #48: Getting things done with data in government - smart data special</a></h3>
<p><strong>Monday 26th February, 18:00-19:20, Online &amp; London</strong></p>
<p>In an exciting, quickfire format, each speaker has eight minutes to present on data in government. Next month’s speakers include Ben Goldacre among others.</p>
<hr>
<p>See more future events on our <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/calendars" target="_blank">confluence calendar</a>❗</p>
<p>Know of any events we should feature next month?Let us know by clicking the “Contribute” button, or <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="knowledge-sharing" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Knowledge Sharing</h1>
</section>
<p><strong><a href="https://future.nhs.uk/connect.ti/DataAnalytics/messageShowThread?threadid=12369486" target="_blank">Blog: Delivering user centred dashboards</a></strong></p>
<p><strong>Harry Kelleher</strong>, Lead BI Developer, shares his experience building dashboards that make a difference, and how a product thinking approach has been the key to unlocking system-wide value.</p>
<hr>
<p>Stay tuned for an update on what seminars &amp; show and tells will look like in the new team. Please bear with us as it is likely to be a learning process! Contact <a href="mailto:amelia.noonan1@nhs.net">Mia Noonan</a> for more information..</p>
<section id="training-opportunities" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Training Opportunities</h1>
</section>
<p>How much do you actually know about the NHS? Check out the <a href="https://www.kingsfund.org.uk/health-care-explained/online-course" target="_blank">The NHS explained free online course: how the health system in England really works</a>.</p>
<p>With the release of the <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/generative-ai-framework-for-hmg/generative-ai-framework-for-hmg-html" target="_blank">Generative AI Framework for HMG</a>, Civil Service Learning now includes a set of open learning relating to Generative AI, including a <a href="https://learn.civilservice.gov.uk/courses/E0nDu3fET6q3Tg5yOBFn_g" target="_blank">technical curriculum</a>, that is a helpful collection of free resources from <a href="https://www.cloudskillsboost.google/paths/183" target="_blank">Google</a>, <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/paths/copilot/" target="_blank">Microsoft</a> and <a href="https://explore.skillbuilder.aws/learn/course/external/view/elearning/17256/planning-a-generative-ai-project" target="_blank">AWS</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p>Check out all the resources in the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Training+Brochure" target="_blank">Training Brochure</a>! Can you spot something missing? Contact <a href="mailto:datascience@nhs.net">Harriet Sands</a>.</p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<p><a href="https://forms.office.com/pages/responsepage.aspx?id=slTDN7CF9UeyIge0jXdO48pr_29hyJFKpCZ7SYYvjeFUNUVPMUk0STlDRlJMNklIWEI3V0NZVTZXVS4u&amp;route=shorturl" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-success btn-lg">Subscribe to the community</a><a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">Contribute</a><a href="./newsletter.pdf" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">PDF Version</a></p>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>newsletter</category>
  <category>delivery</category>
  <guid>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_01/newsletter.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
