<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Data Science PD newsletter</title>
<link>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/</link>
<atom:link href="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>A newsletter to share professional development tips for data scientists in the NHS
</description>
<generator>quarto-1.5.56</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Professional Development Newsletter August 2024</title>
  <dc:creator>Jennifer Struthers</dc:creator>
  <link>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_08/newsletter.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/images/banner_august.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Welcome to the latest Professional Development newsletter, brought to you by the Data Science skilled team Professional Development Functional Team.</p>
<p>The newsletter team are always happy to receive constructive feedback, and we invite you to send us any contributions you may have.</p>
<p>There are some legacy NHS Digital items which we have identified with❗</p>
<p>If you cannot access something of interest to you, please <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new" target="_blank">reach out</a>.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading! – PD newsletter team</p>
<section id="haca-2024-relive-the-experience" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>HACA 2024: Relive the experience</h1>
</section>
<section id="haca-2024-relive-the-experience-1" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="haca-2024-relive-the-experience-1">HACA 2024: Relive the experience</h2>
<p>Couldn’t make the event in person? Had to pick between two presentations on at the same time? No worries - the Health and Care Analytics conference hosted in July recorded all their presentations and has now uploaded them onto their YouTube channel, and can be easily accessed from <a href="https://haca-conference.nhs.uk/programme/" target="_blank">their site</a>.</p>
<p>HACA was also full of amazing posters on a wide range of topics, so many it was hard to read them all! You can check out the posters on <a href="https://haca-conference.nhs.uk/haca-24-posters/" target="_blank">their site</a> as well.</p>
</section>
<section id="events" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Events</h1>
</section>
<p>Lots of exciting things coming up! See the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/calendars" target="_blank">full calendar here</a>❗, and a small selection below.</p>
<section id="code-dependent---data-ethics-and-society-reading-group" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="code-dependent---data-ethics-and-society-reading-group"><a href="https://www.tickettailor.com/events/dataethics/1292240/r/gss" target="_blank">Code Dependent - Data Ethics and Society Reading Group</a></h3>
<p><strong>Wednesday 4th September, 13:00-14:00, Teams</strong></p>
<p>We will be discussing Code Dependent by Madhumita Murgia:</p>
<p>The lives of a British poet, an Uber Eats courier in Pittsburgh, an Indian doctor, and a Chinese activist in exile are linked by their unexpected encounters with AI. In this book Madhumita Murgia, AI Editor at the FT, highlights the voices of ordinary people, to show how automated systems are reshaping lives all over the world, from technology that marks children as future criminals to an app that is helping to give diagnoses to a remote trial community.</p>
<p>See <a href="https://data-ethics-and-society.github.io/data-ethics-and-society-reading-group/" target="_blank">our GitHub page</a> for more information. Registration closes Friday 23rd August 17:00</p>
</section>
<section id="health-data-science-seminar-series-transforming-healthcare-ai-in-health-data-science" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="health-data-science-seminar-series-transforming-healthcare-ai-in-health-data-science"><a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/health-data-science-seminar-series-tickets-947750486217?aff=ebdssbdestsearch" target="_blank">Health Data Science Seminar Series: Transforming Healthcare: AI in Health Data Science</a></h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 12th September 2024, 14:00 - 15:30, Teams</strong></p>
<p>This series of seminars presents an exciting opportunity to hear about recent developments in health data science, generate ideas and help build the health data science community. It is hosted by the ONS’s Data Science Campus and Health Analysis Team in partnership with Health Data Research UK (HDR UK).</p>
<p>The Health Data Science Seminar series provides a dedicated space for data scientists, policymakers, health professionals, academics, epidemiologists, statisticians and other members of the data science community to come together and explore the potential of data science, to help improve health and health policy.</p>
<p>This event will feature presentations from guest speakers including:</p>
<p>Dr Siegfried Karl Wagner - Ophthalmologist and senior research fellow, University College London Professor Christopher Yau - Professor of Artificial Intelligence and Turing AI Fellow, University of Oxford</p>
</section>
<section id="python-elt-with-dlt-zero-to-hero-workshop" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="python-elt-with-dlt-zero-to-hero-workshop"><a href="https://lu.ma/ozfm3thk" target="_blank">Python ELT with dlt: Zero to Hero workshop</a></h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 19th September, Thursday 26th September, 17:00-19:00, Online</strong></p>
<p>A zero-to-hero workshop for learning ELT, dlt and advanced features around it. The goal is to have you walk away with the ability and understanding to build robust ELT pipelines. This will essentially upskill your Python EL ability from just learning to senior data (platform) engineer level.</p>
<p>This is a two-part workshop, with a target audience of data platform engineers, Python First data engineers, and Python normies who want to learn best practice data engineering.</p>
</section>
<section id="data-science-festival-oktoberfest" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-science-festival-oktoberfest"><a href="https://datasciencefestival.com/event/oktoberfest-2024/" target="_blank">Data Science Festival: Oktoberfest</a></h3>
<p><strong>Saturday 19th October 2024, 9am-5pm, CodeNode London</strong></p>
<p>Apply for a FREE ballot entry to this years DSF Oktoberfest. Top tech speakers, incredible partners and a thriving community. There will be a mixture of talks featured at the festival, covering all things data (science, engineering, etc) and a variety of technical levels.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLwzX3WM0AfxopbhVhGCA373Xk-7wNhLfq" target="_blank">Check out highlights from last year here.</a></p>
</section>
<section id="nhs-rpysoc-2024-conference" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="nhs-rpysoc-2024-conference"><a href="https://nhsrcommunity.com/events/nhs-r-nhs-pycom-open-source-conference-nhs-rpysoc-2024-2024-ticket-for-in-person-attendance-on-thursday-21-november-2024/" target="_blank">NHS RPySOC 2024 Conference</a></h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 21st-22nd November, 9am-5pm, in-person (Birmingham) / Online</strong></p>
<p>The <strong>NHS RPySOC 2024 conference</strong> is open for registration now! It will be on <strong>21st &amp; 22nd November in Birmingham</strong>. This is jointly hosted by the NHS R Community and NHS.pycom, and also promotes Open Source.</p>
<ul>
<li>Day 1 will be a mixture of presentations, workshops and lightening talks</li>
<li>Day 2 will be ‘Unconference’ with suggestions for topics being taken on day 1.</li>
</ul>
<p>It’s a great chance to show off our work, share our learning with a like minded community and learn a few things yourself, such as the state of the industry and how techniques are being applied elsewhere.</p>
<p>You can either attend:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://nhsrcommunity.com/events/nhs-r-nhs-pycom-open-source-conference-nhs-rpysoc-2024-2024-ticket-for-in-person-attendance-on-thursday-21-november-2024/">In-Person (The ICC, Hall 11, Birmingham B1 2EA</a> (Sold Out: Waiting List Only)</li>
<li><a href="https://nhsrcommunity.com/events/nhs-r-nhs-pycom-open-source-conference-2024-rpysoc-2024-ticket-for-virtual-attendance-on-thursday-21-november-2024/">Online</a></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>See more future events on our <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Events+calendar" target="_blank">confluence calendar</a>❗</p>
<p>Know of any events we should feature next month? Let us know by clicking the “Contribute” button, or <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="data-science-discussion-democracy" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Data Science Discussion: Democracy</h1>
</section>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_08/robot_parliament.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Cartoon image of a future UK parliament filled with robots</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Recently, we held another Data Science Discussion, where we encourage people to look into a different area or use case of data science than they might strictly look at in their day job and spark discussion on a peer-to-peer level.</p>
<p>This time we delved into the intriguing topic of data science and democracy, hosted by Mia Noonan.</p>
<p>Mia kicked off the discussion by asking the group to consider the different ways data science could interact with and potentially reshape the political landscape. One of the key ideas presented was the concept of AI-driven profiles that could be created based on an individual’s opinions and values, with the potential to vote on bills and acts on their behalf. This led to a lively debate on the implications of such a system, and what type of democracy we’d like to see AI help facilitate- representative, direct or deliberative.</p>
<p>Throughout the session, the group expressed a healthy dose of skepticism, particularly regarding the biases inherent in large language models (LLMs) and AI systems. Concerns were raised about the potential for AI to reflect and even exacerbate existing biases, as well as the broader implications for democracy and personal agency. The discussion highlighted the complex and often controversial nature of combining AI with politics, but also the potential for innovative applications that could transform how we engage with governance.</p>
<p>The Professional Development Functional Team is excited to continue hosting these monthly Data Science Discussions. If you have a data science topic you’re passionate about and would like to share with others, please reach out to us to host a session. The format is designed to be collaborative and conversational, with most of the session taking place in breakout rooms, so all you need is a spark of inspiration to get the conversation started.</p>
<p>Interested in learning a bit more about this topic?</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CyGWML6cI_k" target="_blank">A TED talk on ‘automating’ politicians</a></li>
<li><a href="https://blogs.bath.ac.uk/iprblog/2024/02/22/how-ai-could-help-citizens-assemblies-make-well-informed-decisions/" target="_blank">How LLMs could help citizens assemblies</a></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>Stay tuned for an update on what seminars &amp; show and tells will look like in the new team. Please bear with us as it is likely to be a learning process! Contact <a href="mailto:amelia.noonan1@nhs.net">Mia Noonan</a> for more information.</p>
<section id="training-opportunities" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Training Opportunities</h1>
</section>
<section id="large-language-model-tutorial" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="large-language-model-tutorial">Large Language Model Tutorial</h2>
<p>Curious about how you could create your own LLM but worried it’ll be too complicated or costly? Adam and Sam Hollings have put together an LLM tutorial to walk you through some simple implementations. The software is all free and runs inside Google Collab, so it won’t cost you anything. Some ability with python will be helpful, and an interest in data science and LLMs will help!</p>
<p>Instructions for set up, or for contacting the owners can be found in <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/llm_tutorial" target="_blank">this GitHub repository</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="technical-writing-courses" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="technical-writing-courses">Technical Writing Courses</h2>
<p>Sometimes when we spend most days writing code we forget a huge part of our jobs is communicating our work and documenting it. <a href="https://developers.google.com/tech-writing" target="_blank">Google have a collection of courses and learning resources</a> aiming to improve your technical documentation skills. Learn how to plan and author technical documents. You can also learn about the role of technical writers at Google.</p>
</section>
<section id="need-a-quick-break" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Need a Quick Break?</h1>
</section>
<p><a href="https://mywordle.strivemath.com/?word=hcxln" target="_blank">How many tries will it take you?</a></p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<p><a href="https://forms.office.com/e/JJsmgPmVVJ" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-success btn-lg">Subscribe (nhs.net login)</a><a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">Contribute</a><a href="./newsletter.pdf" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">PDF Version</a></p>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>newsletter</category>
  <guid>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_08/newsletter.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Professional Development Newsletter July 2024</title>
  <dc:creator>Jennifer Struthers</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Warren Davies</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Liz Kelly</dc:creator>
  <link>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_07/newsletter.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/images/banner_july.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Welcome to the latest Professional Development newsletter, brought to you by the Data Science skilled team Professional Development Functional Team.</p>
<p>The newsletter team are always happy to receive constructive feedback, and we invite you to send us any contributions you may have.</p>
<p>There are some legacy NHS Digital items which we have identified with❗</p>
<p>If you cannot access something of interest to you, please <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new" target="_blank">reach out</a>.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading! – PD newsletter team</p>
<section id="health-and-care-analytics-conference" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Health and Care Analytics Conference</h1>
</section>
<p><em>This month some of the NHS England Data Science team went to the Health and Care Analytics Conference (HACA) 2024, hosted in Telford. The team had various talks, posters and workshops delivered at the conference about our work and projects. Warren Davies reports back.</em></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_07/warren_talk.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>NHS England RAP Star Warren Davies giving a talk at HACA on RAP Principles</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>At the HACA conference 2024 I gave a talk on RAP to a huge crowd, over 4,000 people, great people, the best people. OK more like 70. And I also helped run workshops on Python and RAP. I highly recommend the experience overall. I gained the following XP:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>+10 Planning</strong> – it’s tricky to plan when you don’t know in advance the size and experience of the audience (in the workshops we opted to give a flavour of what was possible, along with some simple exercises people could follow along with).</p></li>
<li><p><strong>+10 Schmoozing</strong> – it is actually very easy. People are very happy to talk about their work and how you might be able to help them.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>+20 Resilience</strong> – public speaking can be nerve wracking but that is OK, it’s just weakness leaving the body.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>But you also have the opportunity to help other people. It’s easy to take for granted in NHS England that we basically have a huge bunch of geniuses at our beck and call that that we can pester and learn from every day. But not every analyst in the wider NHS and health world is so lucky. Within trusts and regional organisations, there are often small teams - or even individuals - who do similar work to us but don’t have the kind of support we do.</p>
<p>With events like HACA we have the chance to connect with them, and point them to resources and communities they might not know about. Which not only helps them, but gives you a warm fuzzy feeling inside too (incidentally, it also ticks a whole load of those “Sharing knowledge” boxes on the competency framework…).</p>
<p>You should definitely go next time. You will build your networking skills, help people out, and get loads of great examples you can use when you apply for that promotion. Plus, everyone loves a road trip right?</p>
<section id="school-placement" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>School Placement</h1>
</section>
<p>In July, the NHS England Data Science Professional Development Functional Team hosted a school placement, hosting five students from a London based secondary school to teach them about our work and show them some of the skills they would need to start a career in data science. Liz Kelly describes her experience, working to prepare this week to show the school pupils what our team does, and give them a taste of how it might be to work with us.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_07/school.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Some really happy cartoon kids on a school placement, ready to learn about the NHS England Data Science team.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>This was a rewarding yet difficult task, involving a lot of admin, paperwork, and even a conversation with NHS England lawyers to check we were dotting all our i’s and crossing all our t’s. Naturally, after all this, there were still the dreaded tech setup issues (<em>sigh</em>). But Chaeyoon did an amazing job at fixing them in record time, so the students could still get the most out of their placement.</p>
<p>As a graduate in the Data Science team, I know first-hand how valuable it is for colleagues to take time to explain the various cogs in the NHS system. Because let’s be honest, it’s a bit complicated. So, we made sure to cover as many areas as possible to help with this understanding.</p>
<p>About half of the data scientists (a total of 22) met students during the placement week, alongside more indirect engagements from others such as helping with the training materials. The students rotated through four data science teams and were introduced to two methods of data science ways of working: python programming and collaborative works on GitHub. At the end of the placement week, they had a mock interview and an optional task to build a classifier function with if-else conditions to find which group (from the placement sessions) they could match to the session information. It is incredible to think some of the students had never touched programming before and yet, by the end of the week, they had a basic understanding of Python!</p>
<p>I personally enjoyed the challenge of organising the timetable for the students and leading them through workshops and career talks. Who doesn’t love a good to-do list! And since I don’t cover this kind of outreach in my day-to-day role, this was an excellent opportunity. I could tick off those leadership and mentoring competencies, not to mention dealing with complexity (those pesky access and tech issues). I will admit, teaching a group over Teams is trickier than I thought, especially interactive sessions. The students were eager to discuss and answer questions but sometimes their meeting room microphone didn’t quite catch what they were saying … or perhaps it was just me and the London accent.</p>
<p>As this was the first of its kind, it took a while to discover all the rules and policies. Now we have done this once, subsequent placements should be a lot easier to host. We have collated the resources used <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/PD_kanban_board/blob/main/PD%20Outreach/Host%20a%20placement.md" target="_blank">here</a>, currently accessible to those in NHSE DS GitHub team. We are working to collate and publish our resources more widely in the future.</p>
<p>As soon as we say “I work for the NHS”, peoples first thoughts are frontline staff, not data scientists. It wasn’t until I was graduating university that I stumbled across data science roles in the NHS and even then, it was purely accidental. When I think back to my time at school I would have loved to do this work experience week in the NHS.</p>
<p>I know I am not alone when I say just how important it is to introduce young people to Data Science, particularly in the NHS. This provides them with more avenues to follow and more ideas of what is out there. It makes the world of possibilities just that bit bigger.</p>
<p>Once again, thank you to everyone involved. I’m sure you’ll agree the placement week was a success, just perhaps short of a few tea and biscuit breaks. The students are not used to being at a desk all day!</p>
<section id="events" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Events</h1>
</section>
<p>Lots of exciting things coming up! See the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/calendars" target="_blank">full calendar here</a>❗</p>
<section id="practical-applications-of-generative-ai-building-a-chatbot-answering-questions-about-your-documents." class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="practical-applications-of-generative-ai-building-a-chatbot-answering-questions-about-your-documents."><a href="https://datasciencefestival.com/session/dunnhumby-talk/" target="_blank">Practical applications of Generative AI: building a chatbot answering questions about your documents.</a></h3>
<p><strong>Tuesday 13th August 2024, 13:00 - 14:00, Online</strong></p>
<p>The recent explosion on the scene of Generative AI and Large Language Models (LLMs) is creating a vast array of opportunities. There is more than one way to leverage this recent breakthrough. You can create a chatbot by directly “plugging” to a LLM and start asking questions. However, LLMs are limited to the information available in the data they have seen during their training. So how to build a chatbot that will be able to answer questions related to documents that the model has never seen. One solution is to use a technique called “Retrieval Augmented Generation” (RAG). After an introduction of Generative AI and transformers, we will go through the RAG logic and explore its benefits and potential drawbacks. The talk is intended for anyone interested in generative AI and its potential applications.</p>
</section>
<section id="translational-science-methods-club-explainable-ai" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="translational-science-methods-club-explainable-ai"><a href="https://www.turing.ac.uk/events/translational-science-methods-club-explainable-ai" target="_blank">Translational Science Methods Club: Explainable AI</a></h3>
<p><strong>Tuesday 20th Aug 2024, 15:30 - 17:00, Virtual Seminar</strong></p>
<p>The theme of this T-SciM event will be explainable AI (XAI). This refers to a range of approaches that seek to design or evaluate ways to make the outputs of artificial intelligence algorithms more interpretable. Such explainability is important to better understand the mechanisms underlying the models computations and determine how trustworthy and generalisable their results are.</p>
<p>We will be joined by 3 speakers, who will give short talks introducing their work on XAI, followed by a panel discussion with questions and prompts from the audience.</p>
<p>Speakers include: Dr Ahmed Salih, Dr Tapabrata (Rohan) Chakraborty and Sophie Martin (ex-PhD intern with the NHSE DS team).</p>
</section>
<section id="health-data-science-seminar-series-transforming-healthcare-ai-in-health-data-science" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="health-data-science-seminar-series-transforming-healthcare-ai-in-health-data-science"><a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/health-data-science-seminar-series-tickets-947750486217?aff=ebdssbdestsearch" target="_blank">Health Data Science Seminar Series: Transforming Healthcare: AI in Health Data Science</a></h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 12th September 2024, 14:00 - 15:30, Teams</strong></p>
<p>This series of seminars presents an exciting opportunity to hear about recent developments in health data science, generate ideas and help build the health data science community. It is hosted by the ONS’s Data Science Campus and Health Analysis Team in partnership with Health Data Research UK (HDR UK).</p>
<p>The Health Data Science Seminar series provides a dedicated space for data scientists, policymakers, health professionals, academics, epidemiologists, statisticians and other members of the data science community to come together and explore the potential of data science, to help improve health and health policy.</p>
<p>This event will feature presentations from guest speakers including:</p>
<p>Dr Siegfried Karl Wagner - Ophthalmologist and senior research fellow, University College London Professor Christopher Yau - Professor of Artificial Intelligence and Turing AI Fellow, University of Oxford</p>
</section>
<section id="data-science-festival-oktoberfest" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-science-festival-oktoberfest"><a href="https://datasciencefestival.com/event/oktoberfest-2024/" target="_blank">Data Science Festival: Oktoberfest</a></h3>
<p><strong>Saturday 19th October 2024, 9am-5pm, CodeNode London</strong></p>
<p>Apply for a FREE ballot entry to this years DSF Oktoberfest. Top tech speakers, incredible partners and a thriving community. There will be a mixture of talks featured at the festival, covering all things data (science, engineering, etc) and a variety of technical levels.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLwzX3WM0AfxopbhVhGCA373Xk-7wNhLfq" target="_blank">Check out highlights from last year here.</a></p>
</section>
<section id="nhs-rpysoc-2024-conference---registration-opened" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="nhs-rpysoc-2024-conference---registration-opened"><a href="https://nhsrcommunity.com/events/nhs-r-nhs-pycom-open-source-conference-nhs-rpysoc-2024-2024-ticket-for-in-person-attendance-on-thursday-21-november-2024/" target="_blank">NHS RPySOC 2024 Conference - registration opened</a></h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 21st-22nd November, 9am-5pm, in-person (Birmingham) / Online</strong></p>
<p>The <strong>NHS RPySOC 2024 conference</strong> is open for registration now! It will be on <strong>21st &amp; 22nd November in Birmingham</strong>. This is jointed hosted by the NHS R Community and NHS.pycom, and also promotes Open Source.</p>
<ul>
<li>Day 1 will be a mixture of presentations, workshops and lightening talks</li>
<li>Day 2 <strong>(in-person only)</strong> will be ‘Unconference’ with suggestions for topics being taken on day 1.</li>
</ul>
<p>It’s a great chance to show off our work, share our learning with a like minded community and learn a few things yourself, such as the state of the industry and how techniques are being applied elsewhere.</p>
<p>You can either attend:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://nhsrcommunity.com/events/nhs-r-nhs-pycom-open-source-conference-nhs-rpysoc-2024-2024-ticket-for-in-person-attendance-on-thursday-21-november-2024/">In-Person (The ICC, Hall 11, Birmingham B1 2EA</a></li>
<li><a href="https://nhsrcommunity.com/events/nhs-r-nhs-pycom-open-source-conference-2024-rpysoc-2024-ticket-for-virtual-attendance-on-thursday-21-november-2024/">Online</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong><a href="https://nhsrway.nhsrcommunity.com/conference.html#rpysoc-24-conference---call-for-abstracts" target="_blank">Got something to present? Abstract submissions deadline extended to Monday 12th August!</a></strong></p>
<hr>
<p>See more future events on our <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Events+calendar" target="_blank">confluence calendar</a>❗ Know of any events we should feature next month? Let us know by clicking the “Contribute” button, or <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="digital-health-hive" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Digital Health Hive</h1>
</section>
<p>Yorkshire based, and interested in joining a community of patients, healthcare professionals and decision makers, companies, and researchers with an interest in digital health, and engaging and interacting with one another to develop digital health research and tools? Join the Digital Health Hive by completing <a href="https://forms.office.com/e/B0gNDcYYNT" target="_blank">this form</a> or emailing <a href="mailto:digitalhealthhive@leeds.ac.uk">digitalhealthhive@leeds.ac.uk</a></p>
<div class="text-center">
<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_07/digital_health_hive.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div>
<hr>
<section id="need-a-quick-break" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Need a Quick Break?</h1>
</section>
<p><a href="https://mywordle.strivemath.com/?word=yzvdy" target="_blank">How many tries will it take you?</a></p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<p><a href="https://forms.office.com/e/JJsmgPmVVJ" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-success btn-lg">Subscribe (nhs.net login)</a><a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">Contribute</a><a href="./newsletter.pdf" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">PDF Version</a></p>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>newsletter</category>
  <guid>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_07/newsletter.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Professional Development Newsletter June 2024</title>
  <dc:creator>Jennifer Struthers</dc:creator>
  <link>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_06/newsletter.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/images/banner_june.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Welcome to the latest Professional Development newsletter, brought to you by the Data Science skilled team Professional Development Functional Team.</p>
<p>The newsletter team are always happy to receive constructive feedback, and we invite you to send us any contributions you may have.</p>
<p>There are some legacy NHS Digital items which we have identified with❗</p>
<p>If you cannot access something of interest to you, please <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new" target="_blank">reach out</a>.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading! – PD newsletter team</p>
<section id="highlights" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Highlights</h1>
</section>
<section id="national-competency-framework-tool" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="national-competency-framework-tool"><a href="https://future.nhs.uk/DataAnalytics/view?objectID=163018181" target="_blank">National Competency Framework Tool</a></h2>
<p>The Professional Development Function Team want to promote the National Competency Framework Tool to help shape your objectives for the year ahead.</p>
<p>You can use this tool in any way you like:</p>
<ul>
<li>Do a full self-assessment to build a personal profile of yourself, marking areas where you want to target your development and understanding where you measure up against job bands.</li>
<li>Review areas where you are interested in developing; we recommend checking out the additional modules of the framework covering:
<ul>
<li>Specialised technical skills that you may have developed in a unique role within a team, like Data Visualisation, Machine Learning, or Data Automation.</li>
<li>Broader professional skill areas such as Behaviours, Leadership and Management, and Working in Team that apply across roles regardless of background.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>See where you stand for other job areas like Data Analysis and Data Engineering.</li>
</ul>
<p>While this framework is still in the early stages of adoption, feedback is key to help the Professional Development Function Team and the National Competency Framework team develop more resources. Let us know if and how you are using the tool, or any other ways we can help you use the National Competency Framework <a href="https://forms.office.com/e/XGuTzWcB5j" target="_blank">through this form</a></p>
</section>
<section id="masters-in-research-mres-in-data-science-analytics-for-health" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="masters-in-research-mres-in-data-science-analytics-for-health">Masters in Research (MRes) in Data Science &amp; Analytics for Health</h2>
<p>Applications now open for this funded course -the short application form can be found <a href="https://forms.office.com/e/21dmLrdn4k" target="_blank">here</a>. For more information, please see this <a href="https://nhs.sharepoint.com/:w:/r/sites/X24_DataAnalytics/Shared%20Documents/CPD%20opportunities/Masters%20in%20Research%20frequently%20asked%20questions%20doc.docx?d=w189258124ad541b89217f28fa199c587&amp;csf=1&amp;web=1&amp;e=BlEfB8&amp;xsdata=MDV8MDJ8amVubmlmZXIuc3RydXRoZXJzMUBuaHMubmV0fDNiYjM0YTJlNDBiZTQxZDBhZWFiMDhkYzk2NzgwYTdlfDM3YzM1NGIyODViMDQ3ZjViMjIyMDdiNDhkNzc0ZWUzfDB8MHw2Mzg1NTA2OTA3MjgyMzA0NzF8VW5rbm93bnxUV0ZwYkdac2IzZDhleUpXSWpvaU1DNHdMakF3TURBaUxDSlFJam9pVjJsdU16SWlMQ0pCVGlJNklrMWhhV3dpTENKWFZDSTZNbjA9fDB8fHw%3d&amp;sdata=RW1RSE9sOCsrbS9OZG82L1Y5bnBEeXRFMlZhaldoTkJwWE9GZXZLRFRhYz0%3d">FAQ document</a>. This is a fantastic opportunity for those who want to deepen their expertise in data science and analytics, with a specific focus on a health data research project. The syllabus will include campus-based or remote lectures and practical-based training in:</p>
<ul>
<li>Machine learning</li>
<li>Artificial Intelligence</li>
<li>Programming for Data Science</li>
<li>Data Science &amp; Analytics for Causal Inference and Prediction</li>
</ul>
<p>A workplace-based research project, undertaken within NHS England, supported by the NHS England Data Science Team. A Masters course is a significant personal investment of time, a day a week will be allocated to attend university and it is anticipated that there will be three to six hours per week worth of additional study. Potential applicants should consider this before applying. It is also a substantial investment from NHS England and will therefore be subject to a rigorous, fair and transparent selection process.</p>
<p>Applications will close <strong>August 4th</strong>, and the course is due to start in <strong>October</strong>. If you have any questions, please get in touch with <a href="mailto:s.culkin@nhs.net">Sarah Culkin</a> or <a href="mailto:rupert.chaplin1@nhs.net">Rupert Chaplin</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="events" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Events</h1>
</section>
<p>Lots of exciting things coming up! See the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/calendars" target="_blank">full calendar here</a>❗</p>
<section id="data-and-ai-ethics-community-meeting-ethical-considerations-in-data-linkage-with-splink" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-and-ai-ethics-community-meeting-ethical-considerations-in-data-linkage-with-splink"><a href="https://www.tickettailor.com/events/publicsectoruk/1289987" target="_blank">Data and AI Ethics Community meeting: Ethical Considerations in Data Linkage with Splink</a></h3>
<p><strong>Tuesday 2nd July 13:00-14:00, Teams</strong></p>
<p>Splink is a Ministry of Justices open-source software which uses unsupervised machine learning to link together millions of data records belonging to justice system users. This talk will cover the many and varied ethical considerations of performing data linkage with Splink, how we address these within our work and improvements we are planning for the future. The Data Linkage Hub at NHSE is exploring the use of Splink as a probabilistic data linkage tool. Reach out if you want to know more and familiarize yourself with our pipeline.</p>
</section>
<section id="linking-analysts-in-leeds" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="linking-analysts-in-leeds">Linking Analysts In Leeds</h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 4th July 13:00-14:30, BEC Ground Floor 7&amp;8 Wellington Place and Teams</strong></p>
<p>Linking Analysts In Leeds is an opportunity for analysts working in different civil service departments in Wellington Place in Leeds to meet-up, make links, and share learning.</p>
<p>This session will involves speakers from DataCamp running a session showcasing <a href="https://www.datacamp.com" target="_blank">DataCamp</a> and the extensive training resources it offers.</p>
<p>If you wish to join the meeting please complete the following form (this covers in person and online): <a href="https://forms.office.com/pages/responsepage.aspx?id=PPdSrBr9mkqOekokjzE54W_NLvrah2tMkR4LC77BWoFUMFhKUlBEOTlBU0dQM0g2UUIyMVo4QzNWTi4u" target="_blank">Linking Analysts In Leeds - July</a></p>
</section>
<section id="london-data-week-2024" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="london-data-week-2024"><a href="https://londondataweek.org/" target="_blank">London Data Week 2024</a></h3>
<p><strong>1st-7th July 2024, Online and in person</strong></p>
<p>London Data Week is a city-wide, distributed festival of events focusing on all things data. Data is a major part of our everyday lives, and shapes many of the decisions we make – as well as the decisions that are made about us – whether we know it or not. We believe that everyone should have a seat at the table when it comes to data, and that is the guiding principle behind our core values: to be collaborative, open and inclusive. So, we invite you to be part of the conversation by joining us and our event partners at a London Data Week event.</p>
<p>Find out more about London Data Week and what events are being held <a href="https://londondataweek.org/" target="_blank">here</a></p>
</section>
<section id="health-and-care-analytics-conference-2024" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="health-and-care-analytics-conference-2024"><a href="https://haca-conference.nhs.uk/" target="_blank">Health and Care Analytics Conference 2024</a></h3>
<p><strong>23rd-24th July 2024, Telford International Centre</strong></p>
<p>The HACA conference is a celebration of the great work of health and care analysts bringing together analysts and leaders and decision makers to showcase how analysts can help leaders make high quality decisions.</p>
<p>The programme is now published - <a href="https://haca-conference.nhs.uk/programme/" target="_blank">check out what events and talks you might be interested in!</a> Beforehand, have a look at some of their <a href="https://haca-conference.nhs.uk/e-labs/" target="_blank">E-Labs, running 8th-10th July</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="nhs-rpysoc-2024-conference---registration-opened" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="nhs-rpysoc-2024-conference---registration-opened"><a href="https://nhsrcommunity.com/events/nhs-r-nhs-pycom-open-source-conference-nhs-rpysoc-2024-2024-ticket-for-in-person-attendance-on-thursday-21-november-2024/" target="_blank">NHS RPySOC 2024 Conference - registration opened</a></h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 21st-22nd November, 9am-5pm, in-person (Birmingham) / Online</strong></p>
<p>The <strong>NHS RPySOC 2024 conference</strong> is open for registration now! It will be on <strong>21st &amp; 22nd November in Birmingham</strong>. This is jointed hosted by the NHS R Community and NHS.pycom, and also promotes Open Source.</p>
<ul>
<li>Day 1 will be a mixture of presentations, workshops and lightening talks</li>
<li>Day 2 <strong>(in-person only)</strong> will be ‘Unconference’ with suggestions for topics being taken on day 1.</li>
</ul>
<p>It’s a great chance to show off our work, share our learning with a like minded community and learn a few things yourself, such as the state of the industry and how techniques are being applied elsewhere.</p>
<p>You can either attend:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://nhsrcommunity.com/events/nhs-r-nhs-pycom-open-source-conference-nhs-rpysoc-2024-2024-ticket-for-in-person-attendance-on-thursday-21-november-2024/">In-Person (The ICC, Hall 11, Birmingham B1 2EA</a></li>
<li><a href="https://nhsrcommunity.com/events/nhs-r-nhs-pycom-open-source-conference-2024-rpysoc-2024-ticket-for-virtual-attendance-on-thursday-21-november-2024/">Online</a></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>See more future events on our <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Events+calendar" target="_blank">confluence calendar</a>❗ Know of any events we should feature next month? Let us know by clicking the “Contribute” button, or <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="interview-with-a-data-scientist" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Interview with a Data Scientist</h1>
</section>
<p>Mia Noonan is a Senior Data Scientist in the NHS England Data Science team, who first joined the company as a member of the 2021 graduate cohort.</p>
<p><strong>Thank you for agreeing to be the first “Interview with a Data Scientist” for the PD newsletter! I was wondering, could you tell me a bit about your background and what motivated you to pursue a career in data science in the NHS?</strong></p>
<p>M: I did economics and politics at Uni, but after a year in finance thought this isn’t for me as I didn’t really gel with the sort of work that I was doing at the time. In contrast, I found myself really interested by the work that the IT department was doing because I could see the impact that it had on my day-to-day. For example, there was one task where I had to process a load of invoices and that would take me all afternoon and then one day they just went, <em>“Oh yeah, we’ve automated that”</em> and I was like <em>“what?!”</em> – and immediately wanted to be on the side which was doing that!</p>
<p>So that was one of my main motivations to go into computer science, and I decided to do a computer science Master’s at Bath. It was quite an intense year, but it gave me the upskilling that I needed to go into more technical roles. I got introduced to data science right at the end of that year from my final research project. It was an NLP project where I had to analyse the transcription of everything that’s said in parliament, to understand where MPs are focusing their attention. I really enjoyed it because it was a bridge between economics, politics and computer science.</p>
<p>Once I did that project I thought, <em>yeah, this is this is super cool, this is exactly where I want to be</em>. Someone I was speaking to mentioned that there was a data science team in the NHS and I was like <em>wow, I didn’t know</em> - but immediately wanted to be a part of it! I was lucky enough to get a placement in the data science team through the NHS Digital graduate scheme, and the rest is history…!</p>
<p><strong>What specific professional development tools or resources did you find most helpful in skilling up on your time of the graduate scheme?</strong></p>
<p>M: I had Kin as a line manager, so that was great. He was very, very good at articulating <a href="https://www.atlassian.com/blog/productivity/how-to-write-smart-goals" target="_blank">SMART goals</a>, and I think that really helped because the goals were so well laid out, a lot of the competencies I could just tick off on the job due to the variety of work in the data linkage enhancement team. I was lucky with my placement, my line manager, and had a lot of the things I could just do on the job, which was great.</p>
<p>In terms of technical skills, <a href="https://www.pluralsight.com/" target="_blank">Pluralsight</a> would be my bread and butter in terms of a tool and a resource to turn to just to upskill. If I’m like <em>“oh, I don’t know what an S3 bucket is, I need to do some AWS training”</em>, if there’s a specific technical skill I need to learn, I’d go to that.</p>
<p>I think I find that I probably sometimes upskill a little bit easier when I’m doing something on the job and practically applying it straight away. I really try and actively seek out the opportunities to go and upskill in other areas. I try not to be passive about my development goals and seek out the opportunities, and if there’s something that interests me, follow up on it.</p>
<p><strong>What keeps you motivated and passionate about your work and data science with the NHS?</strong></p>
<p>M: It’s really exciting just being able to continuously learn new things and be on the forefront of new disruptive technologies. I like the fact that the work we’re doing is making a real difference to the NHS, it’s great.</p>
<p>Being surrounded by such great team members also makes a big difference. The team has got so much knowledge inside of it that it’s easy to organically learn things from people. It’s a positive learning environment and has a culture of safety and openness, there’s no one in the team I would feel hesitant going to ask a question to.</p>
<p>And then also having that culture of wanting everyone to do well, makes you want to do well because you want to contribute back and create that positive cycle for the whole team and feel like you’re contributing towards that.</p>
<p><strong>The current graduates will be embarking on their End of Scheme in the next fortnight or so. What is a piece of advice that you have for them?</strong></p>
<p>M: In terms of something that’s relevant to this point in terms of their career and passing their End of Scheme I would say that my biggest piece of advice would be don’t stop being curious about things. They’ve had a really intense upskilling period where they’ve gone through two years of intense rotations, being exposed to those different areas, but don’t stop that momentum just because you’ve rolled off the scheme. Go out, speak to loads of different teams, different people, keep networking. Keep trying different projects, different things because you’ll learn more and more about what interests and motivates you, because two years sounds like a long time, but it’s really short.</p>
<p><em>This interview was edited for brevity</em></p>
<hr>
<section id="training-opportunities" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Training Opportunities</h1>
</section>
<section id="nhs-england-and-microsoft---digital-accessibility-fundamentals-training" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="nhs-england-and-microsoft---digital-accessibility-fundamentals-training"><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-gb/collections/xee0tzym2j7zqm" target="_blank">NHS England and Microsoft - Digital Accessibility Fundamentals Training</a></h2>
<p>NHS England have teamed up with Microsoft to put some training together on Accessibility Fundamentals. For more information and details on how to sign up for the training, check out the <a href="https://nhs.sharepoint.com/sites/thehub/_layouts/15/Event.aspx?ListGuid=dc2bb1a1-a738-4cfd-87a6-500fce05afe2&amp;ItemId=1595" target="_blank">post on the NHS England Hub</a>.</p>
<p>There has also been added information for the event onto the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Accessibility+Hub#AccessibilityHub-HighlightedContent" target="_blank">Accessibility Hub!</a>❗</p>
</section>
<section id="microsoft-learn-for-github" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="microsoft-learn-for-github"><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/github/" target="_blank">Microsoft Learn for GitHub</a></h2>
<p>Check out the GitHub training available on Microsoft Learn, modules available include:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/intro-to-git/" target="_blank">Introduction to Git</a></li>
<li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/learn-continuous-integration-github-actions/" target="_blank">Learn continuous integration with GitHub Actions</a></li>
<li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/manage-sensitive-data-security-policies/" target="_blank">Manage sensitive data and security policies within GitHub</a></li>
<li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/modules/create-custom-github-actions/" target="_blank">Create and publish custom GitHub actions</a></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>Check out all the resources in the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Training+Brochure" target="_blank">Training Brochure</a>! Can you spot something missing? <a href="mailto:datascience@nhs.net">Contact us</a>!</p>
</section>
<section id="need-a-quick-break" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Need a Quick Break?</h1>
</section>
<p><a href="https://mywordle.strivemath.com/?word=oyzow" target="_blank">How many tries will it take you?</a></p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<p><a href="https://forms.office.com/e/JJsmgPmVVJ" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-success btn-lg">Subscribe (nhs.net login)</a><a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">Contribute</a><a href="./newsletter.pdf" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">PDF Version</a></p>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>newsletter</category>
  <category>interview with a data scientist</category>
  <guid>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_06/newsletter.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Professional Development Newsletter May 2024</title>
  <dc:creator>Jennifer Struthers</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sam Hollings</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ben Wallace</dc:creator>
  <link>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_05/newsletter.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/images/banner_may.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Welcome to the latest Professional Development newsletter, brought to you by the Data Science skilled team Professional Development Functional Team.</p>
<p>The newsletter team are always happy to receive constructive feedback, and we invite you to send us any contributions you may have.</p>
<p>There are some legacy NHS Digital items which we have identified with❗</p>
<p>If you cannot access something of interest to you, please <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new" target="_blank">reach out</a>.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading! – PD newsletter team</p>
<section id="events" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Events</h1>
</section>
<p>Lots of exciting things coming up! We are working on revamping the calendar and hope to have something out soon!</p>
<section id="analystx-huddle-ai-enabled-shared-care-records-using-google-cloud-to-transform-healthcare-in-yorkshire-and-humber" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analystx-huddle-ai-enabled-shared-care-records-using-google-cloud-to-transform-healthcare-in-yorkshire-and-humber"><a href="https://gbr01.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/ap/t-59584e83/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fteams.microsoft.com%2Fl%2Fmeetup-join%2F19%253ameeting_YWI5NDM0N2UtMWQyOC00ZGYwLTk0OWQtMThhOGQ4YmU3ODI0%2540thread.v2%2F0%3Fcontext%3D%257b%2522Tid%2522%253a%252237c354b2-85b0-47f5-b222-07b48d774ee3%2522%252c%2522Oid%2522%253a%2522339b2ca8-d397-48dd-a7e3-193ac2e2c2b3%2522%257d&amp;data=05%7C02%7Cjennifer.struthers1%40nhs.net%7Cc37ce647b0734e48efd108dc78400247%7C37c354b285b047f5b22207b48d774ee3%7C0%7C0%7C638517463533546585%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=Kg05YcJ4HCy%2BahlbnxDV4LgCACU7C4bEAyM9hterY3Y%3D&amp;reserved=0" target="_blank">AnalystX Huddle – AI-Enabled Shared Care Records: Using Google Cloud to transform healthcare in Yorkshire and Humber</a></h3>
<p><strong>Tuesday 21st May, 2pm-3pm, Teams</strong></p>
<p>Humber Teaching NHS Foundation Trust, Google Cloud and Deloitte are partnering to drive digital transformation in healthcare and foster innovation in the Yorkshire region with integrated shared care records, and now leveraging Generative AI for EHR search and clinical summarization. Join us for an insightful discussion focused on how Google Cloud is revolutionizing healthcare delivery in the Yorkshire and Humber region. Learn how cutting-edge cloud technologies are improving patient care, streamlining operations, and driving innovation across the NHS.</p>
</section>
<section id="analysis-without-data" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analysis-without-data"><a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/analysis-without-data-tickets-895208000227?aff=odcleoeventsincollection" target="_blank">Analysis without Data</a></h3>
<p><strong>Tuesday 21st May, 12-1pm, Online</strong></p>
<p>This session outlines work by the Ministry of Justice (MoJ)’s Better Outcomes through Linked Data (BOLD) programme Homelessness Pilot colleagues in Department for Levelling Up, Housing and Communities (DLUHC). The Better Outcomes through Linked Data programme aims to demonstrate the benefits of linked data across government. In DLUHC’s Homelessness Pilot Team, our challenge was a lack of full data access for sensitivity reasons. To overcome this, we developed a Reproducible Analytical Pipeline (RAP) for our offending and repeat homelessness projects. For the rough sleeping and drug treatment project, we took a pragmatic approach to writing a report using only aggregated data that was suppressed.</p>
<p>We shall talk about our approaches, including constructing dummy data, modular coding using Quarto (an alternative to RMarkdown) and robust statistical methods such as trimmed means.</p>
</section>
<section id="using-data-science-and-ai-to-transform-delivery-in-the-prison-system" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="using-data-science-and-ai-to-transform-delivery-in-the-prison-system"><a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/using-data-science-and-ai-to-transform-delivery-in-the-prison-system-tickets-885509080497?aff=odcleoeventsincollection" target="_blank">Using Data Science and AI to transform delivery in the prison system</a></h3>
<p><strong>Wednesday 29th May, 2-3pm, Online</strong></p>
<p>Join colleagues from the Ministry of Justice (MoJ) who work alongside other government departments and agencies to bring the principles of justice to life for everyone in society. “We are one of the largest departments with a large proportion of staff working directly to the public and tens of thousands of prison staff making decisions every day about prisoners in their care. In the Prison Data Science team, we aim to support operational decision-making by developing and deploying innovative data science tools.</p>
<p>In this session, we will show examples of how we’ve used data science and AI to transform processes within prison services”</p>
</section>
<section id="innovation-in-analysis-with-professor-sir-ian-diamond" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="innovation-in-analysis-with-professor-sir-ian-diamond"><a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/innovation-in-analysis-with-professor-sir-ian-diamond-tickets-904642649517?aff=odcleoeventsincollection" target="_blank">Innovation in analysis with Professor Sir Ian Diamond</a></h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 30th May, 2:30-3:30pm, Online</strong></p>
<p>Join us to reflect on the innovative topics raised throughout a fantastic AiG Month and consider the importance of innovations to government analysis and where you can get support - no matter which profession or department you work in!</p>
<p>Join this session with, Professor Sir Ian Diamond - Head of the Analysis Function and National Statistician - to hear about the innovations that have caught his eye, and what he thinks are the most interesting and important innovations coming down the road.</p>
</section>
<section id="dark-data---data-ethics-and-society-reading-group" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="dark-data---data-ethics-and-society-reading-group"><a href="https://www.tickettailor.com/events/dataethics/1193123/r/nhs" target="_blank">Dark Data - Data Ethics and Society Reading Group</a></h3>
<p><strong>Tuesday 4th June, 1-2pm, Online (Teams)</strong></p>
<p>Join the Public Sector Data Ethics &amp; Society Reading Group to discuss David Hand’s book ‘Dark Data’. <a href="https://www.tickettailor.com/events/dataethics/1193123/r/nhs" target="_blank">Sign up now to reserve your spot</a> (and receive details of the 40% discount off the paperback we’ve scooped😎).</p>
</section>
<section id="london-data-week-2024" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="london-data-week-2024"><a href="https://londondataweek.org/" target="_blank">London Data Week 2024</a></h3>
<p><strong>1st-7th July 2024, Online and in person</strong></p>
<p>London Data Week is a city-wide, distributed festival of events focusing on all things data. Data is a major part of our everyday lives, and shapes many of the decisions we make – as well as the decisions that are made about us – whether we know it or not. We believe that everyone should have a seat at the table when it comes to data, and that is the guiding principle behind our core values: to be collaborative, open and inclusive. So, we invite you to be part of the conversation by joining us and our event partners at a London Data Week event.</p>
<p>Find out more about London Data Week and what events are being held <a href="https://londondataweek.org/" target="_blank">here</a></p>
</section>
<section id="nhs-rpysoc-2024-conference-21st-nov-birmingham---registration-opened" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="nhs-rpysoc-2024-conference-21st-nov-birmingham---registration-opened"><a href="https://nhsrcommunity.com/events/nhs-r-nhs-pycom-open-source-conference-nhs-rpysoc-2024-2024-ticket-for-in-person-attendance-on-thursday-21-november-2024/" target="_blank">NHS RPySOC 2024 Conference (21st Nov, Birmingham) - registration opened</a></h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 21st-22nd November, 9am-5pm, in-person (Birmingham) / Online</strong></p>
<p>The <strong>NHS RPySOC 2024 conference</strong> is open for registration now! It will be on <strong>21st &amp; 22nd November in Birmingham</strong>. This is jointed hosted by the NHS R Community and NHS.pycom, and also promotes Open Source.</p>
<ul>
<li>Day 1 will be a mixture of presentations, workshops and lightening talks</li>
<li>Day 2 <strong>(in-person only)</strong> will be ‘Unconference’ with suggestions for topics being taken on day 1.</li>
</ul>
<p>It’s a great chance to show off our work, share our learning with a like minded community and learn a few things yourself, such as the state of the industry and how techniques are being applied elsewhere.</p>
<p>You can either attend:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://nhsrcommunity.com/events/nhs-r-nhs-pycom-open-source-conference-nhs-rpysoc-2024-2024-ticket-for-in-person-attendance-on-thursday-21-november-2024/">In-Person (The ICC, Hall 11, Birmingham B1 2EA</a></li>
<li><a href="https://nhsrcommunity.com/events/nhs-r-nhs-pycom-open-source-conference-2024-rpysoc-2024-ticket-for-virtual-attendance-on-thursday-21-november-2024/">Online</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Abstract submissions haven’t been opened yet.</strong></p>
<hr>
<p>Know of any events we should feature next month? Let us know by clicking the “Contribute” button, or <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="data-science-community" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Data Science Community</h1>
</section>
<section id="ai-quality-community-of-practice" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ai-quality-community-of-practice">AI Quality Community of Practice</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_05/AI_CoP.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>A group of data scientists engaging with the AIQCoP</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The AI Quality Community of Practice was launched on Thursday 16th May, a community primarily of testing and assurance professionals focused on the assurance of healthcare AI.</p>
<p>Data Science’s Will Poulett and Ben Wallace gave presentations on research they’d been doing in the AiQCoP, (formally INSTANT) including work on an academic paper which will be presented in IEEE in Athens at the end of the month.</p>
<p>AIQCOP will be closely collaborating with data science in the future, but the best way to get involved right now is to sign up to the <a href="https://engage.cloud.microsoft/main/groups/eyJfdHlwZSI6Ikdyb3VwIiwiaWQiOiIxODQ1ODE2MDMzMjgifQ/about" target="_blank">Viva Engage group</a> and send any papers or articles their way! You can also check out the <a href="https://nhs.sharepoint.com/sites/X26_AssuranceCOE/SitePages/AI-%26-Quality-Assurance.aspx?csf=1&amp;web=1&amp;e=HTahJY&amp;xsdata=MDV8MDJ8fGViMDUyZDJlMWEwYjQxMDUwOTVlMDhkYzUyZjEwOGJmfDM3YzM1NGIyODViMDQ3ZjViMjIyMDdiNDhkNzc0ZWUzfDB8MHw2Mzg0NzY0NDIzNjcxMDEyNzh8VW5rbm93bnxWR1ZoYlhOVFpXTjFjbWwwZVZObGNuWnBZMlY4ZXlKV0lqb2lNQzR3TGpBd01EQWlMQ0pRSWpvaVYybHVNeklpTENKQlRpSTZJazkwYUdWeUlpd2lWMVFpT2pFeGZRPT18MXxMMk5vWVhSekx6RTVPalU0WXpObFkyRXlMVFk1TXpVdE5ERTFZaTA1TkRrNExXWTVZVE0wTm1Sa01UYzJZMTlrTTJNeE9EUTJOeTFoWkRZeExUUTFaVEl0T1RZNU5TMDFZVFF6TkdRMFlURXlPVEZBZFc1eExtZGliQzV6Y0dGalpYTXZiV1Z6YzJGblpYTXZNVGN4TWpBME56UXpOVFkzT1E9PXwyMWY2ZDg2M2UzNzc0ZmNmMDk1ZTA4ZGM1MmYxMDhiZnxmZmE1YTczMTNjY2I0ZWE5OTEwZjZmMjFjMjE0NjE2Nw%3D%3D&amp;sdata=QWVoVk9uOFhHUVZwdCs2SEdsY3EzakxXdEVrTzJCcnB1UTlSeFI1QXpNdz0%3D&amp;ovuser=37c354b2-85b0-47f5-b222-07b48d774ee3%2Canusha.jose%40nhs.net&amp;OR=Teams-HL&amp;CT=1712133835361&amp;clickparams=eyJBcHBOYW1lIjoiVGVhbXMtRGVza3RvcCIsIkFwcFZlcnNpb24iOiI1MC8yNDAyMTUyODYxNiIsIkhhc0ZlZGVyYXRlZFVzZXIiOmZhbHNlfQ%3D%3D&amp;SafelinksUrl=https%3A%2F%2Fnhs.sharepoint.com%2Fsites%2FX26_AssuranceCOE%2FSitePages%2FAI-&amp;-Quality-Assurance.aspx=" target="_blank">sharepoint website</a> or email them at <a href="mailto:nhsdigital.instant@nhs.net">nhsdigital.instant@nhs.net</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="rap-community-of-practice" class="level1">
<h1>RAP Community of Practice</h1>
<p>The <a href="https://nhsdigital.github.io/rap-community-of-practice/?utm_source=p_d_newsletter&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=PR_requests" target="_blank">RAP Community of Practice</a> promotes good coding practice and aims to support analytical teams by developing learning materials, however it’s not a solo effort! Many RAP Champions have worked with the team in recent years and the current RAP Squad wants to encourage everyone to contribute to the Community, whether it be by sending a <a href="https://github.com/NHSDigital/rap-community-of-practice/pulls" target="_blank">Pull Request</a>, raising an <a href="https://github.com/NHSDigital/rap-community-of-practice/issues/new" target="_blank">Issue</a>, or even <a href="mailto:england.rapchampions@nhs.net" target="_blank">emailing them!</a></p>
<p>Help make the RAP <em>Community</em> of Practice a <em>community</em> endeavour!</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="training-opportunities" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Training Opportunities</h1>
</section>
<section id="the-turing-online-learning-platform" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-turing-online-learning-platform"><a href="https://www.turing.ac.uk/courses" target="_blank">The Turing Online Learning Platform</a></h2>
<p>The Turing Online Learning Platform offers a range of <strong>free</strong> online course from AI fairness on social media to an introduction to transparent machine learning. <a href="https://www.turing.ac.uk/courses" target="_blank">Check them all out here</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="microsoft-enterprise-skills-initiative" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="microsoft-enterprise-skills-initiative"><a href="https://esi.microsoft.com/landing" target="_blank">Microsoft Enterprise Skills Initiative</a></h2>
<p>Using your nhs.net email account, you have access to a variety of Microsoft courses for free, as well as <a href="https://esi.microsoft.com/getcertification" target="_blank">certifications</a>. These range from a beginner friendly course titled <em>Deploy and consume models with Azure Machine Learning</em> to an advanced course titled <em>Write advanced Transact-SQL queries</em>.</p>
<hr>
<p>We are currently updating our resource list and reviewing the content: please let us know of any resources you think would be useful! Check out all the resources in the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Training+Brochure" target="_blank">Training Brochure</a>! Can you spot something missing? <a href="mailto:datascience@nhs.net">Contact us</a>!</p>
</section>
<section id="need-a-quick-break" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Need a Quick Break?</h1>
</section>
<p><a href="https://mywordle.strivemath.com/?word=cfrss" target="_blank">How many tries will it take you?</a></p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<p><a href="https://forms.office.com/e/JJsmgPmVVJ" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-success btn-lg">Subscribe (nhs.net login)</a><a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">Contribute</a><a href="./newsletter.pdf" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">PDF Version</a></p>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>newsletter</category>
  <guid>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_05/newsletter.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 20 May 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Professional Development Newsletter April 2024</title>
  <dc:creator>Jennifer Struthers</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Giulia Mantovani</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Harriet Sands</dc:creator>
  <link>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_04/newsletter.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/images/banner_april.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Welcome to the latest Professional Development newsletter, brought to you by the Data Science Professional Development Functional Team.</p>
<p>The newsletter team are always happy to receive constructive feedback, and we invite you to send us any contributions you may have.</p>
<p>There are some legacy NHS Digital items which we have identified with❗</p>
<p>If you cannot access something of interest to you, please <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new" target="_blank">reach out</a>.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading! – PD newsletter team</p>
<section id="highlights" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Highlights</h1>
</section>
<section id="now-accessible-to-all" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="now-accessible-to-all">Now Accessible to All!</h3>
<p>After trialing the use of the <a href="https://github.com/NHSDigital" target="_blank">NHS Digital GitHub</a> to aid in the creation of the newsletter, it has now been officially moved to the publically accessible <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland" target="_blank">NHS England GitHub</a>.</p>
<p>We strongly encourage contributions to the newsletter from all our colleagues, which can be submitted through <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" target="_blank">clicking here</a> or any of the “Contribute” buttons around the site.</p>
</section>
<section id="mentoring-scheme-expression-of-interest" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="mentoring-scheme-expression-of-interest">Mentoring Scheme Expression of Interest</h3>
<p>The Professional Development Function Team are investigating the interest in starting up a Mentorship Scheme between senior and junior NHS Data Science colleagues.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.southampton.ac.uk/professional-development/mentoring/benefits-of-a-mentoring-relationship.page" target="_blank">Mentorship benefits both parties</a>: mentees are provided with guidance from someone who has once been in their shoes and mentors gain insights from a new perspective, and gain experience in staff management and development. If you are interested in becoming a mentor <strong>and/or</strong> mentee, please fill out the <a href="https://forms.office.com/pages/responsepage.aspx?id=slTDN7CF9UeyIge0jXdO45Vp0C6IOYJOjBrGZlr3xANUMkRSNTg1UElOVUJXRzJaS1VGQklPMUY1Ti4u" target="_blank">expression of interest form</a>.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="events" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Events</h1>
</section>
<p>Lots of exciting things coming up! See the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/calendars" target="_blank">full calendar here</a>❗, and a small selection below.</p>
<section id="hdr-uk-advanced-computer-science-summit-ai-and-healthcare" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="hdr-uk-advanced-computer-science-summit-ai-and-healthcare"><a href="https://www.hdruk.ac.uk/events/hdr-uk-advanced-computer-science-summit-ai-and-healthcare/" target="_blank">HDR UK Advanced Computer Science Summit: AI and Healthcare</a></h3>
<p><strong>24 April 2024, 10:00AM - 3:30PM, Online</strong></p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.hdruk.ac.uk/events/hdr-uk-advanced-computer-science-summit-ai-and-healthcare/" target="_blank">HDR UK Advanced Computer Science Summit: AI and Healthcare</a> aims to anticipate advances in technologies that are on the horizon and discuss the impact these may have on health data research.</p>
<p>Cool speakers include but are not limited to:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/elham-kashefi-76b9286/">Elham Kashefi</a> (Chief Scientist for the <a href="https://www.nqcc.ac.uk/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Press-release-Announcement-of-the-appointment-of-the-Chief-Scientist-for-the-NQCC.pdf">UK’s National Quantum Computing Centre</a> will discuss quantum computation)</li>
<li><a href="https://profiles.ucl.ac.uk/78197-honghan-wu">Honghan Wu</a> (Associate Professor at the Institute of Health Informatics at UCL will lead on NLP and using text technologies and Knowledge Graph techniques to analyze health data)</li>
<li><a href="https://www.ed.ac.uk/profile/dr-william-whiteley">William Whiteley</a> (Professor of Neurology and Epidemiology at the University of Edinburgh will discuss replicating RCTs by use of data at large scale)</li>
<li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/mobuolafoluwa-onayade/">Mobuolafoluwa Onayade</a> (Health Data Scientist and Analyst at Swansea University will be presenting on The use of Causal Machine Learning (CausalML) as an upgrade to Traditional Machine Learning)</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="the-turing-roche-knowledge-share-series-fairness-in-ai-for-health" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-turing-roche-knowledge-share-series-fairness-in-ai-for-health"><a href="https://www.turing.ac.uk/events/turing-roche-knowledge-share-series-fairness-ai-health">The Turing-Roche Knowledge Share Series: Fairness in AI for Health</a></h3>
<p><strong>Tuesday 30th April, 3-4pm, Online</strong></p>
<p>Join the Turing-Roche Partnership’s virtual event series for partnership updates, knowledge sharing and new perspectives. This event will explore the theme of fairness in AI, with relation to health, and hear from Leandra Bräuninger, a PhD student at University College London and Adarsh Srivastava, Head of Data and Analytics Quality Assurance at Roche.</p>
</section>
<section id="digital-footprints-2024" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="digital-footprints-2024"><a href="https://digifootprints.co.uk/digital-footprints-2024/" target="_blank">Digital Footprints 2024</a></h3>
<p><strong>Wednesday 8th May 1pm – Thursday 9th May 4pm, University of Bristol</strong></p>
<p>Focusing on digital footprints data for social impact, inviting innovative research that harnesses the potential of these novel datasets to address pressing societal challenges and drive positive change. The conference is organised by Turing Novel Data Linkage for Health and Wellbeing Interest Group.</p>
<p><em>Please note attendance of the conference is subject to a £50 fee.</em></p>
</section>
<section id="data-science-festival-mayday-2024" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-science-festival-mayday-2024"><a href="https://datasciencefestival.com/event/mayday-2024/" target="_blank">Data Science Festival MayDay 2024</a></h3>
<p><strong>Saturday 18th May, 9-6pm, CodeNode, London</strong></p>
<p>Enter the ballot for a chance to grab a <em>free</em> ticket to this years’ Data Science Festival, hosted in London. Many speakers and sessions to be announced, but already lined up are talks on Gender Bias in Machine Learning and Leveraging GANs for Building Synthetic Data.</p>
</section>
<section id="dark-data---data-ethics-and-society-reading-group" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="dark-data---data-ethics-and-society-reading-group"><a href="https://www.tickettailor.com/events/dataethics/1193123/r/nhs" target="_blank">Dark Data - Data Ethics and Society Reading Group</a></h3>
<p><strong>Tuesday 4th June, 1-2pm, Online (Teams)</strong></p>
<p>Join the Public Sector Data Ethics &amp; Society Reading Group to discuss David Hand’s book ‘Dark Data’. <a href="https://www.tickettailor.com/events/dataethics/1193123/r/nhs" target="_blank">Sign up now to reserve your spot</a> (and receive details of the 40% discount off the paperback we’ve scooped😎).</p>
<hr>
<p>See more future events on our <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Data+Science+Events" target="_blank">confluence calendar</a>❗</p>
<p>Know of any events we should feature next month? Let us know by clicking the “Contribute” button, or <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="knowledge-sharing" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Knowledge Sharing</h1>
</section>
<section id="data-science-discussions" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-science-discussions">Data Science Discussions</h3>
<center>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_04/DS_Discussion.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Data Scientists discussing a fun topic over coffee, building relationships and expanding their knowledge base</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</center>
<p>On Thursday 11th April we had our first Data Science discussion, hosted by Will Poulett. Data Science Discussions are a new event, focussed on peer to peer discussions on a broad range of Data Science topics. For this discussion Will asked everyone attending to research a future application of AI that interested them, and also consider how it could be later applied to healthcare. The discussion began with Will presenting his case: <a href="https://www.projectceti.org/" target="_blank">Project CETI</a>, who are applying advanced machine learning and state-of-the-art robotics to listen to and translate the communication of sperm whales. Check out his slide deck <a href="https://nhs.sharepoint.com/:f:/r/sites/msteams_2768a1/Shared%20Documents/FT%20-%20Professional%20Development/PD%20Events/Data%20Science%20Discussions?csf=1&amp;web=1&amp;e=Tbm3Gq" target="_blank">here</a>. We then broke up into smaller groups to further discuss his case and our own.</p>
<p>The Professional Development Functional Team hope to hold Data Science Discussions monthly. If you have an area of Data Science you’re interested in sharing, and encouraging others to look into too, please <a href="mailto:datascience@nhs.net">contact us</a> to host a session! Most of the session is held in break out rooms, and so all you need to do is spark discussion.</p>
</section>
<section id="rap-drop-in-sessions-now-on-tuesdays" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="rap-drop-in-sessions-now-on-tuesdays">RAP Drop In Sessions (Now on Tuesdays)</h3>
<p>The RAP Squad hold a <a href="https://teams.microsoft.com/l/meetup-join/19:meeting_NGE5Mjc5ZGQtYjJkZi00OGQ4LWJmYmMtOGIxYzI3NWQ3NWZi@thread.v2/0?context=%7B%22Tid%22:%2237c354b2-85b0-47f5-b222-07b48d774ee3%22,%22Oid%22:%226a6e419b-5da0-48cb-854e-e7cca39c57e2%22%7D" target="_blank">weekly drop in session on Teams</a>,<strong>Tuesdays 10-11am</strong>, for anything and all things RAP (Reproducibile Analytical Pipelines). Come along to ask questions, get tips, or share instances of best practice in your team!</p>
<p>Check out the <a href="https://nhsdigital.github.io/rap-community-of-practice/?utm_source=p_d_newsletter&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=homepage">RAP Community of Practice website</a> to learn more, including <a href="https://nhsdigital.github.io/rap-community-of-practice/introduction_to_RAP/gov-policy-on-rap/?utm_source=p_d_newsletter&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=gov_policy">information on what the government has been saying about RAP</a> (spoiler: it’s fast becoming the required way of working with data).</p>
<hr>
<p>Stay tuned for an update on what seminars &amp; show and tells will look like in the new team. Please bear with us as it is likely to be a learning process! Contact <a href="mailto:amelia.noonan1@nhs.net">Mia Noonan</a> for more information.</p>
</section>
<section id="training-opportunities" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Training Opportunities</h1>
</section>
<section id="the-turing-way-book-dash" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-turing-way-book-dash">The Turing Way Book Dash</h3>
<p><a href="https://the-turing-way.netlify.app/community-handbook/bookdash/bookdash-events.html"><strong>The Turing Way Book Dash</strong></a> is a collaborative event where you’ll work with others to add to and improve <strong>The Turing Way book</strong> and become a part of its community.</p>
<p>The online contribution sessions (collaborative co-working format) and the social networking session will take place from <strong>3 to 6 June 2024</strong>, and two community share-out events on <strong>7 June 2024</strong>. <a href="https://the-turing-way.netlify.app/community-handbook/bookdash/bookdash-events">See details</a>. There may also be an opportunity to join an in-person hub in your area - please indicate your interest in the application.</p>
<p><strong>Application</strong> <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1FdrlFh_4yw7XsqoG-yQt8zbEH9J8wHVhKl3ZfNz_NBk/edit">Please see the application form here</a>. Submission deadline is <strong>Friday 26th April 2024</strong> and the application form may take around 30 minutes to complete.</p>
<p><strong>Who should apply?</strong> Everyone that has expertise that The Turing Way project can benefit from. The skills and contributions that they’re looking for include, but are not limited to:</p>
<ul>
<li>Tools, methods, and case studies from reproducibility in Data Science 🛠️</li>
<li>Science communication skills: skills in writing, editing, and/or exciting interactive communications 📝</li>
<li>Project design and management skills 📊</li>
<li>Approaches and principles for collaboration in data science 🤝</li>
<li>Collaboratively writing new chapters 📝</li>
<li>Reviewing others’ contributions or editing the current chapters 📋</li>
<li>Updating how the book looks online (e.g., website design, CSS, logos, layout) 🖥️</li>
<li>Documenting other contributions as illustrations or stories 📸</li>
</ul>
<p>Participants will be expected to attend at least one co-working session (2.5 hours each) per day virtually.</p>
<hr>
<p>Check out all the resources in the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Training+Brochure" target="_blank">Training Brochure</a> ❗ Can you spot something missing? <a href="mailto:datascience@nhs.net">Contact us</a>!</p>
</section>
<section id="need-a-quick-break" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Need a Quick Break?</h1>
</section>
<p><a href="https://mywordle.strivemath.com/?word=mivuj">How many tries will it take you?</a></p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<p><a href="https://forms.office.com/e/JJsmgPmVVJ" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-success btn-lg">Subscribe (nhs.net login)</a><a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">Contribute</a><a href="./newsletter.pdf" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">PDF Version</a></p>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>newsletter</category>
  <guid>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_04/newsletter.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Professional Development Newsletter March 2024</title>
  <dc:creator>Jennifer Struthers, Giulia Mantovani</dc:creator>
  <link>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_03/newsletter.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/images/banner_march.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Welcome to the latest Professional Development newsletter, brought to you by the Data Science skilled team Professional Development Functional Group.</p>
<p>The newsletter team are always happy to receive constructive feedback, and we invite you to send us any contributions you may have.</p>
<p>There are some legacy NHS Digital items which we have identified with❗</p>
<p>If you cannot access something of interest to you, please <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new" target="_blank">reach out</a>.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading! – PD newsletter team</p>
<section id="highlights" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Highlights</h1>
</section>
<section id="leadership-competency-framework" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="leadership-competency-framework">Leadership Competency Framework</h3>
<p>NHS England has <a href="https://www.england.nhs.uk/leaders/" target="_blank">published the leadership competency framework</a> which comprises a set of leadership competencies incorporating the skills, values and behaviours required in NHS board roles and establishes what good looks like in leadership terms, providing a new and consistent national standard of leadership. Many of us are very far from those positions, but it does not hurt to aim high. But also, it is good to know what is expected of our leaders. These are the six leadership competency domains that you can learn about reading the framework:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Driving high-quality and sustainable outcomes</li>
<li>Setting strategy and delivering long-term transformation</li>
<li>Promoting equality and inclusion, and reducing health and workforce inequalities</li>
<li>Providing robust governance and assurance</li>
<li>Creating a compassionate, just and positive culture</li>
<li>Building a trusted relationship with partners and communities</li>
</ol>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="events" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Events</h1>
</section>
<p>Lots of exciting things coming up! See the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/calendars" target="_blank">full calendar here</a>❗, and a small selection below.</p>
<section id="ai-uk-fringe-events" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ai-uk-fringe-events"><a href="https://ai-uk.turing.ac.uk/fringe-events/" target="_blank">AI UK Fringe Events</a></h3>
<p><strong>4th-29th March, various times, In person across the UK and online</strong></p>
<p>At a series of events AI UK Fringe brings together leaders in academia from across the UK’s AI ecosystem to demonstrate, exhibit and update on their ground-breaking work. Attendees at our AI UK Fringe events will be able to network with local colleagues and peers and take part in specialist debates and roundtables relevant to their regions. Browse this year’s events below and make sure to register your place.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-person-centred-healthcare-record---pipe-dream-or-inevitability" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-person-centred-healthcare-record---pipe-dream-or-inevitability"><a href="https://www.tickettailor.com/events/publicdigital/1167958?mc_cid=c757cfd211&amp;mc_eid=f15dd17114" target="_blank">The person-centred healthcare record - pipe dream or inevitability?</a></h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 18th April, 6-7:30pm, in person in London or on Zoom</strong></p>
<p>Successive administrations have tried and failed to implement a person-centred healthcare record, but can it be done? Join us to hear four digital healthcare experts debate the question of how interoperable access to patient data could or should be delivered, looking at political, commercial, and technical considerations.</p>
</section>
<section id="lunch-and-learn" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="lunch-and-learn">Lunch and Learn</h3>
<p><strong>Monday 22nd April, 12-1pm, Wellington Place: Town Hall Collaboration Space</strong></p>
<p>Andy Jackson has recently released news of new lunch and learn seminars held in person in Leeds. The next one will feature a guest speaker from ONS - Population Demographics. Watch your email for more information.</p>
</section>
<section id="digital-footprints-2024" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="digital-footprints-2024"><a href="https://digifootprints.co.uk/digital-footprints-2024/" target="_blank">Digital Footprints 2024</a></h3>
<p><strong>Wednesday 8th May 1pm – Thursday 9th May 4pm, University of Bristol</strong></p>
<p>Focusing on digital footprints data for social impact, inviting innovative research that harnesses the potential of these novel datasets to address pressing societal challenges and drive positive change. The conference is organised by Turing Novel Data Linkage for Health and Wellbeing Interest Group.</p>
<p><em>Please note attendance of the conference is subject to a £50 fee.</em></p>
</section>
<section id="data-science-festival-mayday-2024" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-science-festival-mayday-2024"><a href="https://datasciencefestival.com/event/mayday-2024/" target="_blank">Data Science Festival MayDay 2024</a></h3>
<p><strong>Saturday 18th May, 9-6pm, CodeNode, London</strong></p>
<p>Enter the ballot for achance to grab a <em>free</em> ticket to this years’ Data Science Festival, hosted in London. Many speakers and sessions to be announced, but already lined up are talks on Gender Bias in Machine Learning and Leveraging GANs for Building Synthetic Data.</p>
</section>
<section id="dark-data---data-ethics-and-society-reading-group" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="dark-data---data-ethics-and-society-reading-group"><a href="https://www.tickettailor.com/events/dataethics/1193123/r/nhs" target="_blank">Dark Data - Data Ethics and Society Reading Group</a></h3>
<p><strong>Tuesday 4th June, 1-2pm, Online (Teams)</strong></p>
<p>Join the Public Sector Data Ethics &amp; Society Reading Group to discuss David Hand’s book ‘Dark Data’. <a href="https://www.tickettailor.com/events/dataethics/1193123/r/nhs" target="_blank">Sign up now to reserve your spot</a> (and receive details of the 40% discount off the paperback we’ve scooped😎).</p>
<hr>
<p>See more future events on our <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Data+Science+Events" target="_blank">confluence calendar</a>❗</p>
<p>Know of any events we should feature next month? Let us know by clicking the “Contribute” button, or <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="knowledge-sharing" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Knowledge Sharing</h1>
</section>
<section id="generative-ai-in-a-research-context" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="generative-ai-in-a-research-context">Generative AI in a research context</h3>
<p>Generative AI is increasingly used to draft, edit, annotate and debug code. It’s not just industry software developers who are taking advantage of the tools it has to offer. Those who develop and use software for academic research are benefitting from them too. So how do you make the best use of generative AI for coding in a research context? As software engineers with The Alan Turing Institute’s <a href="https://www.turing.ac.uk/work-turing/research/research-engineering-group" target="_blank">Research Engineering Group</a> (REG) and <a href="https://www.turing.ac.uk/work-turing/studentships/enrichment" target="_blank">PhD Enrichment scheme</a>, we’ve been asking ourselves just this question. <a href="https://www.turing.ac.uk/blog/using-generative-ai-write-code-guide-researchers" target="_blank">Here</a>, we share our thoughts, along with some tips for researchers.</p>
</section>
<section id="github-vs-gitlab-terminology-differences" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="github-vs-gitlab-terminology-differences"><a href="https://nhsdigital.github.io/rap-community-of-practice/training_resources/git/github_gitlab_terminology/?utm_source=p_d_newsletter&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=github_gitlab" target="_blank">GitHub vs Gitlab Terminology Differences</a></h3>
<p>GitHub and GitLab are two very similar yet different platforms and that can lead to some confusion between teams who are familiar with one but not the other when some key pieces of terminology have been changed slightly between them. The RAP Community of Pracice have recently released a quick summary of some of these terminology differences. Read over this and you’ll never get your MRs and PRs mixed up again!</p>
<hr>
<p>Stay tuned for an update on what seminars &amp; show and tells will look like in the new team. Please bear with us as it is likely to be a learning process! Contact <a href="mailto:amelia.noonan1@nhs.net">Mia Noonan</a> for more information..</p>
</section>
<section id="training-opportunities" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Training Opportunities</h1>
</section>
<section id="pluralsight-access" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pluralsight-access"><a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Pluralsight+Access" target="_blank">Pluralsight Access</a></h3>
<p>After the reinstation of the Pluralsight license, a confluence page on how to access it (whether or not you had access before) has been set up. Check it out to gain access to all of the Pluralsight training resources again.</p>
<hr>
<p>Check out all the resources in the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Training+Brochure" target="_blank">Training Brochure</a>! Can you spot something missing? <a href="mailto:datascience@nhs.net">Contact us</a>!</p>
</section>
<section id="need-a-quick-break" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Need a Quick Break?</h1>
</section>
<p><a href="https://mywordle.strivemath.com/?word=icuhw" target="_blank">How many tries will it take you?</a></p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<p><a href="https://forms.office.com/e/JJsmgPmVVJ" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-success btn-lg">Subscribe (nhs.net login)</a><a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">Contribute</a><a href="./newsletter.pdf" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">PDF Version</a></p>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>newsletter</category>
  <category>leadership</category>
  <guid>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_03/newsletter.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Professional Development Newsletter February 2024</title>
  <dc:creator>Harriet Sands and Jennifer Struthers</dc:creator>
  <link>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_02/newsletter.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/images/banner_feb.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Welcome to the latest Professional Development newsletter, brought to you by the Data Science skilled team Professional Development Capability team <strong>- now in a new format!</strong></p>
<p>The newsletter team are always happy to receive constructive feedback, and we invite you to send us any contributions you may have.</p>
<p>There are some legacy NHS Digital items which we have identified with❗</p>
<p>If you cannot access something of interest to you, please <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new" target="_blank">reach out</a>.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading! – PD newsletter team</p>
<section id="highlights" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Highlights</h1>
</section>
<section id="your-professional-development---job-descriptions" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="your-professional-development---job-descriptions"><u><strong>Your Professional Development</strong> - Job Descriptions </u></h4>
<p>When preparing for future career opportunities here at NHSE, it’s a good idea to understand the job descriptions for each role you hope to apply for.</p>
<p>Take a look at the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Data+Science+Job+Descriptions" target="_blank">current data science job descriptions saved on Confluence</a> which detail the requirements and expectations for the various roles we may look to recruit for in the team. These will be used for recruitment in the immediate future.</p>
<p>Familiarising yourself with these specifications can help you shape your professional development plans and tailor the training opportunities you seek out.</p>
<p>Please note that in the longer term these job descriptions may change to be aligned to the <a href="https://future.nhs.uk/DataAnalytics/view?objectID=31311216">National Competency Framework</a> and this will be communicated to the team.</p>
</section>
<section id="health-and-care-analytics-conference-2024---call-for-abstracts" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="health-and-care-analytics-conference-2024---call-for-abstracts"><u><strong>Health and Care Analytics Conference 2024</strong> - Call for Abstracts</u></h4>
<p>Have some interesting work to share? The <a href="https://haca-conference.nhs.uk/" target="_blank">HACA Conference 2024</a> is officially accepting applications to present (in the form of a talk or poster) at the 2024 conference, hosted 23rd-24th July at Telford International Centre. The deadline to submit is <strong>Thursday February 29th 2024</strong>. Check out the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/HACA+2024" target="_blank">HACA 2024 Confluence page</a>❗ to see the steps and track submissions.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="events" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Events</h1>
</section>
<p>Lots of exciting things coming up! See the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/calendars" target="_blank">full calendar here</a>❗</p>
<section id="severe-mental-illness-physical-disease" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="severe-mental-illness-physical-disease"><a href="https://www.hdruk.ac.uk/events/severe-mental-illness-and-physical-disease/" target="_blank">Severe Mental Illness &amp; Physical Disease</a></h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 29th February 10:00 - 13:00, Online</strong></p>
<p>Hosted by researchers at the Usher Institute, The University of Edinburgh, with contributions from DataMind, the Health Data Research Hub for Mental Health we will hear from researchers working on projects relating to severe mental illness and receipt of cardiovascular care as well as people with lived experience, clinicians and public health and government representatives.</p>
</section>
<section id="making-a-difference-using-data-to-improve-care" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="making-a-difference-using-data-to-improve-care"><a href="event link" target="_blank">Making a difference: Using Data to Improve Care</a></h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 29th February 2024 13:00 - 16:00, Online</strong></p>
<p>Join us for the HDR UK Midlands &amp; Health Innovation East Midlands Insight Sharing Webinar. Highlights include: Dementia and the correlation with cardiovascular diseases, Leveraging administrative healthcare data to enhance drug approval in rare disease, EU data infrastructure for Rare Disease.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-career-live" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-career-live"><a href="https://nhsengland.sharepoint.com/sites/thehub/SitePages/Help-us-inspire-students-to-join-the-NHS.aspx" target="_blank">What Career? Live</a></h3>
<p><strong>Friday 1st and Saturday 2nd March, NEC Birmingham</strong></p>
<p>NHS Health Careers is looking for people to help inspire students to join the NHS by attending this national careers event. If you’re interested, <a href="mailto:laura.monks2@nhs.net">email Laura Monks</a> by <strong>Monday 26th February</strong> .</p>
</section>
<section id="policy-making-for-the-age-of-ai" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="policy-making-for-the-age-of-ai"><a href="https://thestrandgroup.kcl.ac.uk/event/policy-making-for-the-age-of-ai/" target="_blank">Policy Making for the Age of AI</a></h3>
<p><strong>Wednesday 6th March, 18:30, King’s College London</strong></p>
<p>The sixty-eigth Strand Group will take place at 18.30 on Wednesday 6th March 2024 when Sarah Munby, Permanent Secretary of the Department for Science, Innovation and Technology, will give her second lecture as Visiting Professor on ‘Policy Making in the Age of AI.’</p>
</section>
<section id="the-politics-and-philosophy-of-ai" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-politics-and-philosophy-of-ai"><a href="https://www.lse.ac.uk/Events/2024/03/202403191830/ai" target="_blank">The politics and philosophy of AI</a></h3>
<p><strong>Tuesday 19th March 2024 18:30 to 20:00, London School of Economics &amp; Online</strong></p>
<p>As artificial intelligence (AI) moves beyond the realm of science fiction, it is already having a profound impact on our economies, societies and politics. To make sense of the transformative power and disruptive potential of AI, we are joined by thinkers at the cutting edge of the technological frontier for an in-depth discussion of its multifaceted impact. Speakers include the ‘godfather of AI’, Geoffrey Hinton; Kate Vredenburgh, Assistant Professor in the Department of Philosophy, Logic and Scientific Method at LSE and Robin Archer, the Director of the postgraduate programme in political sociology and the Director of the Ralph Miliband Programme at LSE.</p>
</section>
<section id="digital-footprints-2024" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="digital-footprints-2024"><a href="https://digifootprints.co.uk/digital-footprints-2024/" target="_blank">Digital Footprints 2024</a></h3>
<p><strong>Wednesday 8th May 1pm – Thursday 9th May 4pm, University of Bristol</strong></p>
<p>Focusing on digital footprints data for social impact, inviting innovative research that harnesses the potential of these novel datasets to address pressing societal challenges and drive positive change. The conference is organised by Turing Novel Data Linkage for Health and Wellbeing Interest Group.</p>
<p><em>Please note attendance of the conference is subject to a £50 fee.</em></p>
<hr>
<p>See more future events on our <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Events+calendar" target="_blank">confluence calendar</a>❗</p>
<p>Know of any events we should feature next month? Let us know by clicking the “Contribute” button, or <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="knowledge-sharing" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Knowledge Sharing</h1>
</section>
<section id="refactoring-golden-rules" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="refactoring-golden-rules"><a href="https://nhsdigital.github.io/rap-community-of-practice/training_resources/refactoring-guide/?utm_source=p_d_newsletter&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=refactoring_guide" target="_blank">Refactoring Golden Rules</a></h3>
<p>Are you wondering how you can make your code faster, easier to read, and easier to reuse? Getting your code to work is just the first step! After that, you should refactor your code to make it higher quality - more efficient, more robust, more maintainable. But how do you do that? Well, you can start by reading the <a href="https://nhsdigital.github.io/rap-community-of-practice/training_resources/refactoring-guide/?utm_source=p_d_newsletter&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=refactoring_guide">refactoring golden rules</a> on the RAP Community of Practice website!</p>
<hr>
<p>Stay tuned for an update on what seminars &amp; show and tells will look like in the new team. Please bear with us as it is likely to be a learning process! Contact <a href="mailto:amelia.noonan1@nhs.net">Mia Noonan</a> for more information..</p>
</section>
<section id="training-opportunities" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Training Opportunities</h1>
</section>
<section id="applications-for-the-nihr-health-service-modelling-associates-now-open" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="applications-for-the-nihr-health-service-modelling-associates-now-open"><a href="https://sites.google.com/nihr.ac.uk/hsma" target="_blank">Applications for the NIHR Health Service Modelling Associates now open</a></h3>
<p>This free, 15-month course teaches people how to use Operational Research and Data Science techniques to improve services and aid decision making.</p>
<p>The free course requires a time commitment of one day a week for the full programme. All code in the course is in Python, though some other open-source software will be used too - but no prior experience with Python (or any programming experience at all!) is required.</p>
<p>See the <a href="https://sites.google.com/nihr.ac.uk/hsma/apply-to-become-a-hsma?authuser=0" target="_blank">FAQs</a> and direct any further questions to <a href="mailto:penchord@exeter.ac.uk">penchord@exeter.ac.uk</a> and <a href="mailto:s.j.rosser@exeter.ac.uk">s.j.rosser@exeter.ac.uk</a>.</p>
<p>Applications for the course close on the <strong>4th of March 2024</strong>, with the course beginning <strong>Monday 15th April 2024</strong>.</p>
</section>
<section id="become-a-stem-ambassador" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="become-a-stem-ambassador"><a href="https://www.stem.org.uk/stem-ambassadors/become-a-stem-ambassador" target="_blank">Become a STEM ambassador</a></h3>
<p>STEM Ambassadors help young people to understand the real world applications of their learning. Attend an <a href="https://www.eventbrite.com/e/volunteer-information-session-becoming-a-stem-ambassador-tickets-771603405557?aff=odcleoeventsincollection&amp;keep_tld=1" target="_blank">information session</a> on Thursday 22nd February to learn more.</p>
</section>
<section id="stakeholder-mapping-resources" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="stakeholder-mapping-resources"><a href="https://analysisfunction.civilservice.gov.uk/policy-store/stakeholder-mapping/" target="_blank">Stakeholder Mapping Resources</a></h3>
<p>This guidance includes a helpful template and further resources to help you map stakeholders for user engagement.</p>
</section>
<section id="pluralsight" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pluralsight"><a href="https://www.pluralsight.com/" target="_blank">Pluralsight</a></h3>
<p>Tim Roebuck <a href="https://web.yammer.com/main/org/hscic.gov.uk/threads/eyJfdHlwZSI6IlRocmVhZCIsImlkIjoiMjY2Njk0NDQ1MDQ0NTMxMiJ9?trk_copy_link=V2" target="_blank">announced</a> that following delays to resolve contractual issues for a new contract, access has been restored for existing Pluralsight users, and you should been able to continue any previous training.</p>
</section>
<section id="improve-your-markdown-by-contributing-to-the-data-science-website" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="improve-your-markdown-by-contributing-to-the-data-science-website"><a href="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience/" target="_blank">Improve your Markdown by contributing to the Data Science website!</a></h3>
<p>Ever wanted to try your hand at learning Markdown but never really found a reason? Check out this <a href="https://www.markdowntutorial.com/" target="_blank">Markdown tutorial</a> and then try your hand at it by helping improve the newly launched <a href="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience/" target="_blank">Data Science website</a>.</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_02/amaia_website_newsletter.png" alt="A photoshopped image of Amaia onto a WW2 propaganda poster, saying 'We Need You'" width="350"></td>
<td>We launched the prototype <a href="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience/" target="_blank">Data Science website</a> - but we need your help. <br>We need your contributions (see how to do this <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience/blob/main/CONTRIBUTE.md" target="_blank">here</a>), in particular:<br><br>- Send us a summary of your project (see <a href="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience/our_work/ds218_rap_community_of_practice/" target="_blank">this example</a>)<br>- Follow <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience/blob/main/docs/our_work/template-project.md" target="_blank">this template</a>.<br>- Contribute an article to the blog.<br>- Volunteer to pick up an <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience/issues" target="_blank">issue</a> on GitHub.<br>- Give us feedback about the <a href="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience/" target="_blank">website</a>.<br><br>With the conference season approaching, something up on the web can be useful to point people towards!<br></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Check out all the resources in the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Training+Brochure" target="_blank">Training Brochure</a>! Can you spot something missing? <a href="mailto:datascience@nhs.net">Contact us</a>!</p>
</section>
<section id="need-a-quick-break" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Need a Quick Break?</h1>
</section>
<p><a href="https://mywordle.strivemath.com/?word=zokddgesefp" target="_blank">How many tries will it take you?</a></p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<p><a href="https://forms.office.com/e/JJsmgPmVVJ" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-success btn-lg">Subscribe (nhs.net login)</a><a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">Contribute</a><a href="./newsletter.pdf" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">PDF Version</a></p>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>newsletter</category>
  <category>analytics</category>
  <guid>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_02/newsletter.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Professional Development Newsletter January 2024</title>
  <dc:creator>Harriet Sands and Harry Kelleher</dc:creator>
  <link>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_01/newsletter.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/images/banner_jan.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Welcome to the latest Professional Development newsletter, brought to you by the Data Science skilled team Professional Development Capability team.</p>
<p>The newsletter team are always happy to receive constructive feedback, and we invite you to send us any contributions you may have.</p>
<p>There are some items that are available via legacy systems available to former NHS Digital colleagues. We have marked these with❗</p>
<p>If you cannot access something of interest to you, please <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new" target="_blank">reach out</a>.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading! – PD newsletter team</p>
<section id="highlights" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Highlights</h1>
</section>
<section id="competency-framework-zooming-intodelivery" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="competency-framework-zooming-intodelivery"><u><strong>Competency Framework</strong> – zooming into…Delivery</u></h4>
<p>As we adjust to delivering in the new team structure; using potentially unfamiliar tools like Confluence, JIRA and DevOps, getting to grips with new projects and new stakeholders, it’s the perfect time to refresh our understanding of what makes good delivery.</p>
<p>Delivery is the translation of the insights we produce into actionable outcomes. Keeping a delivery-focussed mindset is key to achieve value for money and improve lives for service users. Without it, we cannot fulfil our mission to drive the digital transformation of the NHS!</p>
<p>Delivery comes in different shapes and sizes, whether it’s being accountable for your own tickets or ensuring your team is focused on the top priorities – each of us play our part.</p>
<p>Check out these top tips from our <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Data+Science+Competency+Framework" target="_blank">Competency Framework</a>❗ :</p>
<ul>
<li>Break down complex objectives into clear tasks to deliver incremental value with each iteration</li>
<li>Regularly sync-up with stakeholders to understand priorities and manage delivery expectations</li>
<li>Be a role model to others by demonstrating a focus on delivery, whilst being open to new ideas and continuous improvement</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>Check out the resources to boost your delivery skills on the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Training+Framework" target="_blank">Training Framework</a>❗and our full collection on the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Training+Brochure" target="_blank">Training Brochure</a>❗ Can you spot something missing? <a href="mailto:datascience@nhs.net">Contact us</a>!</p>
</section>
<section id="events" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Events</h1>
</section>
<p>Lots of exciting things coming up! See the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/calendars" target="_blank">full calendar here</a>❗ , and a small selection below.</p>
<section id="onshdr-health-data-science-seminars" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="onshdr-health-data-science-seminars"><a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/health-data-science-seminar-series-tickets-758986237267" target="_blank">ONS/HDR Health Data Science Seminars</a></h3>
<p><strong>Thursday 25th January, 14:00-15:30, Online</strong></p>
<p>This event, ‘Digital footprints’, will feature presentations from guest speakers: Dr Anya Skatova, Senior Research Fellow at the University of Bristol, Professor Will Dixon, Professor of Digital Epidemiology, The University of Manchester and Professor Tim Chico, Professor of Cardiovascular Medicine, from the University of Sheffield.</p>
</section>
<section id="genomics-england-research-seminars" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="genomics-england-research-seminars"><a href="https://www.genomicsengland.co.uk/events/research-seminar-january-2024" target="_blank">Genomics England Research Seminars</a></h3>
<p><strong>Tuesday 30th January, 14:00-15:00, Online</strong></p>
<p>This seminar series showcases the latest research using data from the National Genomic Research Library. Two projects will be presented: ‘Investigating microRNA-associated variation in the Epileptic Encephalopathies’ and ‘Effects of Ancestry in the 100,000 Genomes Project Cancer Pipelines’. (January is clearly Genomics month, with the <a href="https://festivalofgenomics.com/london/en/page/home" target="_blank">Festival of Genomics &amp; Biodata</a> starting tomorrow!)</p>
</section>
<section id="data-bites-48-getting-things-done-with-data-in-government---smart-data-special" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-bites-48-getting-things-done-with-data-in-government---smart-data-special"><a href="https://www.instituteforgovernment.org.uk/event/data-bites-48-getting-things-done-data-government" target="_blank">Data Bites #48: Getting things done with data in government - smart data special</a></h3>
<p><strong>Monday 26th February, 18:00-19:20, Online &amp; London</strong></p>
<p>In an exciting, quickfire format, each speaker has eight minutes to present on data in government. Next month’s speakers include Ben Goldacre among others.</p>
<hr>
<p>See more future events on our <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/calendars" target="_blank">confluence calendar</a>❗</p>
<p>Know of any events we should feature next month?Let us know by clicking the “Contribute” button, or <a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="knowledge-sharing" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Knowledge Sharing</h1>
</section>
<p><strong><a href="https://future.nhs.uk/connect.ti/DataAnalytics/messageShowThread?threadid=12369486" target="_blank">Blog: Delivering user centred dashboards</a></strong></p>
<p><strong>Harry Kelleher</strong>, Lead BI Developer, shares his experience building dashboards that make a difference, and how a product thinking approach has been the key to unlocking system-wide value.</p>
<hr>
<p>Stay tuned for an update on what seminars &amp; show and tells will look like in the new team. Please bear with us as it is likely to be a learning process! Contact <a href="mailto:amelia.noonan1@nhs.net">Mia Noonan</a> for more information..</p>
<section id="training-opportunities" class="level1 section-heading">
<h1>Training Opportunities</h1>
</section>
<p>How much do you actually know about the NHS? Check out the <a href="https://www.kingsfund.org.uk/health-care-explained/online-course" target="_blank">The NHS explained free online course: how the health system in England really works</a>.</p>
<p>With the release of the <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/generative-ai-framework-for-hmg/generative-ai-framework-for-hmg-html" target="_blank">Generative AI Framework for HMG</a>, Civil Service Learning now includes a set of open learning relating to Generative AI, including a <a href="https://learn.civilservice.gov.uk/courses/E0nDu3fET6q3Tg5yOBFn_g" target="_blank">technical curriculum</a>, that is a helpful collection of free resources from <a href="https://www.cloudskillsboost.google/paths/183" target="_blank">Google</a>, <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/training/paths/copilot/" target="_blank">Microsoft</a> and <a href="https://explore.skillbuilder.aws/learn/course/external/view/elearning/17256/planning-a-generative-ai-project" target="_blank">AWS</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p>Check out all the resources in the <a href="https://nhsd-confluence.digital.nhs.uk/display/DAT/Training+Brochure" target="_blank">Training Brochure</a>! Can you spot something missing? Contact <a href="mailto:datascience@nhs.net">Harriet Sands</a>.</p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<p><a href="https://forms.office.com/e/JJsmgPmVVJ" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-success btn-lg">Subscribe (nhs.net login)</a><a href="https://github.com/nhsengland/datascience-pd-newsletter/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=&amp;projects=&amp;template=suggest-some-newsletter-content-.md&amp;title=" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">Contribute</a><a href="./newsletter.pdf" class="btn-action-primary btn-action btn btn-info btn-lg" target="_blank">PDF Version</a></p>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>newsletter</category>
  <category>delivery</category>
  <guid>https://nhsengland.github.io/datascience-pd-newsletter/posts/2024_01/newsletter.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
